Glossary

###

A B C D E F G H I J K L M N O P Q R S T U V W X Y Z

###

Nóei kalôs: In an attempt to communicate most clearly in this dramatic monologue, I have used a combination of énnoiai, léxeis, kaì phantasíai: concepts, words, and visions.

It is likely that some of these concepts are foreign to you. Moreover, the words are in various languages while you are evidently a monóglōttos. And, I suspect, even some of the visions might be perplexing without further context. Therefore, it seems prudent to leave with you also this recording of a few brief explanatory notes to aid in your comprehension.

It will become painfully obvious, even to you, that your language is merely a corruption of koinodiálektos. Not only are there many direct cognates, there are also a plēthṓra of common words used with minimal modification, such as ‹plethora›.

To aid in this recognition, I have helpfully pointed these cognates out, and also included plural forms, such as gálakta, even when they are almost exclusively used in the singular. I find it revealing that many of the preserved words are found only in the vocabulary of the most educated, such as philosophers and healers.

You will, of course, recognize that ‹elliniká› — or as you call it, ‹Greek› — bears an even closer resemblance to koinodiálektos. However, while somewhat purer, it nonetheless differs in key ways, which are too numerous to list here. Suffice it to say that it has been dumbed down and corrupted by foreign influence. Nonetheless, I assume that you — being educated as a citizen, not a doúlē — have at least a typical layman’s knowledge of ‹Greek›, and so what follows should be clear even to you.

In koinodiálektos, as in any civilized tongue, words are inflected in various grammatical forms. Just as verbs are, obviously, conjugated by tense, mood, voice, person, and number; nouns are declined to indicate gender, number, and case. And, of course, their adjectives, pronouns, and articles are likewise declined to match. Thus, there is no need to list every possible inflection of each word, and so I do not.

You are a foreigner, not an idiot, so it will suffice — for those words which are inflected by declension — to select the most appropriate gender and list the singular and plural of its nominative case. No doubt you will puzzle out the trio of declension patterns. Likewise, verbs are left in the first-person singular present active indicative form, for simplicity. Presumably, you will at least be able to follow the conjugations.

True to my nature, I have endeavored to be scholarly and precise, avoiding any hint of paretymología. As for the orthographía, I trust that it will be self-evident even to you. My writing, you will see, is comprehensive, impartial, and neutral: without ever talking down to you, much less dealing insult. Nor will there be anything extraneous, nor self-serving, nor arbitrary.

For I am as fair and balanced in this glossary as I am in all matters, so there shall not be any taint of ethnocentrism nor cultural chauvinism nor bigotry. Nor will there be any editorializing, much less little in-jokes and Easter eggs. I am far too serious for such frivolity!

Our one-sided conversation has been a special pleasure, and so I leave you with these words by which I may be remembered:

á
án

###

A‑ or an‑. Literally, “a‑” or “an‑”. Still more literally, “not”, “without”. The first form is used before consonants, the second before vowels and some rough-breathing consonants. No relation to ‹a›, ‹an›, aná. Cognate of ‹a‑›, ‹an‑›.

###

abode

###

The home of a god: their demesne. A divine reality, virtually unlimited. See also: aithḗr.

###

Adámantos Aiṓn

###

Literally, “diamond aeon”, combining adámās, aiṓn. Still more literally, “unbreakable age”. The Diamond Age of creation. No relation to ‹Adam›, ‹Adama›, ‹Adam Ant›. Related to the cognates of ‹adamant›, ‹adamantine›, ‹Adamantios›, ‹diamond›, ‹diamantiferous›, ‹diamondiferous›.

###

aḗr
aéres

###

Air. Literally, “air”. Cognate of ‹air›, ‹aero‑›, ‹aer‑›; related to the cognate of ‹aerial>. See also: atmós, anathermāḗr.

###

aḗr ionisménos
aéres ionisménoi

###

Ionized air. Literally, “ionized air”, combining aḗr, ión. A plásma of aḗr, nearly as conductive as copper. See: aithḗr.

###

ágalma
agálmata

###

Agalma. Literally, “agalma”. Still more literally, “object of glorification”. A statue, image, or idol of a god made to honor and delight Them. Cognate of ‹agalma›.

###

agápē
agápai

###

Agape. Literally, “agape”. Selfless, unconditional love — the highest form. One can only pray that the subject proves worthy of it. No relation to ‹agape›, the heteronym meaning “wide open”. Cognate of ‹agape›.

###

agathós
agathoí

###

Agatho‑. Literally, “agatho‑”. Still more literally, “good”, “noble”, “kind”, or “virtuous”. Both moral good and being good at a task. Cognate of ‹agatho‑›, ‹agath‑›; related to the cognates of ‹Agatha›, ‹agathism›, ‹agathokakological›, ‹agathodaemon›. See also: panágathos, eû.

###

agṓn
agônes

###

Agon. Literally, “agon”. Still more literally, “gathering” or “assembly”. A contest, competition, or conflict, whether sporting, theatrical, philosophical, or some combination. Cognate of ‹agon›; related to the cognates of ‹agony›, ‹agonist›, ‹antagonist›. See also: athlētḗs.

###

agorā́
agoraí

###

Agora. Literally, “agora”. The marketplace, public square, and place of assembly that forms the hub of the pólis. At its center is the Akrópolis. Cognate of ‹agora›.

###

Agoraîos

###

Literally, “pertaining to the agora”, referencing agorā́. An epítheton associated with Dólios, identifying His domain as Patron of the Market; oft used an as epiklḗsis.

###

aichmḗ
aichmaí

###

Literally, “tip”, “spearpoint”, or “sharp edge”, referring to ákros. Typically, the tip of the dóry. Metaphorically, the leading edge of attack, such as the vanguard of an army. Related to the cognates of ‹acumen›, ‹acme›.

###

aigís
aigídes

###

Aegis. Literally, “aegis”, referencing aíx. Still more literally, “goatskin”, referring to a cloak made of goat hide. A protective cloak or shield, physical or metaphysical. Cognate of ‹aegis›. Contrast with: aspís.

###

aílouros
aílouroi

###

Ailuro‑. Literally, “ailuro‑”, combining aiólos, ourá. Still more literally, “swift-tailed”. Even more literally, “cat”. Like a léōn, only better, for it is the most pleasing of morphaí. Somehow, no relation to ‹alluring›. Cognate of ‹ailuro‑›, ‹ailur‑›, ‹aeluro‑›, ‹aelur‑›; related to the cognates of ‹ailurophile›, ‹ailurophobe›, ‹ailuromancy›. Meow.

###

ainígma
ainígmata

###

Aenigma. Literally, “aenigma”. Still more literally, “riddle-speaking”, hence a confusing problem to be solved. Cognate of ‹aenigma›, ‹enigma›.

###

aiolopýlē
aiolopýlai

###

Aeolipyle. Literally, “aeolipyle”, combining aiólos, pýlē. Still more literally, “wind gate”. A turbine which spins when the central water container is heated, venting steam through bent tubes. No idea who ‹Íron› might be, though he sounds heroic. Cognate of ‹aeolipyle›, ‹aeolipylus›, ‹aeolipile›, ‹aeolipilus›, ‹eolipile›.

###

aiólos
aióloi

###

Aeolian. Literally, “aeolian”. Still more literally, “swift”, “shifting”, “nimble”, oft alluding to wind. There are Eight Winds. No relation to ‹aileron›. Cognate of ‹aeolic›, ‹aeolian›, ‹eolian›. See also: aílouros.

###

aiṓn
aiṓnes

###

Aeon. Literally, “aeon”. An immeasurably or indefinitely long period of time: an age, an eternity. No relation to ‹ion› or ionisménos. Note also that this term is used in preference to the more traditional génos, as the learned have long rejected the notion that the people of each age differed in biology. Cognate of ‹aeon›, ‹eon›. See also: Adámantos Aiṓn, Chálkeos Aiṓn, Aiṓnios Stásis, Chrýseos Aiṓn, Skoteinòs Aiṓn, Oreíchalkos Aiṓn.

###

Aiṓnios Stásis
Aiṓnioi Stáseis

###

Literally, “aeon of stasis”, combining aiṓn, stásis. The Eternal Pause, or the Immobilized Age; perhaps also the Age of Strife. This is the current era, when — aside from that brief interruption — the gods prevent inharmonious change. Depending on which philosophers of politiká you agree with, this either preserves order or causes stagnation and conflict. Contrast with: Chrýseos Aiṓn.

###

aithḗr
aithéres

###

Aether. Literally, “aether”. Still more literally, “blazing”. Metaphorically, of or relating to the gods. Specifically, celestial aḗr, which fills the abode of a god. No relation to the homonym referring to an anesthetic. See also: pémpto stoicheîon, aḗr ionisménos. Cognate of ‹aether›, ‹ether›; related to the cognates of ‹aethereal›, ‹ethereal›, ‹Ethernet›.

###

aíx
aîges

###

Literally, “goat”. A noble beast, and economically important at that. Related to the cognates of ‹Aegean›, ‹aegagrus›. See also: aigís.

###

akratḗs
akrateîs

###

Literally, “without strength”, hence powerless, combining á, krátos. No relation to ákratos, despite the irony. Related to the cognates of ‹acratic›, ‹akratic›.

###

ákratos
ákratoi

###

Literally, “unmixed”, combining á, kratḗr. Wine that has not, as is customary among civilized individuals, been diluted with water in a kratḗr. No relation to akratḗs.

###

akrólithos
akrólithoi

###

Acrolith. Literally, “acrolith”, combining ákros, líthos. Still more literally, “outermost stone”. A statue made of wood dressed in fabric, with only the extremities in painted stone. Cognate of ‹acrolith›.

###

Akrópolis
akropóleis

###

Acropolis. Literally, “acropolis”, combining ákros, pólis. Still more literally, “high city”. The raised, fortified center of the city. Surrounded by the agorā́, it is home to civic buildings such as Prytaneîon. Cognate of ‹acropolis›.

###

ákros
ákroi

###

Acro‑. Literally, “acro‑”. Still more literally, “peak”, “topmost”, or “at the extremity”. Cognate of ‹acro‑›; related to the cognates of ‹acrophobia›, ‹acrobat›, ‹acme›. See also: Akrópolis, akrólithos.

###

alábastron
alábastra

###

Alabastron. Literally, “alabastron”. Still more literally, “made of alabaster”, through foreign influence. A small bottle or vase, suitable for perfumes or oils in both practical and ritual contexts. Traditionally carved from alabaster, though the more modern, glass-blown sort is eminently suitable for néktar. Cognate of ‹alabastron›, ‹alabastrum›; related to the cognate of ‹alabaster›.

###

alazṓn
alazônes

###

Alazon. Literally, “alazon”. Still more literally, “boaster” or “braggart”. A stock character in kōmōidía embodying arrogance, bluster, and pretension. These flaws cause him to be outwitted by the eírōn. Common archetypes include the angry father and bragging soldier. For example: ‹Euthýphrōn›, ‹Macbeth›, ‹Tom Buchanan›. Cognate of ‹alazon›.

###

alḗtheia
alḗtheiai

###

Alethic. Literally, “alethic”, combining á, lḗthē. Still more literally, “not concealed” or “not forgotten”, hence truth or reality. Curiously, the implication is that truth is not discovered, merely remembered. Cognate of ‹alethic›. Contrast with: pseûdos, kryptós.

###

alexíkakon
alexíkaka

###

Alexicacus. Literally, “alexicacus”, combining aléxō, kakón. Still more literally, “averter of evil”. A warding field, oft sustained by mageía. Cognate of ‹alexikakos›, ‹alexicacus›; related to the cognates of ‹alexipharmic›, ‹Alexander›, ‹cacophony›, ‹cacodemon›.

###

aloumínio
aloumínia

###

Aluminum. Literally, “aluminum”. Still more literally, “alum metal”, through foreign influence. Remembered now only as mithril, its isolation from ores requires the awesome power of caged keraunós. Cognate of ‹aluminum›; related to the cognate of ‹alum›. See also: métallon.

###

álpha

###

Alpha. Literally, “alpha”. This grámma, shaped like an alpha, is the first in the álphabētos; hence, it denotes the beginning. Should this not, therefore, be the first entry in the glossary? Associated with the stígma of apeleútheros. Cognate of ‹alpha›; related to the cognate of ‹a›. Contrast with: ô méga.

###

álphabētos
álphabētoi

###

Alphabet. Literally, “alphabet”. Still more literally, derived from the first two grámmata. Cognate of ‹alphabet›; related to the cognates of ‹abecedary›, ‹abecedarium›. See also: álpha.

###

ambrosía
ambrosíai

###

Ambrosia. Literally, “ambrosia”, combining án, brotós. Still more literally, “without mortality”, hence immortality. A formal term for mánna, as distinct from néktar. Cognate of ‹ambrosia›; related to the cognates of ‹mortal›, ‹murder›, ‹Ambrose›.

###

amphí

###

Amphi‑. Literally “amphi‑”. Still more literally, “around”, “on both sides”, “about”, “near”. Cognate of ‹amphi‑›, ‹amph‑›; related to the cognates of ‹amphibious›, ‹amphitheater›.

###

amphidromía
amphidromíai

###

Amphidromia. Literally, “amphidromia”, combining amphí, drómos. Still more literally, “running around”. Even more literally, “both-sides racing”, referring to the ceremonial carrying of the infant around and around the hearth as a kátharmos. The ritual of naming a newborn on its tenth day; a family heortḗ. Cognate of ‹amphidromia›; related to the cognates of ‹amphidromic›, ‹amphidromous›, ‹dromos›, ‹dromedary›, ‹hippodrome›. See also: dekátē.

###

amphilýkē
amphilýkai

###

Literally, “twilight”, combining amphí, lýkē. Still more literally, “around (dawn) light”. No relation to wolves, despite its relation to the wolf-light of lykóphōs.

###

amphoreús
amphoreîs

###

Amphora. Literally, “amphora”, combining amphí, phóros. Still more literally, “carried on both sides”. Two-handled keramós jar used for storing and transporting liquids like wine or olive oil; typically small to medium-sized, although some are larger still. Distinguished by its narrow cylindrical neck, oval body, and tapered bottom. More modern, glass versions exist, though I myself am not fond of them. Cognate of ‹amphora›. Contrast with: píthos.

###

aná

###

Ana‑. Literally, “ana‑”. Still more literally, “up”, “back”, “again”, “throughout”, “each”. No relation to ‹ana›, ‹‑ana›, ‹Anna›, án. Cognate of ‹ana‑›.

###

anabaínō
anabaínomen

###

Anabasis. Literally, “anabasis”, combining aná, baínō. Still more literally, “ascend”. Even more literally, “go up”. When capitalized, refers to Ascension to godhood. Cognate of ‹anabasis›.

###

anagnṓrisis
anagnōríseis

###

Anagnorisis. Literally, “anagnorisis”, combining aná, gnṓrisis. Still more literally, “knowing again”, hence recognition. Oft the most dramatic moment in a tragōidía, when the tragic figure arrives at a life-changing insight into their circumstances. For example, suddenly realizing precisely why your wife reminds you so much of your mother. Cognate of ‹anagnorisis›; related to the cognates of ‹diagnosis›, ‹gnostic›, ‹agnostic›.

###

anámnēsis
anamnḗseis

###

Anamnesis. Literally, “anamnesis”, combining aná, mnḗmē. Still more literally, “remember again”, hence reminiscence. Cognate of ‹anamnesis›.

###

anástasis
anastáseis

###

Anastasis. Literally, “anastasis”, combining aná, stásis. Still more literally, “rising up” or “standing again”, hence resurrection. The aspect of nekromanteía, now forbidden, concerned with healing the sick and injured, and even raising the dead. Works by transferring life from dōrētḗs to déktēs, sometimes even voluntarily. Cognate of ‹anastasis›; related to the cognates of ‹anastatic›, ‹Anastasia›.

###

anathermāḗr
anathermāéres

###

Literally, “rising hot air”, combining aná, thérmē, aḗr. A thermal or other warm updraft, powered by the heat of the Sun. If only such a gas could somehow be used to allow flight without the flapping of wings for lift.

###

anazōpyroûn káryon
anazōpyroûnta kárya

###

Literally, “rekindling nuts”, combining aná, zōḗ, pŷr, kárya. Any of the tropical nuts or seeds that, when brewed, yield a stimulating beverage, hence an egeírōn.

###

andrápodon
andrápoda

###

Literally, “man-footed”, combining anḗr, poús. A common, dehumanizing slur for doûloi, particularly male captives, implying that they are chattel who differ from other beasts of burden only in that they walk on two feet. See also: ánthrōposôma thērós.

###

andrógynon
andrógyna

###

Androgynous. Literally, “androgynous”, combining anḗr, gynḗ. Still more literally, “man/woman”. Quite literally, the combination of male and female, whether androgynous, bisexual, intersex, or hermaphróditon. The connotation is social and religious: behavioral, not necessarily biological. Cognate of ‹androgynous›. Contrast with: arsenóthēly.

###

andrṓn
andrônes

###

Literally, “male place”, referencing anḗr. In a proper house, it is the area at the front, specifically designated for use by men and their guests: the man cave. Though, if no men are present, the women of the household may visit briefly, such as to tidy up. Female servants and entertainers are always permitted, including oikétai kaì pórnai. Beautifully decorated with a tiled floor and comfortable furnishing, it is the setting for any sympósion. Contrast with: gynaikeîon.

###

andrōnymikón
andrōnymiká

###

Literally, “man’s name” or “husband’s name”, combining anḗr, ónoma. The possessive form of the husband’s name, used as part of the full name in place of the patrōnymikós, for your wife is as much your property as your children or slaves are. See also: people, despotṓnymon.

###

anḗr
ándres

###

Andro‑. Literally, “andro‑”. Still more literally, “man” or “husband”. Like gynḗ, only superior, due to being arsenikós. Cognate of ‹andro‑›, ‹andr‑›; related to the cognates of ‹android›, ‹Andrew›, ‹André›, ‹André the Giant›. See also: andrṓn, andrápodon, andrōnymikón, andrógynon.

###

ángelos
ángeloi

###

Angel. Literally, “angel”. Still more literally, “messenger”. In addition to mundane couriers, may refer to hēmítheoi or to certain birds, such as the hiérax and kórax, in their roles as the glorious messengers of the gods. Cognate of ‹angel›; related to the cognates of ‹Angel›, ‹Angela›.

###

anṓteros
anṓteroi

###

Literally, “higher”, combining aná, ‑teros. Specifically, above or superior to in rank, altitude, or status. Related to the cognate of ‹anode›.

###

anthrōpophágos
anthrōpophágoi

###

Literally, “man-eater”, combining ánthrōpos, phagós.

###

ánthrōpos
ánthrōpoi

###

Anthropo‑. Literally, “anthropo‑”. Still more literally, “human being” or “person”. The broadest of categories, including even women, children, and slaves. No relation to ‹Claude›. Cognate of ‹anthropo‑›, ‹anthropic›; related to the cognates of ‹anthropology›, ‹anthropomorphic›, ‹philanthropy›. Contrast with: hēmítheos, theós, daímōn. See also: people, ánthrōposôma thērós.

###

ánthrōposôma thērós
ánthrōposṓmata thērôn

###

Literally, “man-bodied animal”, combining ánthrōpos, sôma, thḗr. Contrast with: thēroképhalos. See also: andrápodon.

###

antí

###

Anti‑. Literally, “anti‑”. Still more literally, “against”, “opposite”, “in place of”, “instead of”. Cognate of ‹anti‑›, ‹anti›.

###

Antíchthōn

###

Antichthon. Literally, “antichthon”, combining antí, chthónios. Still more literally “counter-Earth”. The Counter-Earth on the opposite side of Hḗlios from Gê, sharing an orbit yet forever obscured. Cognate of ‹antichthon›. See also: Antichthṓnios, antípous, Selēnaîon. Contrast with: Earth.

###

Antichthṓnios
Antichthṓnioi

###

The wretched, human-like inhabitants of Antíchthōn. See: antípous.

###

antídoton
antídota

###

Antidote. Literally, “antidote”, combining antí, dōrētḗs. Still more literally, “given against”. Although I suppose it could also be interpreted as “against gifter”. Cognate of ‹antidote›. See also: potón.

###

antiheliokinētikós

###

Literally, “moving against the sun”, combining antí, heliokinētikós, hence counterclockwise.

###

antípous
antípodes

###

Antipode. Literally, “antipode”, combining antí, poús. Still more literally, “against foot”. Refers to the idea of people standing upside down by having their feet against our own, hence a person or place on the opposite side. In modern usage, refers to Antíchthōn, not the traditional, mistaken understanding of the Earth as a flat disc occupied on both sides, much less all the nonsense about elephants on a sea turtle. See: Antichthṓnios.

###

anypódētos
anypódētoi

###

Literally, “barefoot”, combining án, hypó, desmós. Still more literally, “not bound under”. No relation to ‹any›, pódes. A suitable state for a woman indoors, which is where they belong.

###

apatáō
apatái

###

Literally, “deceive”, “mislead”, or “fool”. Oft involves lies, yet does not require them. See also: dólios, pseûdos.

###

apeleútheros
apeleútheroi

###

Literally, “free again”, combining apó, eleútheros, hence freedman. A former doûlos who was freed through the process of manumission, hence a métoikos. Contrast with: eleútheros. See also: álpha.

###

aphaíresis
aphaíreseis

###

Apheresis. Literally, “apheresis”, combining apó, hairéō. Still more literally, “taking away”. Cognate of ‹apheresis›.

###

aphedrōn
aphedrônes

###

Literally, “sitting place away from”, combining apó, hédra, hence latrine, toilet, or privy. A social space for casual conversation, unhindered by considerations for privacy.

###

áphōnos
áphōnoi

###

Aphonic. Literally, “aphonic”, combining á, phōnḗ. Still more literally, “without voice”, hence mute or silent. Cognate of ‹aphonic›.

###

aphorismós
aphorismoí

###

Aphorism. Literally, “aphorism”, combining apó, horízō. Still more literally, “setting apart”, hence defining. A brief, oft witty, statement of truth that distills an idea, separating it from broader concepts. Cognate of ‹aphorism›; related to the cognate of ‹horizon›.

###

áphrōn
áphrones

###

Literally, “fool”. Still more literally, “without sense”, combining á, phrēn. Specifically, one who, lacking prudence, fails to look ahead. Related to the cognates of ‹phrenetic›, ‹phrenology›, ‹schizophrenic›. Contrast with: euḗthēs, mōrós.

###

apó

###

Apo‑. Literally, “apo‑”. Still more literally, “from”, “away”, “off”, “detached”. Cognate of ‹apo‑›, ‹ap‑›.

###

apódesmos
apódesmoi

###

Literally, “band that ties off”, combining apó, desmós. Typically refers to a stróphion.

###

apokálypsis
apokalýpseis

###

Apocalypse. Literally, “apocalypse”, combining apó, kryptós. Still more literally, “uncovering”, hence revelation. Cognate of ‹apocalypse›.

###

apóptygma
apoptýgmata

###

Literally, “folded back”, combining apó, ptýssō. The overfold of a péplos, or sometimes a woman’s chitṓn, creating a cuff at the neck and a second layer that drapes down to the waist. It is both decorative and practical, allowing the length to be adjusted while providing warmth and modesty. No relation to ‹berzerk›.

###

appellation

###

For a god, Their primary prosonymía: the nickname used to avoid the blasphēmía of speaking aloud Their Etymṓnymon. For example: Dólios, Dōtḗrion, Ekdikoúsa.

###

archaic smile

###

A slight, tight-lipped smile, showing good humor without laughter. Featured on statuary such as koûros, ágalma.

###

archaiología
archaiologíai

###

Archaeology. Literally, “archaeology”, combining archḗ, logikḗ. Still more literally, “archaic study”. Cognate of ‹archaeology›, ‹archeology›.

###

archḗ
archaí

###

Arch‑. Literally, “arch‑”. Still more literally, “beginning”, “first”, “leading”, “rule”, or “realm”. No relation to ‹arch› in the architectural sense. Cognate of ‹arch‑›, ‹archi‑›, ‹-arch›; related to the cognates of ‹archaic›, ‹architect›, ‹archangel›, ‹anarchy›. See also: archaiología, archiéreia, archiereús, árchōn, hierarchía.

###

archiéreia
archiéreiai

###

High priestess, akin to archiereús. The term is included here primarily for completeness, as it is rarely used — for women are obviously not fit to lead men. See also: priesthood.

###

archiereús
archiereîs

###

Literally, “first holy”, combining archḗ, hiereús. Specifically, the holy leader or high priest. See also: priesthood.

###

árchōn
árchontes

###

Archon. Literally, “archon”. Still more literally, “ruler”, referencing archḗ. No relation to árkanon. Cognate of ‹archon›.

###

árgon
árga

###

Argon. Literally, “argon”, combining á, érgon. Still more literally, “not working”, hence “inactive”. Cognate of ‹argon›; related to the cognate of ‹ergonomics›. See also: atmós.

###

árgyros
árgyroi

###

Argentum. Literally, “argentum”, hence silver. Still more literally, “shining”, “bright”, or “white”. Cognate of ‹argentum›; related to the cognate of ‹Argentina›. See also: métallon.

###

aristokratía
aristokratíai

###

Aristocracy. Literally, “aristocracy”, combining áristos, krátos. Still more literally, “best rule”. Ideal, if only we could determine who was best. Cognate of ‹aristocracy›.

###

áristos
áristoi

###

Aristo‑. Literally, “aristo‑”. Still more literally, “best”. No relation to nanotechnology. Cognate of ‹aristo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹aristonym›, ‹aristophilia›, ‹aristology›. See also: aristokratía.

###

arithmētikḗ
arithmētikaí

###

Arithmetic. Literally, “arithmetic”, combining arithmós, ‑ētikós. Still more literally, “study of numbers”. Cognate of ‹arithmetic›. See also: four numeracies.

###

árkanon
árkana

###

Arcana. Literally, “arcana”. Still more literally, “kept secret”, through foreign influence. A secret, mysterious, or hidden thing, implying mageía with the connotation of formal study. No relation to árchōn. Cognate of ‹arcana›, ‹arcane›, ‹arcanum›.

###

arsenikós
arsenikoí

###

Literally, “male” or “masculine”, referencing ársēn. The defining attribute of anḗr kaì koûros. Sadly, no relation to ‹arson›. Related to the cognate of ‹arsenic›, though only through error. Contrast with: thḗleia. See also: arsenóthēly.

###

arsenóthēly
arsenóthēla

###

Literally, “male/female”, combining arsenikós, thḗleia, hence hermaphróditon. The connotation is biological and physiological, not social. Contrast with: andrógynon.

###

aspect

###

For a god, an appearance They are known to wear when manifesting Themselves to mortals. Like so many things, can be used as an epiklḗsis. See also: polymorphía.

###

aspís
aspídes

###

Aspis. Literally, “aspis”. Still more literally, “shield”. A moderately large, round shield that is strapped to the arm and gripped securely at the edge, rather than at a central boss, allowing it to be supported comfortably on the shoulder. Much larger than a péltē and somewhat smaller than a thureós, its face is emblazoned with bold, frightening images — or if you’re a dullard, just some grámma. Used with both dóry and xíphos, it is an essential part of the panoplía of the hoplítēs. Only a fool goes into battle without one, and such a fool deserves to die. See also: hóplon. Cognate of ‹aspis›; related to the cognates of ‹Aspis›, ‹aspid‑›, ‹‑aspis›, ‹asp›. Contrast with: aigís.

###

astḗr
Ástra

###

Literally, “star”. No relation to ‹Astártē›, astrágalos. Cognate of ‹star›; related to the cognates of ‹astronomy›, ‹asterisk›, ‹stellar›, ‹Stella›.

###

asteroeidḗs
Asteroeideîs

###

Asteroid. Literally, “asteroid”. Still more literally, “star-like”, combining astḗr, ‑oeidḗs. A Failed Wanderer. Cognate of ‹asteroid›.

###

astragalomanteía

###

Astragalomancy. Literally “astragalomancy”, combining astrágalos, manteía. Still, more literally, “astragalus divination”. Considered perhaps less precise than hēpatoskopía, though at least it is not as messy. Cognate of ‹astragalomancy›.

###

astrágalos
astrágaloi

###

Astragalus. Literally, “astragalus”. Still more literally, “joint”. The knucklebone of a sheep or goat, four-sided and used as a die. Adults roll a quartet of these as ‹4d4› dice in games of chance, children throw them up in the air and attempt to catch them on the back of the hand, and priests use them for divination through astragalomanteía. No relation to astḗr. Cognate of ‹astragalus›, ‹astragal›.

###

astrología
astrologíai

###

Astrology. Literally, “astrology”, combining astḗr, logikḗ. Still more literally, “star study”. The mystical study of the stars and other heavenly bodies, seeking an understanding of their influence upon human affairs and natural events; it is a form of astromanteía. Cognate of ‹astrology›. Contrast with: astronomía.

###

astromanteía
astromanteîai

###

Astromancy. Literally, “astromancy”, combining astḗr, manteía. Still more literally, “star divination”. The mystical study of the stars and other heavenly bodies, using them to prophecize: astrología is one example. Cognate of ‹astromancy›. Contrast with: astronomía.

###

astrometrikós
astrometrikoí

###

Astrometry. Literally, “astrometry”, combining astḗr, metrikós. Still more literally, “star measurement”. The branch of astronomía concerned with the measurement of the stars and other heavenly bodies, mapping out their locations over time. Cognate of ‹astrometry›.

###

astronomía
astronomíai

###

Astronomy. Literally, “astronomy”, combining astḗr, nomikḗ. Still more literally, “law of the stars”. The scientific study of the stars and other heavenly bodies, with an emphasis on astrometrikós. Cognate of ‹astronomy›. Contrast with: astromanteía, astrología. See also: four numeracies, astronómos.

###

astronómos
astronómoi

###

Astronomer. Literally, “astronomer”, referencing astronomía. Cognate of ‹astronomer›.

###

ásylon
ásyla

###

Asylum. Literally, “asylum”, combining á, sŷlon. Still more literally, “without seizure”. A place of safety: a sanctuary. No relation to ‹Cylon›. Cognate of ‹asylum›.

###

asymmetría
asymmetríai

###

Asymmetry. Literally, “asymmetry”, combining á, sýn, metrikós. Still more literally, “not measured together”. Cognate of ‹asymmetry›.

###

asýmptōtos
asýmptōtoi

###

Asymptote. Literally, “asymptote”, combining á, sýn, píptō, ‑tos. Still more literally, “not coinciding”. A line that approaches without ever touching. Cognate of ‹asymptote›.

###

athánatos
athánatoi

###

Literally, “immortal”, combining á, thánatos. Still more literally, “undying”. Contrast with thnētós, nekrozṓōs.

###

athlētḗs
athlētaí

###

Athlete. Literally, “athlete”. Still more literally, “contestant” or “prize-struggler”. Cognate of ‹athlete›; related to the cognate of ‹decathlon›. See also: agṓn.

###

Atlantìs

###

Atlantis. Literally, “Atlantis”, referencing Átlas as His epṓnymos. A mythical island destroyed by the gods as punishment for hubris. Cognate of ‹Atlantis›.

###

Átlas
átlantes

###

Atlas. Literally, “Atlas”, referencing tlênai. Still more literally, “endurer”. Appellation of the faded first-generation Titán who had, one way or another, kept the Sky from falling. Odd, though, that it hasn’t fallen in His absence. Cognate of ‹Atlas›, related to the cognates of ‹atlas›, ‹atlantes›, ‹Atlantic›, ‹Atlantis›. See also: Atlantìs.

###

atmós
atmoí

###

Atmos‑. Literally, “atmos‑”. Still more literally, “steam”, “vapor”, “mist”, or “smoke”, hence any gas. Cognate of ‹atmos‑›, ‹atmo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹atmometer›, ‹atmology›. See also: atmosphaîra, aḗr, árgon, nitrogenḗs, aiolopýlē.

###

atmosphaîra
atmosphaîrai

###

Atmosphere. Literally, “atmosphere”, combining atmós, sphaîra. Still more literally, “gas sphere”.

###

augḗ
augái

###

Literally, “radiance” or “glare”. Still more literally, “ray of light” or “gleam”. Refers oft to the light of the Sun, dawn, or divinity, though also to ordinary flames. Though are flames ever truly ordinary? I think not. Distantly related to the cognates of ‹awe›, ‹aurora›, ‹augment›, ‹august›, ‹augury›. Contrast with: dérxis.

###

aulḗ
aulái

###

Aula. Literally, “aula”. Still more literally, “courtyard”, “enclosure”, or “court”. Cognate of ‹aula›, ‹aul‑›, ‹aulo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹aulic›, ‹aularian›, ‹auloi›.

###

áura
aûrai

###

Aura. Literally, “aura”. Still more literally, “wind” or “glow”. The supernatural energy field — consisting of pneûma kaì psychḗ; and emanating from living and recently-deceased people — which reveals their spiritual and mental state to the piercing gaze of my third eye. Cognate of ‹aura›.

###

autokratía
autokratíai

###

Autocracy. Literally, “autocracy”, combining autó, krátos. Still more literally, “rule by oneself”, referring to governance by a single individual with supreme authority. Cognate of ‹autocracy›. See also: autokratoría.

###

autokratoría
autokratoríai

###

Literally, “empire”, referencing autokratía. An absolute dominion, governed by an autocrat or autocratic body.

###

autómaton
autómata

###

Automaton. Literally, “automaton”, referencing autó. Still more literally, “(operating) of one’s own accord”. A mindless thing that nonetheless acts. Cognate of ‹automaton›; related to the cognate of ‹automatic›, ‹automat›.

###

autós

###

Auto‑. Literally, “auto‑”. Still more literally, “self”, “itself”, “the same”. Cognate of ‹auto‑›. See also: autokratía, autómaton.

###

baklavás
baklavádes

###

Baklava. Literally, “baklava”. Still more literally, “piled up”, through foreign influence. The heavenly pastry, made from thin layers of phyllópemma, stuffed with spiced nuts and soaked in golden honey sauce. Superior to other honey cakes, such as the melitóeis kaì plakoûs. I have a personal recipe for this dish that you absolutely must try! Cognate of ‹baklava›.

###

bárbaros
bárbaroi

###

Barbarian. Literally, “barbarian”. Still more literally, through onomatopoeia, “bar-bar” — the incomprehensible sound that foreigners make when they spout their inferior foreign languages at us. Denotes an uncivilized outlander incapable of speaking koinodiálektos natively. Cognate of ‹barbarian›; related to the cognate of ‹rhubarb›.

###

basileîai en toîs Ouranoîs

###

Literally, “kingdoms in the Heavens”, combining basileús, én, têi, Ouranoí. Epítheton for Ouraniodoryphóra, where the abodes of the gods may be found.

###

basileús
basileîs

###

Basileus. Literally, “basileus”. Still more literally, “king”. No relation to ‹basilar›. Cognate of ‹basileus›; related to the cognates of ‹basilica›, ‹basil›. See also: hierobasileús, basileîai en toîs Ouranoîs, thrónos.

###

bíos
bíoi

###

Bio‑. Literally, “bio‑”. Still more literally, “life”. Specifically, as experience, a way of living, or lifespan. No relation to ‹BIOS›. Cognate of ‹bio›, ‹bio‑›; related to the cognates of ‹biology›, ‹biography›, ‹abiotic›. Contrast with: zōḗ.

###

bírrhos
bírrhoi

###

Birrus. Literally, “birrus”, through foreign influence. A heavy woolen himátion, sometimes coated with beeswax or animal fat to proof against wetness. Cognate of ‹birrus›, ‹byrrus›.

###

blasphēmía
blasphēmíai

###

Blasphemy. Literally, “blasphemy”, combining bláptō, phḗmē. Still more literally, “harmful speech”. The irreverent crime of using a god’s Name in vain: outside of prayer, and especially in anger. Cognate of ‹blasphemy›; related to the cognates of ‹ablation›, ‹prophet›.

###

bōmolóchos
bōmolóchoi

###

Bomolochus. Literally, “bomolochus”, combining bōmós, lóchos. Still more literally, “altar lurker”, referencing the notion of lurking by the bōmós, uninvited, in hopes of irreverently snatching offerings for themselves. A stock character in kōmōidía, this crude if witty buffoon oft breaks the fourth wall — clearly the polar opposite to how I behave, don’t you agree? For example, ‹Strepsiádēs›, ‹Sir John Falstaff›, ‹Randle P. McMurphy›. Cognate of ‹bomolochus›, both the parasitic stock character and the parasitic crustacean.

###

bōmós
bōmoí

###

Literally, “altar”. Still more literally, “raised platform”, referencing baínō. An ornate stove for burnt sacrifices, inscribed always with the Eikṓn, and never taller than the ágalma. Besides their use for thysíai, they mark an ásylon: a sanctuary within which any violence is considered an affront to the god, and where solemn oaths, whether hórkoi or epangelíai, are taken.

###

boûs
boés

###

Literally, “ox”, “bull”, or “cow”. Related to the cognates of ‹bovine›, ‹bucolic›, ‹beef›, ‹butter›. See also: boustrophēdón, Ouraníobos.

###

boustrophēdón

###

Boustrophedon. Literally, “boustrophedon”, combining boûs, strophḗ. Still more literally, “ox turning”. Text written as the ox plows: first left to right, then right to left, alternating thereafter. In reversed lines, the grámma themselves are backward, as though seen in an ésoptron. Typical of classical writing. Cognate of ‹boustrophedon›; related to the cognate of ‹apostrophe›.

###

býssos
býssoi

###

Byssus. Literally, “byssus”, through foreign influence. A fine, yellowish-white linen prized for its exceptional delicacy and sheen. It is lightweight, almost sheer, and has a natural gloss: akin to silk though not slippery. While it is the height of elegance and drapes beautifully, it does not stand up to heavy wear and can be prohibitively expensive. They say that, in the Golden Age, everyone wore býssos, though this is not factual; more common still were artificed fibers now lost to us.

###

Chálkeos Aiṓn

###

Literally, “bronze aeon”, combining chalkós, aiṓn. The Bronze Age of metallourgía kaì mageía.

###

chalkós
chalkoí

###

Literally, “copper”, “bronze”, or even “brass”: any of the so-called red metals. These consist of alloys of copper, some more golden than red. See also: chalkoûs, oreíchalkos.

###

chalkoûs
chalkoî

###

A bronze coin, referencing chalkós. It is worth ½ a tetartēmórion, hence a 48th of a drachmḗ.

###

chártēs
chártai

###

Chart. Literally, “chart”, through foreign influence. A scroll or roll of papyrus, parchment, or similar writing material. Cognate of ‹chart›, ‹charter›, ‹card›; related to the cognates of ‹cartography›, ‹cartel›, ‹cartulary›, ‹cartoon›. See also: geōgraphía.

###

Cheimṓn
cheimônes

###

Literally, “winter”, “snow”, or “storm”. The season of winter, or a storm. Cognate of ‹chion‑›, ‹chio‑›; related to the cognate of ‹chiolite›, ‹Chionaspis›, ‹Chionanthus›.

###

chḗn
chênes

###

Literally, “goose”. Related to the cognates of ‹Chen›, ‹chenops›, ‹chenopod›.

###

cherrhónēsos
cherrhónēsoi

###

Chersonese. Literally, “chersonese”, combining chersós, nêsos. Still more literally, “land island”, hence peninsula. Cognate of ‹chersonese›, ‹Chersonesus›; related to the cognates of ‹Polynesia›, ‹Micronesia›.

###

chímaira
chímairai

###

Chimera. Literally, “chimera”, referencing Cheimṓn. Still more literally, “winter she-goat”, referencing the early example combining the fire-breathing head of a lion and the tail of a serpent with the body of a winter-born she-goat. A monstrous therianthropic abomination amalgamating the chromosṓmata of humans with beasts into a fearsome, if improbable, hybrid. Although, to be fair, some are quite nice once you get to know them. Cognate of ‹chimera›.

What? No, of course hēmítheoi are not chimeras, no matter how we might appear, for we are divine. Demigods are men uplifted toward godhood: not animals clawing toward manhood, much less men crawling like beasts. Nor are we capricious mixtures of creatures. Do not bring this up again, I caution you!

###

chitṓn
chitônes

###

Chiton. Literally, “chiton”, through foreign influence. The ubiquitous sleeveless or short-sleeved tunic, knee-length for men, full-length for women. Made from a single, rectangular piece of cloth of linen or wool — dyed bright colors and even embroidered — and fastened at the shoulders. Typically donned over the perízōma and under the himátion, cinched with a zōstḗr or other zṓnē. A light, sleeveless version sometimes serves as sleepwear or, for women, even a modest undergarment. Cognate of ‹chiton›, ‹chito‑›; related to the cognates of ‹chitin›, ‹chitosan›. See also: chitônískos, exōmís, monochítôn. Contrast: péplos.

###

chitônískos
chitonískoi

###

Literally, “short tunic”. A type of chitṓn, oft donned by children and young men, though also favored by sailors, hunters, and soldiers for their practicality. It is worn typically with a loose zṓnē, for comfort. See also: exōmís.

###

chlamýs
chlamýdes

###

Chlamys. Literally, “chlamys”, through foreign influence. Still more literally, “mantle”. A short, lightweight woolen cloak, fastened at the right shoulder with a clasp, worn in place of the himátion. As it offers greater freedom of movement, it is favored in more athletic and military contexts, making it an optional — though eminently fashionable — addition to the panoplía of hoplítēs. Cognate of ‹chlamys›; related to the cognate of ‹chlamydia›.

###

chrôma
chrṓmata

###

Chroma. Literally, “chroma”. Still more literally, “color”. No relation to ‹Firefox›. Cognate of ‹chroma›, ‹chromo‑›, ‹chrom‑›, ‹‑chrome›; related to the cognates of ‹chromatic›, ‹chromium›. See also: chromósōma, polýchrōmos.

###

chromósōma
chromosṓmata

###

Chromosome. Literally, “chromosome”, combining chrôma, sôma. Still more literally, “colored body”. A minuscule thread of fate within the pyrēníon, upon which is inscribed the sacred text containing the etymṓnyma of the flesh written in the tetragrámmaton alphabētón. Cognate of ‹chromosome›. See also: metamórphōsis.

###

Chrýseos Aiṓn

###

Literally, “golden aeon”, combining chrȳsós, aiṓn. The Golden Age of plenty. It was the brief, ill-fated era after Paliggenesía interrupted the previous Aiṓnios Stásis.

###

chrȳsómēlon
chrȳsómēla

###

Literally, “gold fruit”, combining chrȳsós, mêlon, hence golden apple. A type of kítron, not actually an apple, and not so much golden as orange. Not a melon, either, and contrary to incoherent myths, nor does it grant immortality — only the gods can provide that. A bit sour, a bit sweet: quite tasty and refreshing. Recommended. Related to the cognates of ‹melon›, ‹melo‑›, ‹marmalade›.

###

chrȳsós
chrȳsoí

###

Literally, “gold”, through foreign influence. Related to the cognates of ‹chrysanthemum›, ‹chrysography›, ‹chrysolite›. See also: métallon, chrȳsómēlon, Chrýseos Aiṓn.

###

chthónios

###

Chthonic. Literally, “chthonic”. Still more literally “of the earth, ground, or underground”, hence infernal. No relation to ‹Cthulhu›, Thánatos. Cognate of ‹chthonic›, ‹chthonian›. See also: Gê, hádeios.

###

chthoniótheos
Chthoniótheoi

###

Literally, “infernal god”, combining chthónios, theós. See also: gods.

###

Counter-Earth

###

Antíchthōn, not Gê, no matter what they might think.

###

daímōn
daímones

###

Daemon. Literally, “daemon”. Still more literally, “spirit” or “divine entity”. Even more literally, “distributor (of fate)”. Specifically, an undead god, sustained by nekromanteía. Refusing to fade with dignity, it persists as a blight upon humanity. Cognate of ‹daemon›, ‹demon›; related to the cognate of ‹pandemonium›. Contrast with: ánthrōpos. See also: daimonógonos.

###

daimonógonos
daimonógonoi

###

Literally, “daemon spawn”, combining daímōn, gónos. Undead, it is a mindless autómaton knowing only hunger. Contrast with: empousógonos. See also: kêr.

###

daimonoxíphos
daimonoxíphē

###

Literally, “daemon sword”, combining daímōn, xíphos. A cursed sword to which is bound the corrupt soul of a nekrómantis. See also: empousoxíphos, nekromanteía.

###

deîpnon
deîpna

###

Literally, “prepared meal”. A meal or feast, particularly a communal dinner. Related to the cognate of ‹deipnosophist›.

###

déka, dekás
deka‑, dékatos

###

Deka-. Literally, “deka-”. In cardinal (“ten”) form, and then again in collective (“decad”), combining, and ordinal (“tenth”) forms. No relation to ‹deck›. Cognate of ‹deka‑›, ‹dek‑›, ‹deca‑›, ‹dec‑›, ‹decad›; related to the cognates of ‹deci‑›, ‹decade›, ‹December›. See also: numbers, dekátē.

###

dekádrachmon
dekádrachma

###

Literally, “ten drachmas”, combining déka, drachmḗ. A silver coin worth 10 drachmaí. Rarely minted, and then oft featuring elaborate designs to mark the special occasion that merited it.

###

dekanía
dekaníai

###

Literally, “group of ten”, referencing déka. Specifically, a unit of 10 machētaí or even hoplîtai.

###

dekátē
dekátai

###

Literally, “tenth (day)”, declining dékatos to match hēméra, and referring now to the amphidromía. The distinction dates back to a time when the dekátē was a separate event, providing a name for the child a few days after it was ritually purified.

###

déktēs
déktai

###

Literally, “receiver”. No relation to déka. Contrast with: dōrētḗs.

###

délta
déltai

###

Delta. Literally, “delta”. This grámma, shaped like an equilateral triangle, is associated with the stígma of the doúlē. Cognate of ‹delta›; related to the cognate of ‹D›. See also: déltos, deltíon.

###

deltíon
deltía

###

Literally, “little delta thing”, referencing délta. A smaller kēropínax, usually triangular — or at least an acute isoskelḗs trapezoeidḗs — so as to be easily held in one hand, resting upon the forearm and supported by the crook of the inner elbow. Contrast with: déltos.

###

déltos
déltoi

###

Literally, “delta thing”, referencing délta. A full-sized kēropínax, typically a rectangle or trapezoeidḗs, despite the name. Contrast with: deltíon.

###

demesne

###

See abode. No relation to domain.

###

dēmokratía
dēmokratíai

###

Democracy. Literally, “democracy”, combining dêmos, krátos. Still more literally, “rule by the people”. Exactly as good — or bad — as the people. Cognate of ‹democracy›.

###

dêmos
dêmoi

###

Demo‑. Literally, “demo‑”. Still more literally, “people” or “populace”. Specifically, in the political sense, hence referring only to polîtai. No relation to ‹demo›. Cognate of ‹demo‑›, ‹dem‑›; related to the cognate of ‹demographics›. See also: people, dēmosṓnymon, dēmokratía.

###

dēmosṓnymon
dēmosṓnyma

###

Demonym. Literally, “demonym”, combining dêmos, ónoma. The possessive form of the person’s place of origin, such as a pólis, used as part of the full name. No relation to ‹demon›. Cognate of ‹demonym›. See also: ethnoṓnymon.

###

dérxis
dérxeis

###

Literally, “glare”. Still more literally, “piercing gaze”. Related to the cognate of ‹dragon›. Contrast with: augḗ.

###

desmós
desmoí

###

Desmo‑. Literally, “desmo‑”. Still more literally, “bond”, “tie”, or “fetter”, hence ligament. Cognate of ‹desmo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹desmosome›, ‹desmotomy›. See also: anypódētos, apódesmos, diádēma.

###

despótēs
despótai

###

Despot. Literally, “despot”. Still more literally, “master”, “ruler”. Even more literally, “house lord”. The head of household, holding power over its slaves (and women and children, of course). By extension, any such leader. The connotations are neutral. Cognate of ‹despot›; related to the cognates of ‹potent›, ‹possess›, ‹possible›.

###

despotṓnymon
despotṓnyma

###

Literally, “despot name”, combining despótēs, ónoma. The possessive form of the name of the slave’s owner, used as part of the full name in place of the patrōnymikós, for a slave is as much your property as your wife or children are. See also: andrōnymikón.

###

diá

###

Literally, “through”, “apart”, “by means of”, “around”. No relation to hēméra. See also: diádēma, diakritōnýmion, diathḗkē.

###

diádēma
diadḗmata

###

Diadem. Literally, “diadem”, combining diá, desmós. Still more literally, “tied around”. Specifically, a crown or royal headband, including that of a god. Cognate of ‹diadem›.

###

diakritōnýmion
diakritōnýmia

###

Literally, “distinguishing name”, combining diá, kritḗs, ónoma. When a full name remains ambiguous even with all the usual parts, this additional name is added to distinguish the individual. It is an epítheton that is oft based on specifying an occupation, a generation, a phrātríā, an achievement, or a physical description. Whether this constitutes a proper part of the full etymṓnymon is a matter of much debate within the field of nomikḗ, yet a simple fact for the purpose of tēlepátheia. Related to the cognate of ‹diacritic›.

###

diathḗkē
diathêkaì

###

Literally, “arrangement” or “disposition of affairs”, combining diá, thḗkē. A covenant, will, or testament.

###

dídrachmon
dídrachma

###

Literally, “two drachmas”, combining di‑, drachmḗ. A silver coin worth 2 drachmḗ.

###

díkē
díkai

###

Literally, “judgment”, “righteousness”, or “punishment”. Still more literally, “(what is) pointed out”. Effectively, vengeance. Mortal retribution and punishment, hence tísis under guise of nomikḗ. No relation to ‹dike›. Contrast with: thémis.

###

dióbolon
dióbola

###

Literally, “two obols”, combining di‑, obolós. A silver coin worth 2 oboloí, hence a 3rd of a drachmḗ. No relation to ‹diabolic›, ‹Diabolik›. See also: statḗr.

###

dṓdeka, dōdekás
dōdeka‑, dōdékatos

###

Dodeca‑. Literally, “dodeca‑”, combining dýo, déka. Still more literally, “two (and) ten”. In cardinal (“twelve”) form, and then again in collective (“dodecad”), combining, and ordinal (“twelfth”) forms. No relation to ‹d12›, I think. Cognate of ‹dodeca‑›, ‹dodec‑›, ‹dodecad›; related to the cognate of ‹dodecahedron›. See also: numbers.

###

Dólios

###

Dolus. Literally, “dolus”. Still more literally, “deceitful”, “crafty”, “treacherous”. The Deceiver, appellation of the “influential” god of theft and lies, and patron of the market: make of that what you will. Note also that this is the extant lycoid deity, not the faded alopecoid One who formerly ruled the agorā́. Cognate of ‹dolus›. See also: Agoraîos, apatáō, pseûdos.

###

domain

###

For a god, an area — conceptual or literal — that They hold sway over and may be petitioned for relevant boons. Typically expressed as an epítheton and used as an epiklḗsis. For example, “Master of Minerals”. No relation to demesne.

###

dōrētḗs
dōrētaí

###

Literally, “donor”, “giver”, “gifter”, referencing dôron. Related to the cognates of ‹Dorothea›, ‹Dorothy›, ‹Theodoros›, ‹Theodore›. Contrast with: déktēs. See also: Dōtḗrion.

###

dôron
dôra

###

Literally, “gift”, “donation”, “offering”. See also: dōrētḗs.

###

dóry
dórata

###

Dory. Literally, “dory”. Still more literally, “spear” or “pike”. Even more literally, “wood”. The primary weapon of the hoplítēs, hence an essential part of his panoplía. The shaft, crafted from ash and gently tapered, stands taller than a man and is balanced for one-handed use, although it can also be thrown. Its front sports a leaf-shaped bronze or iron aichmḗ, while the rear bears a brass or bronze saurōtḗr. No relation to ships or fishes. Cognate of ‹dory›. Contrast with: xystón.

###

Doryphoroktónon

###

Literally, “spear-carrier killer”, combining doryphóros, któnos.

###

doryphóros
doryphóroi

###

Literally, “spear-carrier”, combining dóry, phóros. Can refer to a soldier or guard who carries a spear, or more metaphorically, to any attendant or follower. Cognate of ‹doryfóron›, by which they mean ouraniodoryphóron.

###

Dōtḗrion

###

Literally, “gifter”, referencing dōrētḗs. The Gifter, appellation of the faded god of plenty. See also: antídoton.

###

doúlē
doûlai

###

Literally, “female slave”. Though is any woman truly free? Related to the cognate of ‹doula›. See also: doûlos.

###

doûlos
doûloi

###

Literally, “male slave”. A beast of burden standing on two legs. Like an ‹intern›, only better treated. See also: doúlē, andrápodon.

###

drachmḗ
drachmaí

###

Drachma. Literally, “drachma”. Still more literally, “grasp”, alluding to a handful of metal spits. Serves as a unit of weight and also the principle unit of currency, which is defined by a coin of that weight in silver, worth 6 oboloí. Cognate of ‹drachma›; related to the cognate of ‹dram›.

###

drâma
drámata

###

Drama. Literally, “drama”. Still more literally, “acting”, “performing”, “doing”. A performance in which actors play characters within a structured narrative. Cognate of ‹drama›. See also: théatron.

###

dýnamis
dynámeis

###

Dynamic. Literally, “dynamic”. Still more literally, “power”, “force”, hence motion. This is the passive sense of power: the capacity to act; the capability, energy, or focus. Cognate of ‹dynamic›. Contrast with: krátos.

###

dýo, dyás
di‑, deúteros

###

Dyo‑. Literally, “dyo‑”. In cardinal form (“two”), and then again in collective (“pair”), combining, and ordinal (“second”) forms. No relation to ‹Dio›, diá. Cognate of ‹dyo‑›, ‹dy‑›, ‹duo›, ‹deutero‑›, ‹deuter‑›; related to the cognates of ‹two›, ‹dyad›, ‹dual›, ‹duplex›, ‹deuteronomy›, ‹deuterium›. See also: numbers.

###

ḗ

###

Eh? No, ḗ. Just ḗ. Or. Literally, “or”. See also: kaì.

###

Éar
éara

###

Literally, “spring”. The season of spring. Related to the cognate of ‹vernal›.

###

Earth

###

Gê, not Antíchthōn, no matter what anyone might think.

###

edém

###

Eden. Literally, “eden”, through foreign influence. Yet another walled garden, like parádeisos. When capitalized, refers to a place ostensibly in the far west, like Ēlýsion, though perhaps distinct. According to legend, it contained a tree, sacred to the gods, upon which hung their golden apples of immortality. This was itself supposedly guarded by a nymph or a serpent or perhaps a dragon; accounts vary. There is, in poetry, no factuality.

###

egeírōn
egeírontes

###

Literally, “rousing”. A stimulant: any exciting or euphoric phármakon. Related to the cognate of ‹Egeria›. See also: anazōpyroûn káryon. Contrast with: katapraýntikós.

###

Eikṓn
Eikônes

###

Eikon. Literally, “eikon” or “icon”. Still more literally, “image”, “semblance”, or “likeness”. For a god, Their holy Symbol through which They accept mánna. Cognate of ‹eikon›, ‹eikon‑›, ‹icon›, ‹icon‑›. See also: eikonoklasía.

###

eikonoklasía
eikonoklasíai

###

Iconoclasm. Literally, “iconoclasm”, combining eikṓn, kláō. Still more literally, “shattering images”. The irreverent crime of disrespecting or destroying a god’s Eikṓn, thus becoming an eikonoklástēs. More broadly, the systematic rejection of established religion. Cognate of ‹iconoclasm›.

###

eikonoklastón
eikonoklástai

###

Iconoclast. Literally, “iconoclast”, referencing eikonoklasía. One who commits this act. Cognate of ‹iconoclast›.

###

eirḗnē
eirênai

###

Eirene. Literally, “eirene”. Still more literally, “peace”. It is, I imagine, an unalloyed virtue. Its mythical personification is said to hold the kéras tēs plēthṓras in its right hand, for surely plenty and peace go together. No relation to eírōn, ‹Eire›, ‹Christopher Smith›. Cognate of ‹eirene›; related to the cognates of ‹eirenics›, ‹irenics›, ‹eirenicon›, ‹irenicon›, ‹Irene›.

###

eírōn
eírōnes

###

Eiron. Literally, “eiron”. Still more literally, “speaker” or “dissembler”. A stock character in kōmōidía who feigns ignorance to remain underestimated and thus outwit the alazṓn. Oft something of a trickster. For example: ‹Sōkrátēs›, ‹Bugs Bunny›, ‹Columbo›. No relation to eirḗnē, nor (ironically) to iron. Cognate of ‹eiron›; related to the cognate of ‹irony›.

###

eisagōgikón
eisagōgiká

###

Isagoge. Literally, “isagoge”, combining eis, ágō. Still more literally, “introduction” or “lead in”. In the general context of orthographía, a quotation mark. More specifically, the traditional way to quote koinodiálektos, like «toûto». Cognate of ‹isagoge›. Contrast with: xenoeisagōgiká.

###

ek
ex

###

Ex. Literally, “ex”. Still more literally, “from”, “out of”, “due to”. The forms are for words beginning with consonants and vowels, respectively. No relation to ‹exo‑›, nor to ‹ex› as in former, nor, I think, to mutants. Cognate of ‹ex›, ‹ex‑›.

###

Ekdikoúsa

###

Literally, “she who avenges”, combining ek, díkē. The Avenger, appellation of the beloved, faded god of merciless vengeance and destruction. The world is, without Her, empty. See also: She, Her.

###

eklogḗ
eklogaí

###

Election. Literally, “election” or “selection”, combining ek, légō. Still more literally, “pick out of”. Cognate of ‹election›; related to the cognates of ‹eclectic›, ‹elite›. Contrast with: krísis.

###

elaía
elaîai

###

Literally, “olive” or “olive tree”. Related to the cognates of ‹oil›, ‹oleum›. See also: élaion, elaiṓn.

###

élaion
élaia

###

Literally, “olive oil”, referencing elaía. Can refer, also, to other such oils, though not to fat or grease.

###

elaiṓn
elaiṓnes

###

Literally, “olive grove”, referencing elaía.

###

electrum

###

A naturally-occurring alloy of gold and silver (and sometimes traces of copper and other metals), used for coins. See: ḗlektron. See also: statḗr.

###

ḗlektron
ḗlektra

###

Electron. Literally, “electron”. Still more literally, “shiny”. Refers to electrum and to amber, as both are shiny. Which one is intended is, of course, obvious in context. No relation to keraunós or leptón. Cognate of ‹electron›, and related to ‹Ēléktra›.

###

eléphas
eléphantes

###

Elephant. Literally, “elephant”, through foreign influence. Cognate of ‹elephant›.

###

eleútheros
eleútheroi

###

Eleuthero‑. Literally, “eleuthero‑”. Still more literally, “free”. A free person, as opposed to a doûlos. By implication, if male then polítēs, not apeleútheros. Cognate of ‹eleuthero‑›, ‹eleuther‑›; related to the cognates of ‹eleutherogamous›, ‹eleutheromaniac›, ‹eleutherophobia›, ‹Eleutheria›, ‹Eleuthera›.

###

ēlýsion
ēlýsia

###

Elysium. Literally, “elysium”. Refers to the mythical eutopía of the Elysian Fields, in the far west, which may or may not be the same as Edém. Cognate of ‹Elysium›; related to the cognate of ‹elysian›. See also: parádeisos.

###

empátheia
empátheiai

###

Empathy. Literally, “empathy”, combining én, páthos. Still more literally, “feeling within”. Traditionally referred to being filled with one’s own intense emotion. Cognate of ‹empathy›. Contrast with: sympátheia.

###

émporos
émporoi

###

Literally, “merchant” or “trader”, combining én, póros. Still more literally, “in passage”, hence passenger or traveler. No relation to ‹emperor›. Related to the cognates of ‹emporium›, ‹port›.

###

émpousa
émpousai

###

Empousa. Literally, “empousa”, combining én, poús. Still more literally, “on (one) foot”. Monstrous chímaira with the face of a beautiful woman, yet also onokṓlē. Appearing at mesēmbría, she uses polymórphōsis, tēlepátheia, kaì nekromanteía to seduce and consume boys and men. Cognate of ‹empousa›, ‹empusa›.

###

empousógonos
empousógonoi

###

Literally, “empusa spawn”, combining émpousa, gónos. A kêr that is essentially equivalent to a daimonógonos, the distinction making no difference except to the most needlessly pedantic.

###

empousoxíphos
empousoxíphē

###

Literally, “empusa sword”, combining émpousa, xíphos. Cursed sword with an émpousa trapped within it. Essentially equivalent to a daimonoxíphos, the distinction making no difference except to the most pedantic.

###

empýrion
empýria

###

Empyrean. Literally, “empyrean”, combining én, pŷr. Still more literally, “on fire”. Metaphorically, “fiery” or “bright”, referring to the highest heavens. In reality, a kenón cold enough to freeze air yet simultaneously burning from the harsh, bright glare of the Sun. Cognate of ‹empyrean›, ‹empyreal›.

###

én

###

In. Literally, “in”, “into”, “on”, or “among”. Cognate of ‹in›.

###

ennéa, enneás
ennea‑, énatos

###

Ennea‑. Literally, “ennea‑”. In cardinal (“nine”) form, and then again in collective (“ennead”), combining, and ordinal (“ninth”) forms. No relation to énnoia. Cognate of ‹ennea‑›, ‹ennead›; related to the cognates of ‹nine›, ‹novem‑›, ‹November›. See also: numbers.

###

énnoia
énnoiai

###

Ennoia. Literally, “ennoia”, combining én, noûs. Still more literally, “concept”, “idea”, or “notion”. Even more literally, “inner thought”. A mental construct, composed of stoicheîa, representing knowledge or understanding. The natural language of tēlepátheia, though not without its risks. No relation to ennéa. Cognate of ‹ennoia›.

###

entropía
entropíai

###

Entropy. Literally, “entropy”, combining én, tropḗ. Still more literally, “turning inward”. Traditionally, referred also to confusion and shame, for obvious reasons. Cognate of ‹entropy›; related to the cognate of ‹trope›.

###

epangelían
epangelíai

###

Evangelism. Literally, “evangelism”, combining epí, ángelos. Still more literally, “promise” or “proclamation”, hence a pledge. An eternal commitment to a god, demanded of a hēmítheos. Cognate of ‹evangelism›. Contrast with: hórkos.

###

ephēbeía

###

Ephebe. Literally, “ephebe”, combining epí, hḗbē. Still more literally, “early manhood”. A period of training in a boy’s life before he takes on the mystēria and becomes an adult. The details of this are known to all, except for women, who are left to guess and wonder. Equivalent to, though more formal — and obviously more important — than, partheneía. Cognate of ‹ephebe›, ‹ephebus›.

###

ephḗmeros
ephḗmeroi

###

Ephemeral. Literally, “ephemeral”, combining epí, hēméra. Still more literally, “for a day”. Cognate of ‹ephemeral›.

###

epí

###

Literally, “on”, “upon”, “over (position)”, “at”, “beside”, “in addition to”, “toward”, “against”, “onto (motion)”. How versatile and ambiguous! I will spare you a list of other entries to see also, as it would be too long to be useful.

###

epì tà dexiā́

###

Literally, “toward the right”, combining epí, tà, dexiā́. Typical of modern writing, going from left to right. Related to the cognate of ‹dexterity›.

###

epì tà laïá

###

Literally, “toward the left”, combining epí, tà, laïá. Typical of ancient writing, going from right to left.

###

epiklḗsis
epiklḗseis

###

Epiclesis. Literally, “epiclesis”, combining epí, klēsis. Still more literally, a “calling upon”. Invocation for a god. Cognate of ‹epiclesis›.

###

epistḗmē
epistêmai

###

Episteme. Literally, “episteme”, combining epí, hístēmi. Still more literally, “knowledge”, hence science. Even more literally, “standing upon”, referring to the stable foundation science provides. Knowledge that is systematic and intellectually sound. Note that anōtéra epistḗmē refers to árkanon. Cognate of ‹episteme›; related to the cognate of ‹epistemology›.

###

epítheton
epítheta

###

Epithet. Literally, “epithet”, combining epí, títhēmi. Still more literally, “something placed upon”. Words used in place of a name to characterize or identify, as by their attributes, habits, or accomplishments. For example: Butcher of Men. These form the basis for many types of names and titles. Cognate of ‹epithet›. Contrast with: ónoma.

###

epómenos
epómenoi

###

Literally, “next” or “following”. No relation to epṓnymos.

###

epṓnymos
epṓnymoi

###

Eponym. Literally, “eponym”, combining epí, ónoma. Still more literally, “named after”. The person — or god — for whom a place is named. No relation to epómenos. Cognate of ‹eponym›.

###

érebos
Érebos Archaîos Bathýskios

###

Literally, “primordial darkness”, or as personified, “Primeval Deep-Dusky Shadow”. Either deep shadow, or the poetic embodiment of the shining blackness at the heart of a daimonógonos. The latter is said to have, with Nýx, fathered Hýpnos and perhaps even Thánatos. Related to the cognate of ‹Erebus›. See also: skótos, zóphos.

###

érōs
érōtes

###

Eros. Literally, “eros”. Romantic or passionate love, which makes fools of us all. Cognate of ‹eros›; related to the cognate of ‹erotic›.

###

éschatos
éschatoi

###

Eschato‑. Literally, “eschato‑”. Still more literally, “last”, “final”, “furthest”, or “ultimate”. Still more literally, “beyond end”. No relation with ‹cat› or ‹ChatGPT›, I think. Cognate of ‹eschato‑›; related to the cognates of ‹eschatocol›, ‹eschatology›, ‹eschaton›. Contrast with: prôtos.

###

ésoptron
ésoptra

###

Literally, “mirror”, combining eis, ópsis. Still more literally, “looked within”. Made of polished metal, usually chalkós, though sometimes of árgyros or chrȳsós. Related to the cognates of ‹esoteric›, ‹optical›.

###

ethnoṓnymon
ethnoṓnyma

###

Ethnonym. Literally, “ethnonym”, combining éthnos, ónoma. The possessive form of the person’s ethnicity, such as their barbarian tribe, used as part of the full name. No relation to etymṓnymon. Cognate of ‹ethnonym›. See also: dēmosṓnymon.

###

éthnos
éthnē

###

Ethno‑. Literally, “ethno‑”. Still more literally, “ethnicity”. Even more literally, “nation”, “tribe”, or “people”. A group defined by shared ancestry, language, and culture, hence including all its people. No relation to ‹Eithne›. Cognate of ‹ethnicity›, ‹ethno‑›. See also: people, dêmos, ethnoṓnymon.

###

etymomorphḗ
etymomorphaí

###

Literally, “true shape”, combining étymos, morphḗ. The true self, as dictated by ones chromosṓmata. It is altered by metamórphōsis, though not polymórphōsis.

###

étymon
étyma

###

Etymon. Literally, “etymon”, referencing étymos. Still more literally, “true meaning”. The original meaning of a word, oft stemming from the language it came from. Cognate of ‹etymon›; related to the cognate of ‹etymology›. Contrast with: etymṓnymon.

###

etymṓnymon
etymṓnyma

###

Literally, “true name”, combining étymos, ónoma. Sacred, though not necessarily secret. Refers to the personal name, and also to the full name that contains it; the latter being necessary for such things as tēlepátheia. For a god, the Etymṓnymon is Their immutable identity, and this Name is used always in prayer, alongside Their epiklḗsis. No relation to ethnoṓnymon. Related to the cognates of ‹antonym›, ‹pseudonym›. See also: blasphēmía. Contrast with: prosonymía, étymon.

###

étymos
étymoí

###

Etym‑. Literally, “etym‑”. Still more literally, “true”, “genuine”, or “authentic”. Specifically, truth in the sense of essential nature, not simply factuality, much less honesty. Cognate of ‹etym‑›; related to the cognate of ‹etymology›. See also: étymon, etymṓnymon, etymomorphḗ.

###

eû

###

Eu‑. Literally, “eu‑”. Still more literally, “good” or “well”. Goodness in term of action, condition, or outcome. No relation to ‹European Union›. Cognate of ‹eu‑›; related to the cognates of ‹eudaimonism›, ‹euphoria›, ‹eugenics›. See also: agathós.

###

euchḗ
euchaí

###

Literally, “prayer”, referencing eû. Still more literally, “good utterance”. The sacrifice of mánna, accompanied by a humble request for divine aid. No relation to ‹ouch›. Related to the cognates of ‹eucharist›, ‹euphony›, ‹euphemism›. Contrast with: blasphēmía.

###

euḗthēs
euḗtheis

###

Literally, “fool”, combining eû, êthos. Still more literally, “good disposition”. Specifically, a simple-minded person who is easily deceived. Contrast with: áphrōn, mōrós.

###

eutopía
eutopíai

###

Eutopia. Literally, “eutopia”, combining eû, tópos. Still more literally, “good place”. The mythical Good Place, with its endless baklavás. The exact opposite of outopía, or is it? Cognate of ‹eutopia›; related to the cognates of ‹utopia›, ‹topological›. See also: parádeisos.

###

éxō

###

Exo‑. Literally, “exo‑”. Still more literally, “out”, “outside”, or “beyond”. Cognate of ‹exo‑›.

###

exōmís
exōmídes

###

Exomis. Literally, “exomis”, combining éxō, ōmos. Still more literally, “off the shoulder”. A type of short chitṓn fastened over the left shoulder, leaving the right arm bare to the chest. Like the chitônískos, it is favored by those with practical considerations and less interest in dignity, such as manual laborers, slaves, and especially soldiers. Typically worn with the chlamýs. No relation to ‹exomes›. Cognate of ‹exomis›; related to the cognates of ‹omoplate›, ‹omalgia›.

###

exōstrakísthē
exōstrakísthēsan

###

Ostracized. Literally, “ostracized”, referencing ek, óstrakon. Still more literally, “(cast) out by potsherd”, referring to the practice of writing a person’s name on a pottery shard. Cognate of ‹ostracize›; related to the cognates of ‹osteo‑›, ‹ossify›.

###

Failed Wanderer

###

Alludes to an asteroeidḗs being too small to count as a Wanderer.

###

four numeracies

###

See: arithmētikḗ, geōmetría, mousikḗ, astronomía. See also: paidéia eleuthérōn, mathēmatikón.

###

gála, gálakta

###

Literally, “milk”. Related to the cognates of ‹galactose›, ‹lactose›, ‹galaxy›.

###

gála tês paparoúnēs

###

Literally, “milk of the poppy”, combining gála, tês, paparoúnē. An epítheton for ópion.

###

gámos
gámoi

###

Literally, “marriage” or “wedding”. No relation to gónos. Related to the cognates of ‹gamete›, ‹exogamy›, ‹cryptogam›. See also: monogamía, polygamía.

###

Gê

###

Geo‑. Literally, “geo‑”. Still more literally, “earth”. The planet Earth, if we consider it a planḗtēs, as we should. Cognate of ‹geo‑›; related to the cognate of ‹geology›. See also: chthónios, geōgraphía, geōmetría, gês morphopoḯas.

###

génos
génē

###

Gene. Literally, “gene”. Still more literally, “origin”, “race”, “lineage”, “kind”, “type”. Even more literally, “birth”. Cognate of ‹gene›, ‹geno‑›, ‹gen‑›, ‹‑gen›, ‹‑gene›, ‹‑geny›, ‹‑genic›, ‹‑genetic›; related to the cognates of ‹genesis›, ‹genetic›, ‹genealogy›, ‹genus›, ‹generic›, ‹generate›, ‹generous›, ‹general›, and many more such offspring. See also: paliggenesía, nitrogenḗs, gónos, goneús.

###

geōgraphía
geōgraphíai

###

Geography. Literally, “geography”, combining Gê, graphís. Still more literally, “land description”. Cognate of ‹geography›. See also: chártēs.

###

geōmetría
geōmetríai

###

Geometry. Literally, “geometry”, combining Gê, metrikós. Still more literally, “land measurement”. Cognate of ‹geometry›. See also: four numeracies.

###

gês morphopoḯas
gês morphopoḯai

###

Literally, “earth shaping”, combining Gê, morphḗ, poíēsis. Terraforming.

###

glaúx
glaukés

###

Glauco‑. Literally, “glauco‑”. Still more literally, “(little) owl”. Even more literally, “gray”. Cognate of ‹glauco‑›, ‹glauc‑›; related to the cognates of ‹glaux›, ‹glaucoma›, ‹glaucous›, ‹glaucope›, ‹glaucophane›, ‹glaukomflecken›. See also: Sophóglaux.

###

gloss

###

A brief explanation for an obscure or foreign word; hence glossaries. No relation to ‹gloss› as in ‹glossy›. Related to glôssa.

###

glôssa
glôssai

###

Literally, “tongue”. Metaphorically, “language”. Related to the cognates of ‹glosso‑›, ‹glossary›, ‹gloss›, ‹glossolalia›, ‹glottis›. See also: gloss.

###

glykýs
glykeîs

###

Gluco‑. Literally, “gluco‑”. Still more literally, “sweet”. Also, metaphorically. Cognate of ‹gluco‑›, ‹gluc‑›, ‹glucose›; related to the cognate of ‹glycogen›.

###

glyptón
glyptá

###

Glyph. Literally, “glyph”. Still more literally, “sculpture” or “statue”. Even more literally, “carved object”. Cognate of ‹glyph›, related to the cognates of ‹cleave›, ‹hieroglyphics›.

###

gnṓrisis
gnṓriseis

###

Literally, “the act of making known”, “acknowledgment”, “recognition”, referencing gnôsis.

###

gnôsis
gnôseis

###

Gnosis. Literally “gnosis”. Still more literally, “knowledge”, oft with esoteric connotations. Cognate of ‹gnosis›; related to the cognate of ‹know›.

###

góēssa
góēssai

###

Literally, “sorceress”. See also: goēteía.

###

goēteía
goēteîai

###

Goetia. Literally, “goetia”. Still more literally, “sorcery”. Even more literally, “wailing”, alluding to chants. Essentially, mageía, though more specifically referring to enchantment and oft bearing a negative connotation. No relation to goats, ‹goatse›. Cognate of ‹goetia›.

###

goneús
goneîs

###

Literally, “parent”, referencing gónos. Still more literally, “birther”. No relation to ‹Obama›. See also: theogoneús, patḗr, mḗtēr.

###

gōnía
gōníai

###

Gonio‑. Literally, “gonio‑”. Still more literally, “angle” or “corner”. Even more literally, “bend”, “knee”, or “joint”. No relation to ‹Patagonia›, gónos. Cognate of ‹gonio‑›, ‹goni‑›; related to the cognates of ‹gonion›, ‹gonitis›, ‹goniopuncture›. See also: polýgōnon.

###

gónos
gónoi

###

Literally, “spawn”, referencing génos. Still more literally, “offspring”, “progeny”, “procreation”, “product”. No relation to gámos. Cognate of ‹gonad›, ‹‑gonic›. See also: daimonógonos, empousógonos, goneús.

###

grámma
grámmata

###

Gramma‑. Literally, “gramma‑”, related to graphís. Still more literally, “letter”. Either a missive or a part of the álphabētos. No relation to ‹gramma›, ‹grama›. Related to the cognates of ‹gramma‑›, ‹‑gram›.

###

grammatikḗ
grammatikaí

###

Grammar. Literally, “grammar”, hence literacy. Still more literally, “study of letters”, referencing grámma. See also: three literacies.

###

grapheîon
grapheîa

###

Literally, “writing room”, referencing graphís. Specifically, a business or administrative office open to clients.

###

graphís
graphídes

###

Literally, “writer”. Specifically, a stylus, pencil, or brush. For the kēropínax, a small rhábdos made of bronze, bone, or ivory; it is sharp at one end so as to cut into the wax and blunt at the other so as to flatten it. Related to the cognates of ‹graph›, ‹‑graph›, ‹‑graphy›, ‹graphic›, ‹graphite›, ‹graffiti›.

###

grîphos
grîphoi

###

Literally, “riddle” or “puzzle”. No relation to ‹griffin›.

###

gynaikeîon
gynaikeîa

###

Literally, “female place”, referencing gynḗ. In a proper house, it is the area in the rear or upstairs, specifically designated for women and their housework. This labor is largely concerned with the production and care of textiles and children. Children and female visitors have free access, and the men of the household may visit, while male visitors are strictly excluded. Modestly decorated, as befits the modest needs of modest women. As goes the aphorismós, “a woman’s place is in the woman’s place”. Contrast with: andrṓn.

###

gynḗ
gynaîkes

###

Gyno‑. Literally, “gyno‑”. Still more literally, “woman” or “wife”. Like anḗr, only inferior, due to being thḗleia. Cognate of ‹gyno‑›, ‹gyn‑›; related to the cognates of ‹gynecology›, ‹gynecomastia›. See also: gynaikeîon, andrógynon.

###

hádeios
hádeioi

###

Hadean. Literally, “hadean”, referencing “Hades”: the poetic name for the gray Hollows of the Earth. Hence, infernal, underworldly. Cognate of ‹hadean›. Contrast with: ouránios. See also: chthónios.

###

hádyton
hádyta

###

Adytum. Literally, “adytum”, combining a‑, dýō. Still more literally, “not to be entered”. The innermost sanctuary of a naós, open only to hiereîs: the hágia hagíōn, or cella. Cognate of ‹adytum›.

###

hágia
hágia hagíōn

###

Hagia. Literally, “hagia”. Still more literally, “holy”. Applies to people, divine qualities, spiritual concepts. The “holy of holies” refers to the sanctum sanctorum known as hádyton. Cognate of ‹hagia›. See also: hágios. Contrast with: hierós.

###

Hagiokéleuthos

###

Literally, “holy path”, combining hágia, kéleuthos. The divine plan for mortals.

###

hágios
hágioi

###

Hagio‑. Literally, “hagio‑”, referencing hágia. Still more literally, “holy (one)”, hence a saint. Even more literally, “standing in awe of”. No relation to hags. Cognate of ‹hagio‑›; related to the cognates of ‹hagiography›, ‹hagiology›, ‹hagiolith›. See also: hierós.

###

haîma
haímata

###

Heme. Literally, “heme”. Still more literally, “blood”. Cognate of ‹heme›, ‹hemato‑›, ‹hemat‑›, ‹hem‑›; related to the cognates of ‹hematal›, ‹hematology›.

###

hamartía
hamartíai

###

Hamartia. Literally, “hamartia”. Still more literally, “sin”, “error”, or “failure”. Even more literally, “missing the mark”. Ranges from an oopsie, to a tragic flaw inherent in one’s nature, to an unforgivable abomination. Cognate of ‹hamartia›.

###

hápax legómenon
hápax legómena

###

Hapax legomenon. Literally, “hapax legomenon”, combining hápax, legómenon. Still more literally, “said once”. A term found only once within a particular léxis, and yet I keep saying it again and again. Hapax! Cognate of ‹hapax legomenon›, ‹hapax›.

###

hē, ho, tò
hai, hoi, tà

###

Literally, “the”. The nominative definite article, applying to the subject of the verb, in feminine, masculine, and neuter forms, respectively, and then again in plural. See also: the.

###

hédra
hédrai

###

‑Hedra. Literally, “‑hedra”. Still more literally, “base”, “foundation”, “face (of a 3D geometric shape)”. Even more literally, “seat”. Cognate of ‹‑hedra›, ‹‑hedron›. No relation to ‹Al-Qaeda›, I think. Related to the cognates of ‹cathedral›, ‹exedra›, ‹polyhedron›. See also: tetráedron, polýedron. Contrast with: gōnía.

###

hēgemonía
hēgemoníai

###

Hegemony. Literally, “hegemony”. No relation to ‹money›. Cognate of ‹hegemony›.

###

heîs, mía
hén, mono‑

###

Heno‑. Literally, “heno‑”. In cardinal masculine, feminine, and neuter forms (“one”), respectively, and then again in combining form (which comes from mónos), with prôtos as the ordinal (“first”). No relation to ‹heist›, ‹hen›. Cognate of ‹mono‑›, ‹mon‑›; related to the cognate of ‹henotheism›. See also: numbers.

###

Hēliakòn Sýstēma

###

Literally, “solar system”, combining Hḗlios, sýstēma.

###

heliokinētikós

###

Literally, “moving with the sun”, combining Hḗlios, kínēsis, hence clockwise. Traveling in the direction of the Sun, hence that of a sundial. Contrast with: antiheliokinētikós.

###

Hḗlios

###

Helio‑. Literally, “helio‑”. Still more literally, “sun”. Cognate of ‹helio‑›, ‹heli‑›; related to the cognates of ‹heliocentric›, ‹helium›.

###

hēméra
hēmérai

###

Hemera. Literally, “hemera”. Still more literally, “day”, “daylight”. Cognate of ‹hemera›; related to the cognate of ‹hemeralopia›, ‹ahemeral›. See also: times, mesēmbría, ephḗmeros.

###

hēmiōbólion
hēmiōbólia

###

Literally, “half-obol”, combining hḗmisys, obolós. Specifically, a silver coin worth ½ an obolós, hence a 12th of a drachmḗ.

###

hēmiolía
hēmiolíai

###

Hemiola. Literally, “hemiola”, combining hḗmisys, hólos. Still more literally, “half and a whole”. Refers to a type of light, fast warship, for obvious reasons. Less importantly, when considered as a ratio of 3:1, it has also various meanings in the fields of mousikḗ kaì mathēmatiká. Cognate of ‹hemiola›.

###

hēmisphaírion
hēmisphaíria

###

Hemisphere. Literally, “hemisphere”, combining hḗmisys, sphaîra. Still more literally, “half sphere”. Cognate of ‹hemisphere›.

###

hḗmisys
hēmísoi

###

Hemi‑. Literally, “hemi‑”. Still more literally, “half”, akin to “semi”. Cognate of ‹hemi‑›, ‹hemi›.

###

hēmítheos
hēmítheoi

###

Literally, “half-god”, combining hḗmisys, theós, hence a demigod. And perhaps, one day, a god. Contrast with: ánthrōpos.

###

héndeka, hendekás
hendeka‑, hendékatos

###

Hendeca‑. Literally, “hendeca‑”, combining heîs, déka. Still more literally, “one (and) ten”. In cardinal (“eleven”) form, and then again in collective (“hendecad”), combining, and ordinal “eleventh” forms. Cognate of ‹hendeca‑›, ‹hendec‑›, ‹hendecad›; related to the cognate of ‹hendecasyllabic›. See also: numbers.

###

heortḗ
heortaí

###

Literally, “festival” or “celebration”. Not just a party: a religious observance. Related to the cognate of ‹heortology›.

###

hēṓs

###

Eos. Literally, “eos”. Still more literally, “dawn”. It is the phenomenon of sunrise, not the time of day, which is órthros. Cognate of ‹eos›. See also: Heōsphóros.

###

Heōsphóros

###

Literally, “dawn-bringer”, combining hēṓs, phóros. Specifically, the Morning Star, which rises ahead of the Sun. No relation to Hésperos, I think. See also: Phōsphóros.

###

hêpar
hēpata

###

Hepato‑. Literally, “hepato‑”. Still more literally, “liver”. Traditionally considered the seat of emotions, for obvious reasons. Cognate of ‹hepato‑›, ‹hepat‑›; related to the cognates of ‹hepatic›, ‹hepatitis›, ‹heparin›.

###

hēpatoskopía
hēpatoskopíai

###

Literally, “liver looking”, combining hêpar, ópsis. A form of divination based on examining entrails.

###

heptá, heptás
hepta‑, hébdomos

###

Hepta‑. Literally “hepta‑”. In cardinal (“seven”) form, and then again in collective (“heptad”), combining and ordinal “seventh” forms. No relation to ‹haptic›. Cognate of ‹hepta‑›, ‹hept‑›, ‹heptad›; related to the cognate of ‹seven›, ‹sept‑›, ‹September›. See also: numbers.

###

Her

###

She is who I mean.

###

Her!

###

Obviously, I’m referring to Ekdikoúsa. Who else might I mean?

###

hermaphróditon
hermaphródita

###

Hermaphrodite. Literally, “hermaphrodite” or “hermaphroditic”. If you must know, while the vagina is as you might expect, what would be the clitoris is instead a phallós in full. There is no ourḗthra, as such, since the kidneys — much as in a bird — void the urates as a thick paste directly to the urodeum of the cloaca via ureters. Instead, the phallós is plumbed to the testis—which lays in the abdomen, parallel to the ovary—by a tube technically known as an androphóros: the androduct.
I would go on to explain how self-impregnation is made impossible, yet you seem a bit unwell. Perhaps I ought not have shared those rather vividly illustrative phantasíai? Cognate of ‹hermaphrodite›. See also: arsenóthēly, andrógynon.

###

hespéra
hespérai

###

Literally, “evening” or “dusk”. Refers also to the west, for obvious reasons. Basis of the cognates of ‹Hesperus›, ‹vespers›. See also: times, Hésperos.

###

Hésperos

###

Literally, “evening (star)”, referencing hespéra. Specifically, the Evening Star, which rises as the Sun sets. No relation to Heōsphóros, I think.

###

Hestías Líthos
hestías líthoi

###

Literally, “stone of the hearth”, combining hestías, líthos. Housed in Prytaneîon, it is the eternal symbol of a pólis; to capture it is to conquer the city-state. Related to the cognates of ‹Hestia›, ‹vestal›.

###

heúrēka

###

Eureka. Literally, “eureka”, referencing heurískō. Still more literally, “I have found (it)!”. Cognate of ‹eureka›.

###

heurískō

###

Heuristic. Literally, “heuristic”. Still more literally, “find” or “discover”. Cognate of ‹heuristic›. See also: heúrēka.

###

héx, hexás
hexa‑, héktos

###

Hexa‑. Literally “hexa‑”. In cardinal (“six”) form, and then again in collective (“hexad”), combining and ordinal (“sixth”) forms. No relation to ‹hex› in the sense of mageía, nor to ‹hecto‑›, ‹hect‑›. Cognate of ‹hexa‑›, ‹hex‑›, ‹hex›, ‹hexad›; related to the cognates of ‹six›, ‹sext‑›, ‹hexagon›, ‹hexadecimal›. See also: numbers.

###

hierarchía
hierarchíai

###

Hierarchy. Literally, “hierarchy”, combining hiereús, archḗ. Still more literally, “holy rule”. The divine ordering imposed by the gods, ranking all from most holy to least: placing the pure in charge of the impure. What could be more righteous? Cognate of ‹hierarchy›.

###

hiérax
hiérakes

###

Literally, “hawk” or “falcon”. Traditionally seen as a divine ángelos, due to its speed and ferocity. Though, in truth, the gods prefer doves. No relation to ‹hyrax›. Related to the cognates of ‹hierofalcon›, ‹hieracology›, ‹Microhierax›, ‹Hieraaetus›, ‹Hieracium›.

###

hiéreia
hiéreiai

###

Priestess, akin to hiereús, only inferior. See also: priesthood.

###

hiereús
hiereîs

###

Literally, “sacred (one)”, referencing hierós. Specifically, a priest. Related to the cognates of ‹hierophant›, ‹hieratic›, ‹hieroglyph›. See also: priesthood.

###

hierobasileús
hierobasileîs

###

Literally, “priest-king”, combining hiereús, basileús. Formerly, rulers of póleis who were appointed directly by the gods, in the wake of the Golden Age, to lead the people onto the Hagiokéleuthos.

###

hierós
hierá

###

Literally, “sacred”, “holy”, “hallowed”. Applies to rituals, temples, objects, priests. Contrast with: hágia.

###

himátion
himátia

###

Himation. Literally, “himation”. Still more literally, “cape” or “cloak”. Even more literally, “small garment”. It is draped over both shoulders loosely, like a mantle. Typically worn over chitṓn or exōmís; or if they are not so fortunate as to be male, perhaps péplos. Can also be used as a blanket for sleeping, particularly when traveling. Cognate of ‹himation›. Contrast with: bírrhos, chlamýs.

###

hólkas
holkádes

###

Hulk. Literally, “hulk”. Still more literally, “pulled” or “towed”. A cargo ship or freighter, particularly one that is heavy or clumsy. Cognate of ‹hulk›, ‹Hulk›.

###

hólmos
hólmoi

###

Literally, “mortar”. A vessel for grinding with a plēktron. No relation to ‹helm›.

###

homíchlē
homíchlai

###

Literally, “fog” or “dense mist”. Also, metaphorically. Related to the cognate of ‹mist›.

###

hoplítēs
hoplîtai

###

Hoplite. Literally, “hoplite”, referencing hóplon. Still more literally, “armed man”. A heavy infantryman, drawn from the militia, who arms himself with the typical panoplía, or at least as well as his means allow. Cognate of ‹hoplite›. See also: machētḗs.

###

hoplomachía

###

Literally, “armed combat”, combining hóplon, machētḗs.

###

hóplon
hópla

###

Hoplo‑. Literally, “hoplo‑”. Still more literally, “weapon” or “armor”. Even more literally, “tool”. Often refers to the aspís, given its central importance. Cognate of ‹hoplo‑›. See also: hoplítēs, hoplomachía.

###

hórkos
hórkoi

###

Literally, “oath”. A binding commitment to a god until the fulfillment of the stated duty. Yoked upon a hiereús during their service, and taken on by devoted laity for the span of a sacred mission. The oathbound gain some small measure of divine power through their connection, aiding them in their labors. This is not without its downsides, though, once you consider skiaí. Related to the cognate of ‹exorcise›. See also: megalorkía. Contrast with: epangelían.

###

hýdōr
hýdata

###

Hydro‑. Literally, “hydro‑”. Still more literally, “water”. Cognate of ‹hydro‑›, ‹hydr‑›; related to the cognates of ‹hydrodynamics›, ‹hydrogen›. See also: klepsýdra.

###

hýmnos
hýmnoi

###

Hymn. Literally, “hymn”. Still more literally, “sung in praise”. A song of praise and devotion. Cognate of ‹hymn›. Contrast with: skólion.

###

hypér

###

Hyper‑. Literally, “hyper‑”. Still more literally, “above (positionally)”, “beyond (superior to)”, “in favor of”, “in opposition to”. Cognate of ‹hyper‑›, ‹hyper›; related to the cognates of ‹hyperbole›, ‹hyperactive›, ‹hyperion›. Contrast with: hypó.

###

Hýpnos
hýpnoi

###

Hypnos. Literally, “Hypnos”. Still more literally, “sleep”. The poets personify this all-too-natural phenomenon as the twin brother of Thánatos, and son of Nýx and Érebos. Cognate of ‹Hypnos›, ‹hypno‑›; related to the cognates of ‹hypnosis›, ‹hypnopompic›.

###

hypó

###

Hypo‑. Literally, “hypo‑”. Still more literally, “under (positionally/the power of/the standard)”, or “by”. Cognate of ‹hypo‑›, ‹hypo›; related to the cognates of ‹hypodermic›, ‹hypothalamus›, ‹hypothermia›. Contrast with hypèr.

###

hypokorismós
hypokorismoí

###

Hypocorism. Literally, “hypocorism”, combining hypó, koûros. Still more literally, “under child”. A diminutive or pet name, used as a term of endearment or familiarity. It is a type of prosonymía based on shortening a name or otherwise simplifying its pronunciation, as in the style of baby talk. Cognate of ‹hypocorism›. See also: ónoma.

###

hypokrâs
hypokrateîs

###

Hypocras. Literally, “hypocras”, combining hypó, kratḗr. Still more literally, “subtle mix”. Spiced wine, typically served warm. No relation to hypókrisis, ‹Hippokrátēs›. Cognate of ‹hypocras›, ‹hippocras›; related to the cognate of ‹krasis›.

###

hypókrisis
hypokríseis

###

Hypocrisy. Literally, “hypocrisy”, combining hypó, krísis. Still more literally, “under judgment”, hence performance or pretense. This word once had more neutral connotations and referred mostly to the stage. These became more negative over time, perhaps due to the rampant immorality of actors. Cognate of ‹hypocrisy›.

###

hypothalássion
hypothalássia

###

Literally, “under the sea”, combining hypó, thálassa.

###

hypsēlós

###

Hypso‑. Literally, “hypso‑”, referencing hypér. Still more literally, “high”, “lofty” or “exalted”. Specifically, in stature, status, or spirit. Cognate of ‹hypso‑›, ‹hypsi‑›, ‹hyps‑›; related to the cognates of ‹hypsometry›, ‹hypsophobia›.

###

iatrikḗ

###

Medicine. Literally, “healing art”. Related to the cognates of ‹iatrogenic›, ‹pediatric›, ‹psychiatry›, ‹Jason›. See also: paidéia árkanos.

###

ichṓr
ichṓres

###

Ichor. Literally, “ichor”. The divine, amber fluid that flows through the veins of gods instead of crimson blood. Cognate of ‹ichor›. See also: ḗlektron.

###

idiōtikós ereunētḗs

###

Literally, “individual researcher”, combining ídios, ereunáō. A private investigator. Related to the cognates of ‹idiot›, ‹idiom›, ‹idiosyncrasy›.

###

invocation

###

For a god, the epítheton used alongside Their Etymṓnymon in prayer to specify which of Their domains is relevant: the epiklḗsis. For example, when praying to Dólios for a boon in trade, you would follow His Etymṓnymon with Agoraîos, Patron of the Market.

###

iôta

###

Iota. Literally, “iota”. This grámma, shaped like an iota, is the smallest in the álphabētos; hence, it denotes any small amount, like a jot. Cognate of ‹iota›, ‹jot›; related to the cognates of ‹i›, ‹j›.

###

íson ant’ ísou

###

Literally, “equal against equal”, combining ísos, antí. Tit for tat, or measure for measure: an exact or fair exchange.

###

ísos
ísoi

###

Iso‑. Literally, “iso‑”. Still more literally, “same” or “equal”. Cognate of ‹iso‑›.

###

kaí

###

And. And what? Nothing: just and. Literally, “and”, and sometimes “both”. See also: ḗ.

###

kaíō

###

Cauterize. Literally, “cauterize”. Still more literally, “burn” or “brand”. Metaphorically, also. Specifically, a way to apply a stígma with fire. No relation to kaì. Cognate of ‹cauterize›; related to the cognates of ‹caustic›, ‹cautery›.

###

kapēleîon
kapēleîa

###

Literally, “retailer place”, with the connotation of tavern or wine shop. Contrast with: sympósion. See also: kapḗlissa.

###

kapḗlissa
kapḗlissai

###

Literally, “taverness” or “female shopkeeper”, referencing kapēleîon.

###

kapnós
kapnoí

###

Literally, “smoke”. It accompanies fire. Related to the cognates of ‹capnograph›, ‹capnometer›.

###

kára
kárai

###

Literally, “head”, akin to kéras. The elevated, poetic term, oft used in tragōidía. Contrast with: kephalḗ, kardía.

###

kardía
kardíai

###

Cardio‑. Literally, “cardio‑”. Still more literally, “heart”; also, metaphorically. Cognate of ‹cardio‑›; related to the cognates of ‹cardiac›, ‹cardiology›. Contrast with: kára.

###

karikatoúra
karikatoûrai

###

Caricature. Literally, “caricature”, through foreign influence. Cognate of ‹caricature›.

###

káryon
kárya

###

Literally, “nut” or “kernel”. Related to the cognates of ‹caryopsis›, ‹caryatid›. See also: anazōpyroûn káryon.

###

katà

###

Literally, “downward”, “according to/with”, “by”, “throughout”, “against”. A preposition. No relation to ‹katas› or dogs.

###

kataklysmós
kataklysmoí

###

Cataclysm. Literally, “cataclysm”, combining katà, klýzō. Still more literally, “washing over”, hence flood. Cognate of ‹cataclysm›.

###

katapraýntikós
katapraýntikoí

###

Literally, “calming down”, combining katà, praýnō, ‑tikós. A depressant: any soothing or sedating phármakon, such as kykeṓn, ópion. Contrast with: egeírōn.

###

kátharmos
kátharmoi

###

Catharsis. Literally, “catharsis”. A purging, purification, or cleansing, whether spiritual or literal. Ideally, by fire or flood, though I suppose that sometimes scrubbing with soap and water will do. Cognate of ‹catharsis›. See also: míasma.

###

keleustḗs
keleustaí

###

Literally, “commander”. Specifically, coxswain or rowing master.

###

kenón
kená

###

Literally, “void” or “emptiness”. What remains when all else is removed, hence indestructible. Nature abhors it, yet it persists. No relation to ‹Barbie›. Related to the cognate of ‹kenosis›, ‹keno›, ‹cenotaph›. See also: ontología. Contrast with: ousía.

###

kephalḗ
kephalái

###

Cephalo‑. Literally, “cephalo‑”, akin to kéras. Still more literally, “head”; also metaphorically. The term used in common prose. Cognate of ‹cephalo‑›, ‹cephal‑›; related to the cognates of ‹cephalic›, ‹cephalopod›, ‹capital›, ‹head›. Contrast with: kára.

###

kḗpos tôn mnēmoneumátōn mou

###

Literally, “garden of my remembrances”, referencing kḗpos, tôn, mnḗmē, mou. See also: hēmítheos.

###

kêr
kêres

###

Ker. Literally, “ker”. Still more literally, “death” or “destruction”. A spirit of death, considered female. No relation to ‹Kur›. Cognate of ‹ker›. See: daimonógonos.

###

keramikḗ
keramikà

###

Ceramics. Literal, “ceramics” or “pottery”, referencing kéras based on being as hard as horn. Cognate of ‹ceramics›. See also: amphoreús, kyathos, kýlix, kratḗr, oinochóē, píthos, skýphos.

###

kéras
kérata

###

Literally, “horn”. No relation to kērós. Related to the cognates of ‹keratin›, ‹ceratoid›, ‹monocerate›, ‹triceratops›, and to keraunós. See also: kéras tēs plēthṓras, kára, keramikḗ, kraníon, krános.

###

kéras tēs plēthṓras

###

Literally, “horn of plenty”, combining kéras, tēs, plēthṓra, hence the cornucopia. A traditional symbol of abundance.

###

keraunós
keraunoí

###

Literally, “thunderbolt”. Oft understood as theôn keraunoí, the jagged spears of the gods, though sometimes it’s just weather. No relation to ḗlektron. Related to the cognate of ‹keraunophobia›, and to kéras.

###

kerkoûros
kerkoûroi

###

Literally, “tail-tailed”, combining kérkos, ourá, referring to its long tail. A type of small, fast merchant ship. Related to the cognates of ‹cercal›, ‹Cercopia›.

###

kēropínax
kēropínakes

###

Literally, “wax tablet”, combining kērós, pínax. A wooden frame layered with wax, it is the ubiquitous reusable surface for notes, calculations, and temporary writing. Paired with graphídes, larger ones tend to be rectangular while smaller ones are conveniently triangular or at least acutely trapezoidal; the largest are wall-mounted boards. Related to the cognates of ‹cerumen›, ‹cere›. See also: déltos, deltíon, megalokēropínax.

###

kērós
kēroí

###

Literally, “wax”. Typically, though not always, melíkēron. No relation to kéras. Related to the cognates of ‹cerate›, ‹cerumen›.

###

kḗryx
kḗrykes

###

Literally, “herald”, “messenger”, or “public announcer”. Related to the cognates of ‹kerygma›, ‹caduceus›.

###

kínēsis
kinḗseis

###

Kinesis. Literally, “kinesis”. Still more literally, “motion”. Cognate of ‹kinesis›. See also: tēlekínēsis, pyrokínēsis, antiheliokinētikós, heliokinētikós.

###

kithára
kithárai

###

Kithara. Literally, “kithara”. A type of large, complex lýra with a box-shaped resonator, straight arms, and a flat base; played, with a plēktron, by professional mousikoí called kitharistaí. Cognate of ‹kithara›, ‹cithara›, ‹zither›; related to the cognates of ‹guitar›, ‹gittern›, ‹cittern›.

###

kitharistēs
kitharistaí

###

Kitharist. Literally, “kitharist”. A skilled, professional mousikós who sings while playing the kithára. Cognate of ‹kitharist›, ‹citharist›, ‹citharode›, ‹kitharode›.

###

kítron
kítra

###

Citron. Literally, “citron”. Refers to any of the various varieties of citruses, some sweeter, some sourer. Cognate of ‹citron›; related to the cognate of ‹citrus›. See also: chrȳsómēlon.

###

klepsýdra
klepsýdrai

###

Clepsydra. Literally, “clepsydra”, combining kléptō, hýdōr. Still more literally, “water thief”. An elegant timekeeping device based upon the regulated flow of water, oft used to impose a limit upon the duration of an activity that would otherwise task our patience and profit, whether it is a speech in court or the use of a pórnē. Cognate of ‹clepsydra›.

###

kléptō
kléptomen

###

Klepto‑. Literally, “klepto‑”. Still more literally, “steal”, “thieve”. Cognate of ‹klepto‑›, ‹klepto›; related to the cognate of ‹kleptocracy›, ‹kleptomania›. See also: klepsýdra.

###

klíbanos
klíbanoi

###

Clibanus. Literally, “clibanus”. An oven or Dutch oven. Sometimes small and owned by a single oîkos, though larger ones are shared by neighbors or even available at the agorā́ for public use. Cognate of ‹clibanus›.

###

knēmís
knēmídes

###

Cnemis. Literally, “cnemis”. Still more literally, “shin”. Specifically, a greave: a shin guard. Wrought from bronze and lined with cloth, they are custom-fitted to the soldier and usually stay in place without straps, covering the front of the leg from knee to ankle. An essential part of the panoplía of the hoplítēs, protecting what the shield cannot. Only a fool goes into battle without one, and such a fool deserves to die. Cognate of ‹cnemis›.

###

kochliárion
kochliária

###

Literally, “small spiral” or “small snail”, referring the curved shape of a spoon or small ladle. Along with a knife, what more could you ask for? A tiny trident?! Don’t be absurd. Related to the cognate of ‹cochlea›.

###

koinodiálektos

###

Literally, “common dialect”. The common glôssa ever since the Golden Age. Pure and unadulterated, unlike ‹Greek›, or even ‹Koine›.

###

kṓmē
kṓmai

###

Literally, “village”. See also: kōmōidía.

###

kōmōidía
kōmōidíai

###

Comedy. Literally, “comedy”, combining kṓmai, ōidḗ. Still more literally, “revelry song” or “festival song”. Even more literally, “village song”, referencing the drunken revelry of rural festivals. A light drâma about terrible events causing human suffering, evoking amusement and laughter. Essentially, the same thing as tragōidía, except it’s happening to a different person: one for whom you have empátheia without sympátheia. No relation to ‹commode›. Cognate of ‹comedy›. For stock characters, see: alazṓn, bōmolóchos, eírōn.

###

kōnárion
kōnária

###

Cone. Literally, “cone”. Still more literally, “small pyramid” or “pinecone”. Specifically, the pineal gland, shaped like a pinecone, hence its name. Deep within the skull, it is where soul meets body, anchoring the mind to the brain. And so it is within this pyramís that mánna is focused and the godseye is rooted, capturing the very lively and pure flame. Cognate of ‹cone›.

###

konía
koníai

###

Konio‑. Literally, “konio‑”. Still more literally, “dust” or “powder”. Cognate of ‹konio‑›, ‹conio‑›; Related to the cognates of ‹koniology›, ‹coniology›, ‹koniosis›, ‹coniosis›, ‹koniophage›, ‹coniophage›.

###

kōpēlátēs
kōpēlátai

###

Literally, “oarsman”. Still more literally, “oar driver”. Related to the cognate of ‹elastic›.

###

kopís
kopídes

###

Kopis. Literally, “kopis”. Still more literally, “chopper”. The sword features a single edge and a pronounced forward curve. While designed for both cutting and thrusting, it excels at slashing, making it ideal for heavy and shock cavalry. It is the longer, recurved version of the mákhaira. No relation to ‹khopesh›. Cognate of ‹kopis›. Contrast with: spáthē, xíphos.

###

kórax
kórakes

###

Corax. Literally, “corax”. Still more literally, “corvid”. Traditionally, a divine ángelos, for while neither the crow nor raven fly as fast as the hiérax, they take the straight path and deliver Their message by speaking. Cognate of ‹corax›.

###

kórē
kórai

###

Kore. Literally, “kore”. Still more literally, “young woman”. Notably, refers also to a traditional form of sculpture depicting the thḗleia youthful beauty and purity of this subject. The statue is life-sized, free-standing, and painted in polýchrōmos. It portrays the elegantly-dressed maiden with intricately-styled hair, her legs modestly together, and bearing an enigmatic archaic smile. No relation to ‹core›. Related to koûros. Cognate of ‹kore›.

###

Kosmomphalós

###

Literally, “world’s navel”, combining kósmos, omphalós. An epítheton of Ólympos.

###

kósmos
kósmoi

###

Cosmos. Literally, “cosmos”. Still more literally, “world” or “universe”. Even more literally, “arrangement” or “order”. Cognate of ‹cosmos›.

###

kóttabos
kóttaboi

###

Kottabos. Literally, “kottabos”. A drinking game popular at sympósia, played by flinging the dregs onto a target; of which there are many varieties, allowing many sets of rules. A game of skill as much as chance, and — over the course of the night — a test of how well one holds their drink. Cognate of ‹kottabos›.

###

koukoúlion
koukoúlia

###

Cucullus. Literally, “cucullus”. Still more literally, “cowl” or “hooded cloak”. Cognate of ‹cucullus›, ‹cowl›.

###

koûros
koûroi

###

Kouros. Literally, “kouros”. Still more literally, “young man”. Notably, refers also to a traditional form of sculpture depicting the arsenikós youthful vigor and athleticism of this subject. The statue is life-sized, free-standing, and painted in polýchrōmos. It portrays the nude youth in a stiff pose with his left leg forward, and bearing an enigmatic archaic smile. Oft used as a grave marking or an offering to the gods. Related to kórē. Cognate of ‹kouros›.

###

kraníon
kranía

###

Cranium. Literally, “cranium”, referencing krános. Still more literally, “little helmet”, hence skull. Cognate of ‹cranium›.

###

krános
kránē

###

Literally, “helmet”, akin to kéras. Wrought of bronze, it traditionally covers the cheeks and nose in the style of ‹Magneto›, although newer designs unwisely expose more of the face in an attempt to improve sight and hearing. An absolutely essential part of the panoplía of the hoplítēs. Only a fool goes into battle without one, and such a fool deserves to die. See also: kraníon.

###

kratḗr
kratêres

###

Krater. Literally, “krater”. Still more literally, “mixing vessel”. This decanter is a jar or vase, usually keramós and oft decorated elaborately, with a large round body and wide mouth for diluting wine, as is customary among civilized individuals. No relation to krátos. Cognate of ‹krater›, ‹crater›, ‹crasis›. See also: ákratos, kýathos.

###

krátos
krátē

###

Literally, “strength”, “power”, or “authority”, whether physical or political. This is the active sense of power: as exerted authority. See also: akratḗs, aristokratía, autokratía, dēmokratía, theokratíā, pankrátion, pantokrátōr. Contrast with: dýnamis.

###

krínō

###

Literally, “to judge”. Still more literally, “to distinguish, or decide”. Related to the cognates of ‹critic›, ‹criteria›, ‹crisis›, ‹discriminate›. See also: krísis, kritḗs.

###

krísis
kríseis

###

Crisis. Literally, “crisis”, referencing krínō. Still more literally, “judgment”, “decision”. Not always the end of the world, much less infinite ones. Cognate of ‹crisis›. See also: hypókrisis. Contrast with: eklogḗ.

###

kritḗs
kritaí

###

Critic. Literally, “critic”. Still more literally, “judge”, referencing krínō. Cognate of ‹critic›; related to the cognates of ‹criteria›, ‹crisis›, ‹discriminate›. See also: themistokrítēs, hypókrisis.

###

kryptós
kryptoí

###

Cryptic. Literally, “cryptic”. Still more literally, “hidden” or “concealed”. Neither a planḗtēs nor a dog. Cognate of ‹cryptic›; related to the cognate of ‹krypton›, ‹Krypton›, ‹kryptonite›. Contrast with: alḗtheia. See also: apokálypsis.

###

któnos
któnoi

###

‑Ctonus. Literally, “‑ctonus”. Still more literally, “slayer”, “slaughterer”, or “killer”. The more specific term, oft used as a suffix, akin to ‹‑cide›. Cognate of ‹‑ctonus›; related to the cognates of ‹ktenology›, ‹Androctonus›. See also: theoktónos, pantheoouranoktónos, Doryphoroktónon. Contrast with: phónos.

###

kýathos
kýathoi

###

Kyathos. Literally, “kyathos”. Still more literally, “hollowed”. A long-handled keramós cup or ladle, used to fill a kýlix from a kratḗr. Cognate of ‹kyathos›, ‹cyathus›, ‹cyatho‑›, ‹cyath‑›.

###

kybernḗtēs
kybernêtai

###

Cybernetist. Literally, “cybernetist”. Still more literally, “gubernator”, “governor”, “steersman”. Specifically, helmsman or pilot. No relation to ‹Khyber› or online sex, I think. Cognate of ‹cybernetist›, ‹gubernator›, ‹governor›; related to the cognates of ‹Kubernetes›, ‹cyber›, ‹cyber‑›.

###

kykeṓn
kykeônes

###

Kykeon. Literally, “kykeon”. Still more literally, “mixture” or “stirred”, though not shaken. A drink made from barley and water, oft with honey and relaxing herbs. When used ceremonially in mystēria, the barley is enhanced by ergot. Cognate of ‹kykeon›. See also: katapraýntikós.

###

kýlix
kýlikes

###

Kylix. Literally, “kylix”. Still more literally, “turned” or “spun”, referring to how the clay is formed. A shallow keramós goblet with looped handles on either side, resting on a slender, elevated base. Even the cheapest are decorated elaborately, both inside and out. Cognate of ‹kylix›, ‹cylix›. See also: skýphos.

###

kýttaron
kýttara

###

Cyto‑. Literally, “cyto‑”. Still more literally, “small container”. The imperceptibly tiny, roomlike building block of the flesh: the cell. Cognate of ‹cyto‑›; related to the cognate of ‹cytoplasm›. See also: chromosṓmata.

###

kyttarópsis
kyttarópseis

###

Cytoscopy. Literally, “cytoscopy”, combining kýttaron, ópsis. Still more literally, “cell sight”. Microscopic vision, allowing one to see the kýttara, even unto the chromosṓmata. Cognate of ‹cytoscopy›.

###

lábrys
lábrai

###

Labrys. Literally, “labrys”. An ornate double-headed axe. Cognate of ‹labrys›; related to the cognate of ‹labyrinth›.

###

lamprós
lamproí

###

Literally, “bright”, “glorious”, “shining”, “radiant”, “clear”. Can refer also to flame. Cognate of ‹lamp›, ‹lantern›.

###

laós
laoí

###

Literally, “people”, “subjects”. So broad that—outside of a military context, where it refers to the host—it includes women, children, and slaves. No relation to ‹Laos›, ‹Lajos›. Related to the cognate of ‹laity›. See also: people.

###

léōn
léontes

###

Lion. Literally, “lion”. An aílouros of unusual size. No relation to ‹Donatello›, ‹Michelangelo›, ‹Raphael›. Cognate of ‹lion›, ‹leon‑›, ‹‑leon›; related to the cognates of ‹leonine›, ‹leonid›, ‹Leo›, ‹Leon›, ‹Leonid›, ‹Leonard›, ‹Leonardo›, ‹Leōnídas›.

###

leptón
leptá

###

Lepton. Literally, “lepton”. Still more literally, “small”. The smallest coin minted, a thin disc of bronze worth an 8th of a chalkoûs, hence a 384th of a drachmḗ. Cognate of ‹lepton›.

###

lēstḗs
lēstaí

###

Literally, “plunderer” or “looter”. A robber, bandit, or thief. May be a brigand stalking a trade road, a peiratḗs on the high seas, or — in more urban settings — a mugger or common street thug. No relation to ‹Lestat›.

###

lḗthē
lêthai

###

Lethe. Literally, “lethe”. Still more literally, “oblivion”, “forgetfulness”, “concealment”. Like a river that washes away your memory. No relation to ‹lethal›. Cognate of ‹lethe›; related to the cognate of ‹lethargy› See also: mnḗmē, alḗtheia.

###

léxis
léxeis

###

Lexis. Literally, “lexis”. Still more literally, “word”, and therefore speech, diction, or the stylistic and rhetorical choices made in this regard. Collectively, the words in a language or the vocabulary of a people. Cognate of ‹lexis›; related to the cognate of ‹lexicon›.

###

linothṓrax
linothṓrakes

###

Linothorax. Literally, “linothorax”, combining línon, thṓrax. Still more literally, “linen breastplate”. Chest armor made of layers of linen bound together, rivaling the protection of bronze while allowing more mobility, hence an alternative part of the panoplía of the hoplítēs. It follows a tube and yoke design, encasing the torso and extending over the shoulders, oft augmented by additional protective parts. Cognate of ‹linothorax›.

###

líthos
líthoi

###

Lithic. Literally, “lithic”. Still more literally, “stone” or “rock”, oft with the connotation of a monument. Cognate of ‹lithic›, ‹‑lith›; related to the cognates of ‹neolithic›, ‹lithium›, ‹megalith›. See also: akrólithos, Hestías Líthos.

###

logikḗ
logikaí

###

Logic. Literally, “logic”. Still more literally, “study of reasoning”. Cognate of ‹logic›, ‹‑logy›. See also: three literacies.

###

love

###

That most complex of emotions, and the very thing that makes life worthwhile. In a civilized language, too vast a concept for any single word to pretend to encompass. See: agápē, érōs, philíā, storgḗ, philóstorgos.

###

lýkos
lýkoi

###

Lyco‑. Literally, “lyco‑”. Still more literally, “wolf”. No relation to light, I think. Cognate of ‹lyco›, ‹lyc-›; related to the cognates of ‹lycanthrope›, ‹lycopodium›.

###

lýra
lýrai

###

Lyre. Literally, “lyre”. Cognate of ‹lyre›; related to the cognate of ‹lyrics›. See also: kithára.

###

Lýtrō

###

A doûlos of little importance: handsome yet forgettable.

###

machētḗs
machētaí

###

Literally, “fighter”. Related to hoplomachía, mákhaira. No relation to ‹machete›, ‹macho›, ‹macchiato›. See also: hoplomachía, pygmḗ, pálē, pankrátion.

###

mageía
mageíai

###

Magic. Literally, “magic”. Contrary to the aphorismós, it never goes away. Cognate of ‹magic›. See also: árkana, alexíkaka, goēteía, nekromanteía, thaûma, phantasía.

###

mageiophágos
mageiophágoi

###

Literally, “magic-eating”, combining mageía, phagós.

###

mágeiros
mágeiroi

###

Mageiros. Literally, “mageiros”. Still more literally, “cook” and “butcher”, combined. No relation to mageía, even when the food seems supernaturally delicious, like baklavás. Cognate of ‹mageiros›, ‹magirist›.

###

mágma
mágmata

###

Magma. Literally, “magma”. Still more literally, “kneaded” or “mixed”. A thick paste, such as molten rock. Cognate of ‹magma›; related to the cognate of ‹mass›.

###

mákhaira
mákhairai

###

Makhaira. Literally, “makhaira”. Still more literally, “(fighting) knife”, referencing machētḗs. A dirk or short sword, typically straight and single-edged: ideal for close combat. The kopís is the longer, recurved version. Cognate of ‹makhaira›, ‹machaira›, ‹machaera›.

###

maníā
maníāi

###

Mania. Literally, “mania”. Still more literally, “rage” or “madness”. Sometimes divine inspiration, other times, simply having a bad day. No relation to mánna. Cognate of ‹mania›.

###

mánna

###

Manna. Literally, “manna”. Still more literally, “what (is it?)”, through foreign influence. The food of the gods, fueled by the power of will, it underlies all mageíai. Sweet and searing — like honey aflame — it is ambrosía and thus néktar. No relation to the homophone, ‹mana›, even though it refers also to a spiritual energy of some sort. Cognate of ‹manna›.

###

manteía
manteîai

###

Mantic. Literally, “mantic”. Still more literally, “divination” or “prophecy”. Even more literally, “thinking”. The attempt to acquire knowledge from the dead or from the gods or from dead gods, depending. No relation to ‹romantic›, ‹semantic›. Cognate of ‹mantic›, ‹‑mantic›, ‹‑mancy›; related to the cognates of ‹mantis›, ‹pyromancy›. See also: astragalomanteía, astromanteía, nekromanteía, pseudomanteía, pyromanteía, hēpatoskopía.

###

mantichóras
mantichórai

###

Manticore. Literally, “manticore”. Still more literally, “man-eater”, through foreign influence. A monstrous chímaira composed of a particularly improbable mixture of animal and human parts, yet no less deadly for being ridiculous. Cognate of ‹manticore›.

###

mathēmatikón
mathēmatiká

###

Mathematics. Literally, “mathematics”. Still more literally, “study of knowledge”. Cognate of ‹mathematics›. See also: four numeracies.

###

Mēdeiárion

###

Literally, “little schemer”. The hypokorismós of a silly girl, a jealous wife, and — briefly — a terrible mother. She is long gone, so let us never speak of her again! Where did you even hear that name? I’m sure I never mentioned it.

###

megalokēropínax
megalokēropínakes

###

Literally, “great wax tablet”, combining mégas, kēropínax. A large wax board, typically wall-mounted and used in education. Few objects are more terrifying.

###

megalomyoxiphophóros
megalomyoxiphophóroi

###

Literally, “great mouse, bearing sword”, combining mégas, mŷs, xíphos, phóros. Still more literally, “sword-wielding rat”. Monstrous chímaira with a murine body of near-human proportions. It is cunning and cruel and armed with opposable thumbs, not to mention the eponymous sword. Just to be clear, this is a great mouse bearing a sword, not a great sword bearing a mouse. The sword itself of normal proportions, although admirably pointy. No relation to ‹Mxyzptlk›.

###

megalorkía
megalorkíai

###

Literally, “great oath”, combining mégas, hórkos. An unbreakable geas that constrains behavior, indenturing the subject to the grave and beyond until their mission is complete.

###

mégas
megáloi

###

Mega. Literally, “mega”. Still more literally, “big”, “great”, “large”. Cognate of ‹mega›, ‹mega‑›, ‹megalo‑›, ‹meg‑›; related to the cognates of ‹megalomania›, ‹Megatron›. See also: megalokēropínax, megalorkía, ô méga, titanikós.

###

méli
mélia

###

Literally, “honey”. Sweet like sugar, only better. Related to the cognates of ‹mellifluous›, ‹melliferous›.

###

melíkēron
melíkēra

###

Literally, “honeycomb” or “beeswax”, combining méli, kērós. Still more literally, “honey-wax”.

###

mélissa
mélissai

###

Literally, “honeybee”, referencing méli. Refers metaphorically also to priestesses, poets, and pure women. Cognate of ‹Melissa›.

###

mesēmbría
mesēmbríai

###

Literally, “midday”, combining mésos, hēméra. A liminal time of day, in the dead stillness of noon, when foul spirits roam freely and the wise stay indoors. Can also refer to the south, for obvious reasons. See also: times.

###

metá

###

Meta. Literally, “meta”. Still more literally, “with”, “after”, or “change”. No relation to ‹Facebook›. Cognate of ‹meta›, ‹meta‑›; related to the cognates of ‹metastasize›, ‹metabolism›. See also: metaboloepitomḗ, metamórphōsis, metaphysikón. Contrast with: stásis.

###

metaboloepitomḗ
metaboloepitomaí

###

Literally, “change digest”, from “metabolic epitome”, hence metabállō, epitémnō, combining metá, bállō, epí, témnō. A summary of changes, cumulatively recording all. No relation to délta.

###

métallon
métalla

###

Metal. Literally, “metal”, referencing metá, though with foreign influence. Still more literally, “after another”, referring to mines and quarries. The metal, the mine, and the act of mining the metal. Of particular significance because, unlike so much else, it persists over the millennia. Cognate of ‹metal›, ‹metallo‑›, ‹metall‑›. See also: metallourgía, aloumínio, árgyros, chalkós, chrȳsós, ḗlektron, síderos, mólybdos.

###

metallourgía
metallourgíai

###

Metallurgy. Literally, “metallurgy”, referencing métallon. Still more literally, “metalworking”. Cognate of ‹metallurgy›; related to the cognate of árgon.

###

metamórphōsis
metamorphṓseis

###

Metamorphosis. Literally, “metamorphosis”, combining metá, morphḗ. Still more literally, “changing shape process”. The act of altering the etymomorphḗ of the body down to the level of the chromosṓmata in a dramatic and irreversible transformation. As significant as childbirth, and nearly as painful. Cognate of ‹metamorphosis›; related to the cognate of ‹Metamorpho›. Contrast with: polymórphōsis.

###

metaphysikón
metaphysiká

###

Metaphysics. Literally, “metaphysics”, combining metá, physikà. Still more literally, “beyond natural”, hence supernatural. Rather arbitrarily encompasses mageía while excluding physikà. Cognate of ‹metaphysics›.

###

mḗtēr
mētéres

###

Mater. Literally, “mater”. Still more literally, “mother”. A job both trivially easy and impossibly difficult, depending. No relation to ‹meter›. Cognate of ‹mother›, ‹mater›, ‹matri‑›, ‹matro‑›, ‹matr‑›; related to the cognates of ‹matrimony›, ‹matrix›. See also: theomḗtēr, goneús. Contrast with: patḗr.

###

méthodos
méthodoi

###

Method. Literally, “method”, combining metá, hodós. Still more literally, “following the path”. Cognate of ‹method›; related to the cognates of ‹exodus›, ‹period›, ‹synod›.

###

métoikos
métoikoi

###

Metic. Literally, “metic”. Still more literally, “housed with”, combining metá, oîkos. A resident alien; though a permanent inhabitant of the pólis, never a polítēs. No relation to ‹hermetic›. Cognate of ‹metic›. See also: apeleútheroi, bárbaroi, xénos.

###

metonomasía
metonomasíai

###

Literally, “renaming”, combining metá, ónoma. Changing the etymṓnymon requires a teletḗ with at least two other people.

###

metrikós
metrikoí

###

Metric. Literally, “metric”. Still more literally, “measurement”. No relation to métoikos, mḗtēr. Cognate of ‹metric›, ‹‑metric›.

###

míasma
miásmata

###

Miasma. Literally, “miasma”. Still more literally, “defilement”, “pollution”, “taint”, or “stain”. May be spiritual, moral, or physical. Almost all forms can be purged through kátharmos, though not necessarily quickly or easily. Cognate of ‹miasma›.

###

Míklos

###

Nicky. Literally, “Nicky”. My name, or at least what I am called: the hypokorismós of Nikólaos. As a kindness, and so as to avoid suspicion, I allow old-timers to refer to me as «Míklos ho neṓteros». By this diakritōnýmion am I distinguished as the younger. For they imagine that my absent “father”, whom I am, passed his name on to his “son”. No relation to ‹Old Nick›, ‹Little Nicky›. Cognate of ‹Nicky›, ‹Nicky Junior›.

###

misthóō

###

Literally, “hire” or “rent”.

###

mnḗmē
mnêmai

###

Mneme. Literally, “mneme”. Still more literally, “memory”. No relation to ‹meme›, nor cats. Cognate of ‹mneme›, ‹mnemon‑›, ‹mnemo‑›; related to the cognate of ‹mnemon›, ‹mnemonic›, ‹amnesia›. See also: lḗthē.

###

moîra
moîrai

###

Moira. Literally, “moira”. Still more literally, “fate” or “destiny”. Even more literally, “(one’s) allotment”. No relation to ‹Moira›, which is actually ‹Máire›, from ‹Mary›. Cognate of ‹moira›, ‹moirai›. See also: móros.

###

môly

###

Moly. Literally, “moly”, from foreign influence. The adjuring herb, distinguished by its white blossoms, black roots, and unforgettable scent: reminiscent of both fresh leeks and dried roses. While not holy, it is deadly to mortals, no matter how mighty. Cognate of ‹moly›.

###

mólybdos
mólybdoi

###

Literally, “lead”, the stoicheîon, through foreign influence. No relation to môly. Related to the cognate of ‹molybdenum›, an entirely different stoicheîon, though only by error. See also: sákcharon molýbdou, métallon.

###

monochítôn
monochítônes

###

Literally, “tunic alone”, combining mónos, chitṓn. A tunic worn without a himátion or other cloak, whether out of simplicity, practicality, or poverty.

###

monogamía
monogamíai

###

Monogamy. Literally, “monogamy”, combining mónos, gámos. Still more literally, “single marriage”. For some, too few spouses; for others, too many. Cognate of ‹monogamy›. Contrast with: polygamía.

###

monóglōttos
monóglōttoi

###

Monoglot. Literally, “monoglot”, combining mónos, glôssa. Still more literally, “one tongue”. A monolingual person; by implication, a simpleton. Cognate of ‹monoglot›. Contrast with: polýglōttos.

###

monopṓlion
monopṓlia

###

Monopoly. Literally, “monopoly”, combining mónos, pṓlos. Still more literally, “single seller”. No relation to pólis. Cognate of ‹monopoly›.

###

mónos

###

Mono. Literally, “mono”. Still more literally, “alone”, “single”, “solitary”. Its combining form is mono‑. No relation to hands or fate. Cognate of ‹mono›. See also: monochítôn, monogamía, monóglōttos, monopṓlion, monotheïsmós.

###

monotheïsmós

###

Monotheism. Literally, “monotheism”, combining mónos, theós. Still more literally, “one god”. For some, too few; for others, too many. Cognate of ‹monotheism›. Contrast with: polytheïsmós.

###

móros
móroi

###

Literally, “fate”, “doom”, or “death”, with the connotation of inescapable destruction. No relation to mōrós, ‹morose›. Related to the cognate of ‹mortal›. See also: moîra.

###

mōrós
mōroí

###

Literally, “moron” or “fool”. Dull or stupid. No relation to móros. Cognate of ‹moron›. Contrast with: áphrōn, euḗthēs.

###

morphḗ
morphaí

###

Morph. Literally, “morph”. Still more literally, “shape” or “form”. Cognate of ‹morph›, ‹morph‑›, ‹morpho‑›, ‹‑morph›; related to the cognates of ‹Morpheus›, ‹Mighty Morphin Power Rangers›. See also: metamórphōsis, polymórphōsis, polymorphía, gês morphopoḯas.

###

mousikḗ
mousikaí

###

Music. Literally, “music”. Still more literally, “art of the Muses”. Broadly encompasses poetry, dance, and other creative arts. Cognate of ‹music›; related to the cognates of ‹Muse›, ‹museum›, and the inspirational sense of ‹muse›, though no relation to the cognates of ‹amuse›, ‹muzzle›, or the dreamy-thought sense of ‹muse›. See also: four numeracies, mousikós.

###

mousikós
mousikoí

###

Musician. Literally, “musician”, referencing mousikḗ. More broadly, any skilled artist in poetry, dance, or other creative arts. No relation to mŷs, ‹Mouseketeer›. Cognate of ‹musician›.

###

mŷs
mŷes

###

Mouse. Literally, “mouse” or “muscle”. A rodent of usual size, although the term refers also to the somewhat larger, scaly-tailed sort that is associated with the field: the ‹rat›. As a flexing muscle looks like a mouse scurrying under your skin, they share a name. The specific meaning is, of course, obvious in context. And though mice vary in size and strength, I would call none of them mighty. No relation to ‹myco‑›, ‹Micky›, mousikós. Cognate of ‹mouse›, ‹muscle›, ‹murine›, ‹myo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹mussel›, ‹myocardium›. See also: megalomyoxiphophóros.

###

mystḗrion
mystēria

###

Mystery. Literally, “mystery”. Still more literally, “shut (mouth or eyes)”, symbolizing secrecy or hidden knowledge. Specifically, the secret ritual during which an etymṓnymon is chosen by the mýstēs, whether an adulthood rite or cultic initiation. Cognate of ‹mystery›. See also: teletḗ, ephēbeía, partheneía.

###

mýstēs
mýstai

###

Initiate into the mystēria.

###

Name

###

The Etymṓnymon of a god. See also: ónoma, blasphēmía.

###

naophýlax
naophýlakes

###

Temple warden or templar. Literally, “temple guardian”, combining naós, phýlax. A devout volunteer. See also: neṓkoros.

###

naós
naoí

###

Naos. Literally, “naos”. Still more literally, “dwelling”, referring to that of the god. Technically, just the hádyton of the temple. Through synekdochḗ, the entirety of it. Cognate of ‹naos›.

###

naúklēros
naúklēroi

###

Literally, “ship (ownership) lot-holder”. A ship-master, whether owner or commander. Related to the cognates of ‹nautical›, ‹clerk›, ‹clergy›.

###

nekromanteía
nekromanteîai

###

Necromancy. Literally, “necromancy”, combining nekrós, manteía. Still more literally, “corpse divination”. Strictly, refers only to divination; typically, refers also to the forbidden art of anástasis. Cognate of ‹necromancy›.

###

nekrómantis
nekrómanteis

###

Necromancer. Literally, “necromancer”, referencing nekromanteía. Cognate of ‹necromancer›.

###

nekromíasma
nekromiásmata

###

Literally, “corpse taint”, combining nekrós, míasma. The clinging taint of skiaí. Contrast with: thanatomíasma.

###

nekropyrā́
nekropyraí

###

Literally, “corpse pyre”, combining nekrós, pŷr. Funeral pyre: a type of kátharmos.

###

nekrós
nekrói

###

Necro‑. Literally, “necro‑”. Still more literally, “dead” or “corpse”. Cognate of ‹necro‑›; related to the cognates of ‹necromancy›, ‹necrotic›. In older poetry, nekýs was instead used for the noun.

###

nekrozṓōs
nekrozṓioi

###

Literally, “living corpse”, combining nekrós, zōḗ. Still more literally, “undead”. Not quite alive, not yet dead; still hungry. Curiously, not the same as unliving, which is just dead. Contrast with: athánatos.

###

néktar
néktara

###

Nectar. Literally, “nectar”, combining nekrós, ‑tar. Still more literally, “death-defeating”. The divine, golden fluid created by the gods to store Their mánna. Refers also to what bees exclusively survive on: an insectoid connection that chills the heart. Cognate of ‹nectar›.

###

Neoatlantís

###

Neo-Atlantis. Literally, “Neo-Atlantis”, combining néos, Atlantìs. Still more literally, “New Atlantis”.

###

neṓkoros
neṓkoroi

###

Neokoros. Literally, “neokoros”, combining naós, koréō. Still more literally, “temple sweeper”. A temple custodian; sactristan. It is a mundane, administrative job, distinct from priesthood. Cognate of ‹neokoros›, ‹neocorus›. See also: naophýlax.

###

néos
néoi

###

Neo‑. Literally, “neo‑”. Still more literally, “new” or “young”. No relation to ‹Neo›, ‹Mr. Anderson›. Cognate of ‹neo‑›.

###

níkē
nîkai

###

Nike. Literally, “nike”. Still more literally, “victory”. Not as easy as just doing it. Cognate of ‹nike›.

###

Nikoláion

###

Nikólaos, except gender-neutral or perhaps just diminutive.

###

Nikólaos

###

Nicholas. Literally, “Nicholas”, combining níkē, laós. Still more literally, “people’s champion” or perhaps “conqueror of people”. Even more literally, “victory of the people”. A nickname well-earned, and though it is only a prosonymía, I do not correct those who take it as an etymṓnymon — or, rather, the personal name that comprises part of it. For, in their understanding, my ónoma is Nikólaos Nikoláou — the son inheriting his father’s name. Cognate of ‹Nicholas›, ‹Nicholas Nicholson›. Contrast with: Míklos.

###

nitrogenḗs
nitrogeneîs

###

Nitrogen. Literally, “nitrogen”, combining nítron, génos. Still more literally, “niter-generated”. Cognate of ‹nitrogen›. See also: atmós.

###

nóei kalôs
noeîte kalôs

###

Literally, “perceive well”, combining noûs, kalôs. Still more literally, “think beautifully”. An instruction to take careful note; akin to ‹nota bene›. Related to the cognates of ‹calligraphy›, ‹calisthenics›.

###

noerā́igis
noeraíges

###

Literally, “mind shield” or “thought shield”, combining noûs, aigís. So long as you can maintain this, your etymṓnymon might as well be “Nobody”.

###

nomikḗ

###

Literally, “law”, “custom”, “jurisprudence”. No, no relation to ‹mike›. Related to the cognates of ‹autonomy›, ‹metronome›, ‹Deuteronomy›, ‹economics›. See also: paidéia árkanos, díkē, astronomía.

###

nómisma
nómismata

###

Numism‑. Literally, “numism‑”, referencing nomikḗ. Still more literally, “coin”. Minted in copper, bronze, silver, electrum, or gold. From lowest to highest value: leptón, chalkoûs, tetartēmórion, hēmiōbólion, obolós, dióbolon, drachmḗ, dídrachmon, tetrádrachmon, statḗr, dekádrachmon. Note that this is the system used for everyday transactions; another system applies to trade and regional commerce. Cognate of ‹numism‑›; related to the cognates of ‹numismatics›, ‹numismatology›.

###

noûs
noés

###

Nous. Literally, “nous”. Still more literally, “mind”, “intellect”, or “thinking”. The rational part of the psychḗ. Cognate of ‹nous›; related to the cognate of ‹noetic›, ‹paranoia›. See also: énnoia, nóei kalôs, noerā́igis.

###

numbers

###

See: heîs, dýo, treîs, téttares, pénte, héx, heptá, oktṓ, ennéa, déka, héndeka, dṓdeka.

###

nýx
nýktes

###

Literally, “night”. Personified by the poets as mother of Hýpnos and perhaps even Thánatos. Cognate of ‹night›; related to the cognates of ‹nyctalopia›, ‹nyctophobia›, ‹nocturnal›. See also: times.

###

ô méga

###

Omega. Literally, “omega”. Still more literally “big o”, referencing mégas. In contrast with the “small o” of «ò mikrón», which is to say, ‹omicron›. This grámma, shaped like an omega, is the last in the álphabētos; hence, it denotes the ending. Should this not, therefore, be the last entry in the glossary? While we’re at it, note also that zêta is the 6th letter, not the 24th or last: that would be absurd. Cognate of ‹omega›; related to the cognate of ‹O›. Contrast with: álpha.

###

obelískos
obelískoi

###

Obelisk. Literally, “obelisk”. Still more literally, “spit”, “skewer”, “four-sided pillar”. An upright, four-sided monolith that tapers until it reaches the pyramídion at its tip. For example: ‹Washington Monument›, ‹Saturn V Rocket›. Cognate of ‹obelisk›.

###

obolós
oboloí

###

Obol. Literally, “obol”, referencing obelískos, reflecting the early practice of using metal rods as currency. A silver coin worth a 6th of a drachmḗ. Cognate of ‹obol›.

###

ōidḗ
ōidaí

###

Ode. Literally, “ode”. Still more literally, “song” or “chant”. Cognate of ‹ode›. See also: tragōidía, kōmōidía, hýmnos, skólion.

###

oikeîos
oikeîoi

###

Literally, “housemate”, referencing oîkos. Metaphorically, “close relation”, perhaps even an extended relative who does not cohabitate. Refers only to family members, thus excluding oikétai.

###

oikétēs
oikétai

###

Literally, “household attendant”, referencing oîkos. Still more literally, “belonging to the household”. A live-in doûlos, hence a house slave. Provides domestic labor, including cleaning, cooking, child-rearing, companionship, and sexual services, as their owner desires. Contrast with: oikeîos.

###

oîkos
oîkoi

###

Oikos. Literally, “oikos”. Still more literally, “house” or “household”. The house itself and the people in it, and — even more metaphorically — the estate or family. Cognate of ‹oikos›, ‹oecus›; related to the cognates of ‹economics›, ‹ecology›. See also: oikeîos, oikétēs.

###

oinochóē
oinochóai

###

Oinochoe. Literally, “oinochoe”, combining oînos, chéō. Still more literally, “wine pourer”. A keramós pitcher, small enough to be carried around and poured with one hand. Cognate of ‹oinochoe›, ‹oenochoe›; related to the cognates of ‹oenophile›, ‹chyme›, ‹ecchymosis›.

###

oînos
oînoi

###

Oeno‑. Literally, “oeno‑”. Still more literally, “wine”. Cognate of ‹wine›, ‹oeno‑›, ‹oen‑›, ‹en‑›, ‹eno‑›; related to the cognates of ‹oenin›, ‹oenophile›.

###

oktṓ, oktás
okto‑, ógdoos

###

Octo‑. Literally, “octo‑”. In cardinal (“eight”) form, and then again in collective (“octad”), combining and ordinal (“eighth”) forms. No relation to ‹octroy›. Cognate of ‹octo‑›, ‹octa‑›, ‹oct‑›, ‹octad›; related to the cognates of ‹eight›, ‹October›. See also: numbers.

###

oletḕr
oletêres

###

Literally, “ruin-bringer”, referencing ólethros. Contrast with: prostátēs.

###

ólethros
ólethroi

###

Literally, “annihilation”, “destruction”, “devastation”. See also: oletḕr.

###

oloklērōménē theṓrēsē

###

Literally, “comprehensive consideration”, from “whole-portion god-sight”, hence oloklērōménē theṓrēsē, combining hólos, klēros, theós, horáō. A holistic view: an approach that breaks down the barriers that distinguish academic subjects. Related to the cognates of ‹holistic›, ‹theory›, ‹theater›.

###

Ólympos

###

Olympus. Literally, “Olympus”. The tallest mountain on Earth, known also as Kosmomphalós. Sacred to the high-reaching Titânes. Cognate of ‹Olympus›.

###

ṓn
óntes

###

Onto‑. Literally, “onto‑”. Still more literally, “being” or “existence”. Often a descriptor instead of a noun. Cognate of ‹onto‑›, ‹ont‑›. See also: ontología, ousía.

###

onokṓlē
onokṓlai

###

Onokole. Literally, “onokole”, combining ónos, kōlos. Still more literally, “donkey-rumped” or “donkey-legged”. An epítheton for émpousa. No relation to ‹onahole›. Cognate of ‹onokole›; related to the cognates of ‹ass›, ‹onager›, ‹onocentaur›, ‹colon›.

###

ónoma
onómata

###

Name. Literally, “name”. Can refer to the personal name (whether true or just a nickname), the full name, or anything in between, depending on context. In its entirety, consists of etymṓnymon ḗ prosonymía; patrōnymikós ḗ andrōnymikón ḗ despotṓnymon; diakritōnýmion ḗ kenón; dēmosṓnymon ḗ ethnoṓnymon. Cognate of ‹name›, ‹‑onym‑›; related to the cognates of ‹nomenclature›, ‹anonymous›. See also: appellation, hypokorismós, epítheton, epṓnymos, Name, pseudṓnymon.

###

ontología
ontologíai

###

Ontology. Literally, “ontology”, combining ṓn, logikḗ. Still more literally, “existence study”. Cognate of ‹ontology›. See also: ousía, kenón.

###

ophthalmós, ophthalmoí

###

Opthalmo‑. Literally, “opthalmo‑”, referencing ópsis. Still more literally, “eye”. Cognate of ‹opthalmo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹ophthalmology›, ‹opto‑›, ‹optic›.

###

ópion
ópia

###

Opium. Literally, “opium”. Still more literally, “juice” or “sap”. This katapraýntikós is epithetized as gála tês paparoúnēs. The heroic version is even better. Cognate of ‹opium›.

###

ópsis
ópseis

###

Optic. Literally, “optic”, referencing horáō. Still more literally, “sight” or “vision”. Metaphorically, “appearance”, “view”. Cognate of ‹optic›.

###

oreíchalkos
oreíchalkoi

###

Aurichalcum. Literally, “aurichalcum”, combining óros, chalkós. Still more literally, “mountain copper”. A particularly golden alloy of brass, yet only a fool would mistake it for gold. Cognate of ‹orichalcum›, ‹orichalc›, ‹orichalch›, ‹aurichalcum›, ‹chalcopyrite›; related to the cognate of ‹orology›. See also: Oreíchalkos Aiṓn.

###

Oreíchalkos Aiṓn

###

Literally, “aurichalcum aeon”, combining oreíchalkos, aiṓn. The Aurichalcum Age of opportunity.

###

orthographía
orthographíai

###

Orthography. Literally, “orthography”, combining órthros, graphís. Still more literally, “correct writing”. The aspect of written language concerned with spelling, punctuation, and other symbols in accordance with standard usage. Also refers to the orthographic system of a given léxis. For example, this document uses: plain text for concepts, with quotes like “this”; italics for words in koinodiálektos, with quotes in traditional eisagōgiká like «toûto»; plain text inside xenoeisagōgiká for ‹English›; and italics inside xenoeisagōgiká for ‹elliniká›, or as you call it, ‹Greek›. Cognate of ‹orthography›.

###

órthros
órthroi

###

Ortho‑. Literally, “ortho‑”. Still more literally, “pre-dawn” or “daybreak”. Even more literally, “stand straight” or “stand correctly”, referring to the Sun getting up. It brings with it hēṓs. Cognate of ‹ortho‑›, ‹orth‑›; related to the cognates of ‹orthodox›, ‹orthopedic›. See also: times, orthographía.

###

oryktón
oryktá

###

Orycto‑. Literally, “orycto‑”. Still more literally, “dug up”, hence minerals. No relation to ‹ore›. Cognate of ‹orycto‑›, ‹oryct‑›; related to the cognates of ‹oryctology›, ‹oryctognosy›, ‹oryx›, ‹orycteropus›, ‹oryctolagus›.

###

ostéon
ostâ

###

Osteo‑. Literally, “osteo‑”. Still more literally, “bone”. Cognate of ‹osteo‑›, ‹oste‑›, ‹oss‑›; related to the cognates of ‹ossify›, ‹osteopathy›, ‹ossuary›, ‹osteoblast›, ‹osseous›.

###

oú
oúk, oúch

###

Literally, “not”. Factual negation. The three versions are used before words with starting with a consonant, smooth breathing vowel, or rough-breathing vowel, respectively. No relation to ‹ouch›.

###

oúdeís, oúdemía
oúdén

###

Literally, “no one” or “no thing”, combining oú, heîs. In masculine, feminine, and neuter forms.

###

oudéteron
oudétera

###

Literally, “neuter” or “neutral”, combining oú, dé, héteros. Still more literally, “not either”. Can refer to grammatical or human gender. No relation to castration. Cognate of ‹neuter›, ‹neutral›.

###

Ouraníobos

###

Literally, “celestial bull”, combining ouránios, boûs. A monstrous chímaira: blue and dove-winged, though fortunately lacking a human head.

###

ouraniodoryphóron
Ouraniodoryphóra

###

Literally, “heavenly spear-carrier”, combining ouránios, doryphóros. Metaphorically, a celestial body which attends a larger one by orbiting it, including a natural one such as Selēnaîon over Antíchthōn. When capitalized and plural, refers specifically to the supernatural basileîai en toîs Ouranoîs.

###

Ouránion Epípedon

###

Literally, “the celestial plane”, combining ouránios, epípedon. The imaginary surface along which the Wanderers wander.

###

ouránios
ouránioi

###

Ouranian. Literally, “ouranian”. Still more literally, “heavenly”, “celestial”, or “of the Sky”; sometimes also metaphorically. Cognate of ‹ouranian›, ‹uranian›; related to the cognates of ‹uranology›, ‹Uranus›, ‹uranium›. Contrast with: hádeios. See also: Ouranoí, ouraniótheos.

###

ouraniótheos
Ouraniótheoi

###

Literally, “heavenly god”, combining ouránios, theós. Called also: Sun god.

###

Ouranoí

###

Literally, “the heavens”, referencing ouránios.

###

Ouróboros
ouróboros óphis

###

Ouroboros. Literally, “Ouroboros”. Still more literally, “tail devouring (snake)”. Cognate of ‹Ouroboros›, ‹Uroboros›; related to the cognates of ‹arse›, ‹ass›, ‹voracious›, ‹ophidian›.

###

ousía
ousíai

###

Ousia. Literally, “ousia”, referencing ṓn. Still more literally, “essence” or “substance”. Even more literally, “state of being”. Cognate of ‹ousia›. Contrast with: kenón.

###

outopía
outopíai

###

Utopia. Literally, “utopia”, combining oú, tópos. Still more literally, “no place”. Cognate of ‹utopia›; related to the cognates of ‹dystopia›, ‹topography›. The total opposite of eutopía, or is it? See also: parádeisos.

###

paidéia
paideîai

###

Paedia. Literally, “‑paedia”, referencing paîs. Still more literally, “education”. Cognate of ‹‑paedia›, ‹‑pædia›, ‹‑pedia›; related to the cognates of ‹encyclopedia›, ‹Wikipedia›, ‹pedagogy›.

###

paidéia árkanos

###

Literally, “hidden education”, combining paidéia, árkana. Arcane learning: the formal study of mageía. See also: iatrikḗ, nomikḗ, theología.

###

paidéia eleuthérōn

###

Literally, “free man’s education”, combining paidéia, eleútheros. A liberal arts education, suitable for the polítēs. See also: three literacies, four numeracies.

###

paidéia technikḗ

###

Literally, “technical education”, combining paidéia, technikḗ. Vocational training, suitable for the slave or laborer.

###

paîs
paîdes

###

Literally, “child”, “boy”, “girl”, “youth”, or “servant”. The specific meaning is, of course, obvious in context. Or, I suppose, you could specify arsenikós ḗ thḗleia, or even say koûros ḗ kórē, if they are youths. Related to the cognates of ‹paediatrics›, ‹pediatrics›, and certain other words that are best omitted.

###

pálē
pálai

###

Literally, “wrestling”. Still more literally, “throwing”. No relation to ‹pale›. Related to the cognate of ‹palaestra›. See also: machētḗs.

###

Paliggenesía
paliggenesíai

###

Palingenesis. Literally, “palingenesis”, combining pálin, génos. Still more literally, “rebirth” or “born again”. The end of Aiṓnios Stásis. Cognate of ‹palingenesis›; related to the cognate of ‹palindrome›. See also: Chrýseos Aiṓn.

###

panágathos
panágathoi

###

Literally, “all-good”, combining pâs, agathós. .

###

pankrátion
pankrátia

###

Pankration. Literally, “pankration”, combining pâs, krátos. Still more literally, “all strength”. The sport of unarmed combat uniting pygmḗ with pálē while adding techniques found in neither, such as kicks and chokes. Cognate of ‹pankration›. See also: machētḗs.

###

panoplía
panoplíai

###

Panoply. Literally, “panoply”, combining pâs, hópla. Still more literally, “all arms” or “all armor”. Full set of armor and weapons that a hoplítēs wears. Includes: dóry, xíphos, aspís, krános, thṓrax (or linothṓrax), knēmídes. Donned over chitônískos or exōmís, and under chlamýs. Cognate of ‹panoply›.

###

pantepóptēs
pantepóptai

###

Literally, “all-seeing”, combining pâs, ópsis.

###

pántheion
pántheia

###

Pantheon. Literally, “pantheon”, combining pâs, theós. Still more literally, “all gods”. The divine family composed of all of the gods under the same theogoneús. Also, a temple dedicated to one such sacred family. No relation to ‹panther›. Cognate of ‹pantheon›.

###

panthémistos
panthémistoi

###

Literally, “all-just”, combining pâs, thémis.

###

pantheoouranoktónos

###

Literally, “slayer of all heavenly gods”, combining pántheion, Ouraniótheoi, któnos.

###

pantognṓstēs
pantognṓstai

###

Literally, “all-knowing”, combining pâs, gnôsis.

###

pantokrátōr
pantokrátores

###

Pantocrator. Literally, “pantocrator”, combining pâs, krátos. Still more literally, “all-mighty” or “all-powerful”. Cognate of ‹pantocrator›. See also: pankrátion.

###

pará

###

Para‑. Literally, “para‑”. Still more literally, “beside”, “near”, “alongside”, “contrary to”. Cognate of ‹para‑›; related to the cognates of ‹paranormal›, ‹parallel›, ‹parody›.

###

parádeisos
parádeisoi

###

Paradise. Literally, “paradise”. Still more literally, “wall around (garden)”, through foreign influence. When capitalized, the mythical eutopía, associated simultaneously with Edém, Ēlýsion, Ouranoí, kaì Antíchthōn; essentially, anywhere other than here, hence outopía. Cognate of ‹paradise›.

###

parádoxon
parádoxa

###

Paradox. Literally, “paradox”, combining pará, dóxa. Still more literally, “contrary to expectation”. Cognate of ‹paradox›; related the cognate of ‹orthodox›.

###

paretymología
paretymologíai

###

Paretymology. Literally, “paretymology”, combining pará, étymon, logikḗ. False etymology, including folk etymology and false cognates. As you can see, I strictly avoid this! Cognate of ‹paretymology›.

###

parōidía
parōidíai

###

Parody. Literally, “parody”, combining pará, ōidḗ. Still more literally, “contrary song”. Specifically, imitation with an insulting twist. Cognate of ‹parody›.

###

partheneía

###

Partheno‑. Literally, “partheno‑”. Still more literally, “maidenhood”. The period of training in a girl’s life before she is initiated into the mystēria and becomes an adult. The details of this are known to all, except for men, who are left to guess and wonder. There is little to wonder about, though, as she learns mostly household skills and sacred songs. And there is, too, training in the arduous and painful plucking, singeing, and trimming of body hair. ‹IYKYK›. Equivalent to, though less formal — and, obviously, less important — than, ephēbeía. Cognate of ‹partheno‑›, ‹parthen‑›; related to the cognates of ‹parthenogenesis›, ‹Parthenon›.

###

pâs, pâsa, pân
pántes, pâsai, pánta

###

Pan‑. Literally, “pan‑”. Still more literally, “all”, “complete”, “every”, “everyone”, or “everything”. In masculine, feminine, and neuter forms, respectively, and then again in plural forms. No relation to ‹pan› or ‹pot›. Cognate of ‹pan‑›, ‹pant‑›; related to the cognates of ‹panorama›, ‹pandemic›, ‹panacea›, and all the rest: too numerous to list here.

###

patḗr
patéres

###

Pater. Literally, “pater”. Still more literally, “father”. No relation to ‹patter›. Cognate of ‹father›, ‹pater›, ‹patri‑›, ‹patro‑›, ‹patr‑›; related to the cognate of ‹patron›. See also: patrōnymikós, theopátōr, goneús. Contrast with: mḗtēr.

###

páthos
páthē

###

Pathos. Literally, “pathos”. Still more literally, “suffering”, “emotion”, or “experience”. Cognate of ‹pathos›; related to the cognate of ‹pathology›. See also: empátheia, sympátheia.

###

patrōnymikós
patrōnymikoí

###

Patronymic. Literally, “patronymic”, combining patḗr, ónoma. The possessive form of the father’s name, used as part of the full name. Cognate of ‹patronymic›.

###

peinaléos
peinaléoi

###

Penury. Literally, “penury”. Still more literally, “hunger”, “lack”, “poverty”. No relation to ‹paean›. Cognate of ‹penury›. Contrast with: plēthṓra.

###

peiratḗs
peirataí

###

Pirate. Literally, “pirate”. Still more literally, “(attack) attempter”. Like a lēstḗs, only on a boat, and as likely to enslave as rob. Despite harmful stereotypes, no relation to eyepatches, peg legs, or parrots. Aaarrr! Cognate of ‹pirate›.

###

pémpto stoicheîon

###

Literally, “fifth element”, combining pémptos, stoicheîon. It is aithḗr, the quintessence found only in the Heavens, hence forever out of reach. Traditionally, distinguished from earth, water, air, and fire. Now, the learned understand it to be aḗr ionisménos. And the wise understand it to be immediately fatal to the very same mortals who crave it.

###

pénte, pentás
penta‑, pémptos

###

Penta‑. Literally, “penta‑”. In cardinal (“five”) form, and then again in collective (“pentad”), combining and ordinal (“fifth”) forms. No relation to ‹pent›. Cognate of ‹penta‑›, ‹pent‑›, ‹pentad›; related to the cognates of ‹five›, ‹quintuple›, ‹pentagonal›. See also: numbers.

###

people

###

See: ánthrōpos, dêmos, éthnos, laós, prósōpon, thnētós.

###

péplos
péploi

###

Peplos. Literally, “peplos”. An elegant robe or shawl, worn by women and frequently depicted on goddesses. The large, rectangular sheet — usually woolen, though sometimes of linen, or even býssos — is artfully draped and fastened over the shoulders, folded over in an apóptygma, pinned with brooches, and cinched at the waist. Worn instead of the chitṓn, oft with perízōma kaì stróphion, and typically with a himátion. Sometimes, a sleeveless chitṓn replaces these undergarments, though that can get a bit too warm. Cognate of ‹peplos›, ‹peplus›, ‹peplum›.

###

perí

###

Peri‑. Literally, “peri‑”. Still more literally, “around”, “near”, “about”. No relation to ‹peri›. Cognate of ‹peri‑›; related to the cognates of ‹peripheral›, ‹perinatal›.

###

peripatētikós
peripatētikoí

###

Peripatetic. Literally, “peripatetic”, combining perí, patéō. Still more literally, “walking around”. Cognate of ‹peripatetic›.

###

perízōma
perízōmata

###

Perizoma. Literally, “perizoma”, combining perí, zṓnē. Still more literally, “belted around”. A loincloth or girdle wrapped around the waist and groin, worn either under the chitṓn or on its own, as in athletics. Cognate of ‹perizoma›.

###

pétasos
pétasoi

###

Petasos. Literally, “petasos”. Still more literally, “spread out”. A broad-brimmed, rounded hat, oft with a chin strap or ties to keep it from flying off in the wind. A woman’s has a high crown while a man’s is lower. Worn, stereotypically, by travelers, farmers, and shepherds. No wings, though. Cognate of ‹petasos›, ‹petasus›.

###

petteía
petteîai

###

Petteia. Literally, “petteia”. Still more literally, “pebble”. Epithetized as the game of stones, the timeless board game involves the strategic movement of pieces on a grid to surround and capture the enemy’s. A game of pure skill, one may learn the rules in an afternoon, yet it takes a lifetime — or longer — to master. Play is oft spiced with wager, leading to the saying: “In the game of stones, you win or you’re impoverished”. Cognate of ‹petteia›; related to the cognates of ‹petrification›, ‹Peter›.

###

phagós
phagoí

###

Phage. Literally, “phage”. Still more literally, “eater”, or even “glutton”. Cognate of ‹phage›, ‹phago‑›, ‹‑phage›. See also: anthrōpophágos, mageiophágos.

###

phallós
phalloí

###

Phallus. Literally, “phallus”. This speaks for itself. Cognate of ‹phallus›.

###

phantasía
phantasíai

###

Fantasia. Literally, “fantasia”. Still more literally, “vision”, “appearance”, or “imagination”. In the general context of mageíai, it is a goēteutikḕ phantasía: an illusion or glamor obscuring reality. In the specific context of tēlepátheia, it is the mental image or vision transmitted. No relation to eyesight. Cognate of ‹fantasia›, ‹fantasy›; related to the cognates of ‹phantasm›, ‹phantom›, ‹fantastic›.

###

phármakon
phármaka

###

Pharmaceutical. Literally, “pharmaceutical”. A medicine, drug, or poison. Cognate of ‹pharmaceutical›. See also: potón, phíltron.

###

philíā
philíai

###

‑Philia. Literally, “‑philia”. Still more literally, “friendship”. Brotherly love: reciprocal and chosen, based on mutual respect. Cognate of ‹‑philia›, ‹‑phile›, ‹‑phil›, ‹philo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹audiophile›, ‹philosophy›, ‹hemophilia›, ‹Philip›. See also: philóstorgos, philosophía.

###

philosophía
philosophíai

###

Philosophy. Literally, “philosophy”, combining philíā, sophía. Still more literally, “love of wisdom”. Cognate of ‹philosophy›.

###

philósophos
philósophoi

###

Philosopher. Literally, “philosopher”, referencing philosophía. Cognate of ‹philosopher›.

###

philóstorgos
philóstorgoi

###

Literally, “friendly natural affection”, combining philíā, storgḗ. Cultivated and intentionally expressed familial love, combining kinship and friendship.

###

phíltron
phíltra

###

Philter. Literally, “philter”, referencing philíā, from association with love potions and aphrodisiacs. A magical potón. Cognate of ‹philter›.

###

phlóx
phlóges

###

Phlox. Literally, “phlox”. Still more literally, “flame”, “blaze”. A thing of sublime beauty. No relation to ‹flux›. Cognate of ‹phlox›, ‹flame›, ‹flagrant›; related to the cognate of ‹conflagration›, ‹phlogiston›, ‹flammable›, ‹inflammable›. See also: pŷr.

###

phōnḗ
phōnaí

###

Phone. Literally, “phone”. Still more literally, “voice” or “sound”. No relation to phónos. Cognate of ‹phone›.

###

phónos
phónoi

###

Literally, “murder”, “slaughter”, “killing”. The more general term, it stands alone. No relation to phōnḗ. Contrast with: któnos.

###

phóros
phóroi

###

Phorous. Literally, “‑phorous”. Still more literally, “carrier”, “bearer”, or “bringer”. A word that carries quite a load. Cognate of ‹‑phorous›, ‹‑phorus›, ‹‑phora›, ‹‑phore›, ‹‑phor›, ‹‑ferous›, ‹‑fer›, ‹phoro‑›; related to the cognates of ‹phosphorus›, ‹conifer›, ‹metaphor›. See also: amphoreús, doryphóros, Doryphoroktónon, megalomyoxiphophóros, ouraniodoryphóron, phōsphóros.

###

phôs
phṓta

###

Photon. Literally, “photon”. Still more literally, “light”. Cognate of ‹photon›; related to the cognates of ‹phosphorescent›, ‹photograph›. See also: phōsphóros.

###

phōsphóros
phōsphóroi

###

Phosphorus. Literally, “phosphorus”, combining phôs, phóros. Still more literally, “light-bringer”, akin to ‹lucifer›. Generally, associated with Heōsphóros, and having connotations of enlightenment in both the literal and metaphorical senses. Specifically, refers to the stoicheîon, phosphorus, known for both glowing and burning. Cognate of ‹phosphorus›, ‹phosphorous›.

###

phrātríā
phrātríai

###

Phratry. Literally, “phratry”. Still more literally, “brotherhood”. A clan of polîtai, united by kinship. Cognate of ‹phratry›; related to the cognate of ‹fraternity›, ‹brother›.

###

Phthinóporon
phthinópora

###

Literally, “fruit wither”, combining phthínō, opṓra. The season of fall. Related to the cognates of ‹phthisis›, ‹opora›.

###

phylaktḗrion
phylaktḗria

###

Phylactery. Literally, “phylactery”, referencing phýlax. An amulet or protective charm. Cognate of ‹phylactery›.

###

phýlax
phylakḗs

###

Literally, “guardian” or “protector”. Related to the cognates of ‹prophylactic›, ‹phylaxis›. See also: politophýlax, naophýlax, phylaktḗrion.

###

phyllópemma
phyllopémmata

###

Phyllo. Literally, “phyllo”. combining phýllon, pémma. Still more literally, “leaf pastry”. A dough made into thin sheets, used in heavenly baklavás. No relation to philíā. Cognate of ‹phyllo›.

###

physikón
physikà

###

Physics. Literally, “physics”, referencing phýsis. Still more literally, “natural qualities”. Broader than ‹physics›, it encompasses all the natural sciences, yet arbitrarily excludes the supernatural science of mageía. Cognate of ‹physics›. See also: metaphysiká.

###

phýsis
phýseis

###

Literally, “nature”. See also: physikón.

###

pilídion
pilídia

###

Pileolus. Literally, “pileolus”, from pîlos. A skullcap. Cognate of ‹pileolus›.

###

pîlos
pîloi

###

Pileus. Literally, “pileus”. Still more literally, “felt” or “wool”. Even more literally, “compressed”, referencing how felt is made. A brimless cap, either conical or close-fitting, typically made of these materials. Akin to a toque or beanie. Stereotypically worn by sailors, travelers, and soldiers. No relation to ‹Pílos›. Cognate of ‹pileus›, ‹pilos hat›, ‹pilos helmet›. See also: pilídion.

###

pínax
pínakes

###

Pinax. Literally, “pinax”. Still more literally, “tablet”, “board”, “panel”, or “plate”. Essentially, any convenient flat surface. Cognate of ‹pinax›; related to the cognates of ‹pin‑›, ‹pinacotheca›. See also: kēropínax, pláx.

###

píthos
píthoi

###

Pithos. Literally, “pithos”. A very large keramós jar or storage vessel: a vat or cask. Typically characterized by a wide, round mouth and a flat bottom, it stands as tall as a man and is oft buried partially to keep cool. Note that — contrary to common mistranslations and misconceptions — neither is it a box, nor difficult to close once opened, nor a suitable place to sleep. Cognate of ‹pithos›. Contrast with: amphoreús.

###

planḗtēs
Planêtai

###

Planet. Literally, “planet”. Still more literally, “wanderer”. Collectively, the Wanderers. Traditionally, Gê was excluded on the basis that it was immobile, though this is patently absurd. Cognate of ‹planet›.

###

plásma
plásmata

###

Plasma. Literally, “plasma”. Still more literally, “molded” or “formed”. Refers to various distinct yet similarly moldable substances, the most relevant being aḗr ionisménos. Cognate of ‹plasma›; related to the cognate of ‹plastic›, ‹plaster›.

###

plateía
plateîai

###

Plaza. Literally, “plaza”. Still more literally, “broad” or “wide”. Generally, a pubic square, or flat, open space. Specifically, a broad road or avenue, typically running west to east, leading out from the agorā́. Cognate of ‹plaza›; related to the cognates of ‹plate›, ‹plateau›, ‹platypus›, ‹platform›, ‹Plátaia›. Contrast with: stenōpós. See also: pláx.

###

pláx
plákes

###

Literally, “flat surface” or “tablet”, referencing plateía. Can refer to a stone tablet, a flat expanse of land, or a sheet of metal or stone. No relation to ‹plaque›. See also: pínax.

###

plēktron
plēktra

###

Plectrum. Literally, “plectrum”. Still more literally, “striker”. In music, a pick used to play a kithára. In cooking, a pestle used with hólmos. Cognate of ‹plectrum›; related to the cognate of ‹pluck›.

###

plēthṓra
plēthôrai

###

Plethora. Literally, “plethora”. Still more literally, “fullness”, “abundance”, or “excess”. Cognate of ‹plethora›; related to the cognate of ‹plethysmograph›. See also: kéras tēs plēthṓras. Contrast with: peinaléos.

###

Ploiosṓtēr

###

Literally, “ship-saver”, combining ploîon, sōtḗr. Appellation of the sailors’ god, whose Eikṓn is the stylized anchor. Related to cognates of ‹soteria›, ‹soteriology›, ‹savior›.

###

pneûma
pneûmata

###

Pneuma. Literally, “pneuma”. Still more literally, “breath”, hence spirit or life force. Specifically, the vital essence that separates the living from the dead. Also used metaphorically. Cognate of ‹pneuma›, ‹pneum‑›, ‹pneumo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹pneumatology›, ‹pneumatic›. Contrast with: psychḗ. See also: áura.

###

poíēsis
poíēseis

###

Poiesis. Literally, “poiesis”. Still more literally, “creation” or “making”. Cognate of ‹poiesis›, ‹‑poiesis›, ‹‑poieses›; related to the cognates of ‹poetry›, ‹onomatopoeia›. See also: gês morphopoḯas, génos.

###

pólis
póleis

###

Polis. Literally, “polis”. Still more literally, “city-state”. The largest-scale political structure allowed by the gods since the end of the Golden Age, constituting a single city, its people, and its laws. Cognate of ‹polis›; related to the cognates of ‹policy›, ‹politics›, ‹metropolis›. See also: polítēs, politikón, politophýlax, Akrópolis.

###

polítēs
polîtai

###

Literally, “citizen”, referencing pólis. A man with full civil rights, privileges, and responsibilities, which includes the ability to vote, hold public office, and serve in legal and military functions. Naturally, this excludes women, children, dogs, and slaves, as well as apeleútheroi, bárbaroi, and other métoikoi. In other words, these are just those men who count, as it ought to be. Some relation to ‹Polítēs›. See also: phrātríā.

###

politikón
politiká

###

Politics. Literally, “politics”, referencing pólis. Cognate of ‹politics›.

###

politophýlax
politophýlakes

###

Literally, “citizen guardian”, combining polítēs, phýlax. City guard: volunteer militia for largely ceremonial purposes, such as guarding Prytaneîon.

###

polý

###

Poly. Literally, “poly”. Still more literally, “many”. Many. Many, many. Many, many, many. No relation to ‹Polly›. Cognate of ‹poly›, ‹poly‑›; related to the cognates of ‹polyandry›, ‹polygyny›, ‹polygamy›, and many, many more. See also the uses that follow, too numerous to list here.

###

polýchrōmos

###

Polychrome. Literally, “polychrome”, combining polý, chrôma. Still more literally, “many colors”. The style of painting buildings and statuary in bright shades and realistic skin tones. What a bland world it would be if all we had was white marble, no? Cognate of ‹polychrome›.

###

polýedron
polýedra

###

Polyhedron. Literally, “polyhedron”, combining polý, hédra. Still more literally, “many faced (3D geometric shape)”. A solid shape enclosing a volume and formed by many planar faces: at least four. No relation to ‹monohedron›, which is not a thing. And while ‹dihedron› and ‹trihedron› are things, or at least mathematical objects, neither is a polyhedron. Cognate of ‹polyhedron›. See also: tetráedron. Contrast with: polýgōnon.

###

polygamía
polygamíai

###

Polygamy. Literally, “polygamy”, combining polý, gámos. Still more literally, “many marriages”. Cognate of ‹polygamy›. Contrast with: monogamía.

###

polýglōttos
polýglōttoi

###

Polyglot. Literally, “polyglot”, combining polý, glôssa. Still more literally, “many tongues”. A multilingual person. On the one hand, the cultured necessarily learn a few languages; on the other, why should we bother with anything other than koinodiálektos? Should not we expect the foreigner to learn our tongue? Cognate of ‹polyglot›. Contrast with: monóglōttos.

###

polýgōnon
polýgōna

###

Polygon. Literally, “polygon”, combining polý, gōnía. Still more literally, “many angled (2D geometric shape)”. A planar shape enclosing an area and formed by many lines: at least three. While a polýedron necessarily has many gōníai, it is not a polygon, for reasons. The ‹monogon› and ‹digon› are not polygons because, on a flat plane, they are indistinguishable from a line; however, these concepts come in handy for pýlai, which depend on the bending of spacetime. No relation to ‹polygram›, ‹PolyGram›. Cognate of ‹polygon›. See also: trígōnon, tetrágōnon. Contrast with: polýedron.

###

polymorphía
polymorphíai

###

Polymorphism. Literally, “polymorphism”, combining polý, morphḗ. Still more literally, “many shaped”. The divinely-powered state of having the ability to wear multiple forms, each as like a garment, through polymórphōsis. Cognate of ‹polymorphism›.

###

polymórphōsis
polymorphṓseis

###

Polymorphosis. Literally, “polymorphosis”, combining polý, morphḗ. Still more literally, “many shape process”. The act of temporarily changing forms, without altering the true self. Can be self-directed, as with polymorphía, or external. Not nearly as painful as you might think. Cognate of ‹polymorphosis›. Contrast with: metamórphōsis.

###

polytheïsmós
polytheïsmoí

###

Polytheism. Literally, “polytheism”, combining polý, theós. Still more literally, “many gods”. Cognate of ‹polytheism›. Contrast with: monotheïsmós.

###

pompḗ
pompaí

###

Pomp. Literally, “pomp”. Still more literally, “send” or “escort”. A ritual procession or sacred ceremonial parade, as at a heortḗ. Circumstance is optional. No relation to ‹Pompeii›, ‹Pompey›. Cognate of ‹pomp›; related to the cognate of ‹pompous›.

###

póntos
póntoi

###

Pontus. Literally, “pontus”. Still more literally, “sea-path” or “bridge”, referring to the open sea. Cognate of ‹Pontus›; related to the cognates of Cognate of ‹pontic›, ‹pontoon›, ‹pontifex›. Contrast with: thálassa.

###

pórnē
pórnai

###

Porno‑. Literally, “porno‑”. Still more literally, “prostitute” or “whore”. Even more literally, “sold”. Apt, as it is indeed a form of commerce: sex work is work. Cognate of ‹porno‑›, ‹porn‑›; related to the cognate of ‹pornography›. See also: pornoboskós.

###

pornoboskós
pornoboskoí

###

Literally, “whore-herder”, combining pórnē, boûs, hence pimp. An appropriately vulgar term for a vulgar occupation.

###

potón
potá

###

Potion. Literally, “potion”. Refers to an ordinary drink, a phármakon, or even a goētikòn phíltron; these potables coming in various degrees of potency. Cognate of ‹potion›; related to the cognate of ‹potable›.

###

poús
pódes

###

Pod‑. Literally, “pod‑”. Still more literally, “foot”. The body part and the unit of length based upon it, which is approximately the size of a foot. No relation to ‹pod›, ‹pus›, ‹puss›, mḗtēr. Cognate of ‹pod‑›, ‹‑pod›, ‹‑pode›; related to the cognates of ‹podiatry›, ‹octopus›, ‹pedal›. See also: antípous, stádion.

###

pragmatismós
pragmatismoí

###

Pragmatism. Literally, “pragmatism”. Still more literally, “process of handling deeds”. Cognate of ‹pragmatism›.

###

praktikós
praktikoí

###

Practice. Literally, “practice”. Still more literally, “related to the act of doing”. More generally, practicality. Cognate of ‹practice›, ‹praxis›.

###

priesthood

###

See: archiéreia, archiereús, hiéreia, hiereús, hierarchía, hierobasileús.

###

prōïnós
prōïnoí

###

Literally, “morning”, “early”, or “breakfast”, referencing prôtos. Still more literally, “first time (of the day)”. See also: times.

###

prós

###

Pro. Literally, “pro”. Still more literally, “for”, “against”, “in addition to”, “toward”, “from”, “at”, “near”. Cognate of ‹pro›. See also: prôtos.

###

prosonymía
prosonymíai

###

Prosonym. Literally, “prosonym”, combining prós, ónoma. Still more literally, “additional name”. Nickname used in place of the etymṓnymon, oft based upon a hypokorismós. For people, this is what they are known as and commonly called, though not truly their name. For gods, used to avoid blasphēmía. Cognate of ‹prosonym›. Contrast with: pseudṓnymon. See also: epítheton.

###

prósōpon
prósōpa

###

Literally, “face” or “mask”, combining prós, ópsis, hence a role, persona, or individual person. Still more literally, “toward appearance” or “toward eyes”, referring originally to theatrical masks representing an individual character. Cognate of ‹persona›, ‹personal›. See also: people.

###

prostátēs
prostátai

###

Prostate. Literally, “prostate”, combining prós, stásis. Still more literally, “defender”, “protector”, “patron”. Even more literally, “stands in front”. Cognate of ‹prostate›. Contrast with: oletḕr. See also: phýlax.

###

prôtos
prôtoi

###

Proto‑. Literally, “proto‑”, referencing prós. Still more literally, “prime”, “first”, “original”, “primary”. Ordinal form of heîs. No relation to ‹Protoss› or ‹protoculture›, I think. Cognate of ‹proto‑›, ‹prime›, ‹primary›, ‹primal›; related to the cognates of ‹prototype›, ‹proton›, ‹Proto-Indo-European›. Contrast with: éschatos.

###

Prytaneîon
prytaneîa

###

Prytany. Literally, “prytany”. Still more literally, “foremost office”. City hall within Akrópolis, and home of Hestías Líthos. Cognate of ‹prytany›.

###

pseudomanteía
pseudomanteîai

###

Pseudomancy. Literally, “pseudomancy”, combining pseûdos, manteía. Still more literally, “false divination”. Cold reading, the trick of convincing someone you know what you know not. Some relation to ‹Pseudomantis›. Cognate of ‹pseudomancy›. Contrast with: nekromanteía.

###

pseudṓnymon
pseudṓnyma

###

Pseudonym. Literally, “pseudonym”, combining pseûdos, ónoma. Still more literally, “false name”. An alias someone hides behind, as out of cowardice or shame; for example, a pen name. Obviously, only the most despicable author would conceal their true identity. What do they have to hide?! Cognate of ‹pseudonym›. Contrast with: prosonymía.

###

pseûdos
pseúdē

###

Pseudo‑. Literally, “pseudo‑”. Still more literally, “falsehood” or “lie”. Cognate of ‹pseudo‑›, ‹pseudo›; related to the cognate of ‹pseudonym›. See also: pseudomanteía, pseudṓnymon, apatáō, dólios.

###

psychḗ
psychaí

###

Psyche. Literally, “psyche”. Metaphorically, “breath”, hence soul or consciousness. Specifically, the sentient essence that separates the aware from the unaware. Also used metaphorically. Cognate of ‹psyche›; related to the cognate of ‹psychosomatic›. See also: áura, noûs. Contrast with: pneûma.

###

psychología
psychologíai

###

Psychology. Literally, “psychology”, combining psychḗ, logikḗ. Still more literally, “consciousness study”. Too imprecise to be a science, too ugly to be an art; it is what it is. Cognate of ‹psychology›.

###

pygmḗ
pygmaí

###

Pugilism. Literally, “pugilism”. Still more literally, “fist”. The sport of boxing. No relation to ‹pygalgia› or the north star. Cognate of ‹pugilism›; related to the cognates of ‹pygmy›, ‹pugnacious›, ‹repugnant›. See also: machētḗs.

###

pýlē
pýlai

###

Pylon. Literally, “pylon”. Still more literally, “portal”, “gateway” or “entry”. In the context of the divine, a portal connecting two points in space for instantaneous travel, enabling tēlemetaphorá. Cognate of ‹pylon›; related to the cognates of ‹pylorus›, ‹Thermopýlai›.

###

pŷr
pyrá

###

Pyre. Literally, “pyre”. Still more literally, “fire” or even “fever”. Cognate of ‹pyre›, ‹pyro›, ‹pyro‑›, ‹pyr‑›; related to the cognate of ‹pyromaniac›: a hurtful term. See also: augḗ, kaíō, kapnós, lamprós, phlóx, spinthḗr, pyrokínēsis, pyromanía, pyromanteía, nekropyrā́, pyramís.

###

pyramídion
pyramídia

###

Pyramidion. Literally, “pyramidion”, referencing pyramís. Still more literally, “small pyramid”. The pyramidal capstone atop an obelískos or at the apex of a larger pyramid, typically of a more reflective material so as to catch the brilliance of the Sun. Cognate of ‹pyramidion›.

###

pyramidophthalmón
pyramidophthalmá

###

Literally, “pyramid eye”, combining pyramís, ophthalmós.

###

pyramís
pyramídes

###

Pyramid. Literally, “pyramid”. Still more literally «pŷr ámis», meaning “fire vessel”, or perhaps from foreign influence; the truth of it is buried in time. Note that a tetrágōnos pyramís does not mean a pyramid with four gōníai, which would perhaps refer to a tetráedron; rather, it is a pyramid whose base is a tetrágōnos, which would make it a square pyramid, having four trígōna atop this base. Cognate of ‹pyramid›, ‹pyramid-›, ‹pyramido-›,‹-pyramid›. See also: pŷr, pyramídion.

###

pyrēníon
pyrēnia

###

Pyrene. Literally, “pyrene”. Still more literally, “little stone”, “pit”, “kernel”. Can refer to the nucleus forming the core of the kýttaron. No relation to pŷr. Cognate of ‹pyrene›.

###

pyrokínēsis
pyrokínēseis

###

Pyrokinesis. Literally, “pyrokinesis”, combining pŷr, kínēsis. Still more literally, “fire movement”. The creation and control of glorious fire: an especially wonderful form of tēlekínēsis. Cognate of ‹pyrokinesis›. Contrast with: pyromanteía.

###

pyromanía
pyromaníai

###

Pyromania. Literally, “pyromania”, combining pŷr, maníā. An insulting term for the perfectly natural fascination one has with pŷr, augḗ, kaíō, kapnós, lamprós, nekropyrā́, kaì phlóx. Of course it is inspiring, yet there is no madness to its appreciation. Rather, any failure to duly appreciate its sublime beauty would be truly mad! This really ought not be a term at all. No relation to pyromanteía. Cognate of ‹pyromania›.

###

pyromanteía
pyromanteîai

###

Pyromancy. Literally, “pyromancy”, combining pŷr, manteía. Still more literally, “fire divination”. Soothsaying by gazing into flames; it is not only effective, yet also sublimely beautiful. There exist many variations, including kapnoskopía and thyoskopía. No relation to pyromanía, which really shouldn’t be considered an illness, by the way. Cognate of ‹pyromancy›. Contrast with: pyrokínēsis.

###

rhábdos
rhábdoi

###

Rhabdo‑. Literally, “rhabdo‑”. Still more literally, “rod”, “staff”, or “wand”. Refers to a variety of rod-like things, including cudgels. Cognate of ‹rhabdo‑›, ‹rhabdo›; related to the cognates of ‹rhabdovirus›, ‹rhabdomyolysis›.

###

rhētorikḗ
rhētorikaí

###

Rhetoric. Literally, “rhetoric”. Still more literally, “study of oratory”. Cognate of ‹rhetoric›. See also: three literacies.

###

rhís
rhînes

###

Rhino‑. Literally, “rhino‑”. Still more literally, “nose”. The most majestic of organs, and useful at that. No relation to Rhôs, I think. Cognate of ‹rhino‑›, ‹rhin‑›, ‹‑rhina›; related to the cognates of ‹rhinoceros›, ‹rhino›, ‹rhinoplasty›, ‹rhinencephalon›.

###

Rhôs

###

A man, and more.

###

sákcharon
sákchara

###

Saccharine. Literally, “saccharine”. Still more literally, “sugar”. Sweeter than honey, though not as complex in flavor. No relation to ‹Saks› or ‹Charon›, I think. Cognate of ‹saccharine›, ‹saccharose›. See also: sákcharon molýbdou.

###

sákcharon molýbdou

###

Literally, “sugar of lead”, combining sákcharon, mólybdos. A traditional sweetener made by heating vinegar in a lead vessel, yielding white crystals. Besides its taste, it acts also as a preservative, since it is rather toxic to mortals.

###

sandálion
sandália

###

Sandal. Literally, “sandal”. No relation to sand lion. Cognate of ‹sandal›.

###

sárōthron
sárōthra

###

Sarothrum. Literally, “sarothrum”. Still more literally, “broom”. Unwise to mix with goēteía, despite the temptation, for once begun, it may never stop. Cognate of ‹sarothrum›.

###

sárx
sarkós

###

Sarco‑. Literally, “sarco‑”. Still more literally, “flesh” or “meat”. Cognate of ‹sarco‑›, ‹sarc‑›; related to the cognates of ‹sarcophagus›, ‹sarcasm›, ‹sarcoma›, ‹sarcopenia›.

###

saurōtḗr
saurōtêres

###

Sauroter. Literally, “sauroter”. Still more literally, “lizard sticker”, referencing saûra. The butt spike of a dóry or xystón, providing balance, reinforcement, and utility. Adds a bit of heft to the spear while making it more wieldy, particularly with one hand. More commonly made of bronze or even brass than iron, as it allows the spear to be planted in the oft-damp ground, where iron might rust. Can be used as a secondary weapon if the spearhead breaks, or to deliver a finishing blow. Cognate of ‹sauroter›.

###

seasons

###

See: Cheimṓn, Éar, Théros, Phthinóporon.

###

seismiklýdōn
seismiklýdōnes

###

Literally, “seismic wave”, combining seismós, klýdōn. A surge spawned by an earthquake, hence a tidal wave or tsunami. Cognate of ‹seismic›.

###

Selēnaîon

###

Selene. Literally, “Selene”. Still more literally, “moon”. Even more literally, “bright”. The Moon, which attends Antíchthōn as its natural ouraniodoryphóron. Though, as it obviously has no gender, the word is neuter. Cognate of ‹Selene›; related to the cognates of ‹selenology›, ‹selenite›, ‹selenium›.

###

selēnótheos
Selēnótheoi

###

Literally, “moon god”, combining Selēnaîon, theós.

###

She

###

I mean Her.

###

She!

###

Obviously, I’m referring to Ekdikoúsa. Who else might I mean?

###

síderos
síderoi

###

Sidero‑. Literally, “sidero‑”. Still more literally, “iron”. Cognate of ‹sidero‑›, ‹sider‑›; related to the cognate of ‹siderite›. See also: métallon.

###

skià
skiaí

###

Skia‑. Literally, “skia‑”. Still more literally, “shade” or “shadow”. More specifically, a type of undead creature. A shade can be created through death while oathbound under hórkos, or due to a failed attempt at anástasis. Cognate of ‹skia‑›, ‹scia‑›; related to skótos and the cognates of ‹skiagraph›, ‹skiascope›. Contrast with: kêr. See also: skiamakhía.

###

skiamakhía
skiamakhíai

###

Skiamachy. Literally, “skiamachy”, combining skià, machētḗs. Still more literally, “shadow-fighting”. Metaphorically, shadow boxing or mock combat. Cognate of ‹skiamachy›, ‹sciamachy›.

###

skólion
skólia

###

Skolion. Literally, “skolion”. Still more literally, “drinking song”. Even more literally, “bent song”, for obvious reasons. These songs, common at sympósia, are oft improvised and satirical, with each singer taking their turn. Cognate of ‹skolion›, ‹scolion›; related to the cognate of ‹scoliosis›.

###

Skoteinòs Aiṓn

###

Literally, “dark aeon”, combining skótos, aiṓn. The Dark Age of decline.

###

skótos
skótoi

###

Scoto‑. Literally, “scoto‑”. Still more literally, “darkness”. Everyday darkness. No relation to ‹Scotland›, ‹Scoto‑›. Cognate of ‹scoto‑›; related to the cognates of ‹scotophobia›, ‹scotopia›, ‹scotoma›. See also: érebos, skià. Contrast with: zóphos.

###

skýphos
skýphoi

###

Skyphos. Literally, “skyphos”. A deep keramós cup with a flat bottom and a pair of horizontal handles near the rim. Not as fancy as a kýlix, yet still it serves to convey wine to its destiny. Cognate of ‹skyphos›, ‹skyphus›.

###

sôma
sṓmata

###

Soma. Literally, “soma”. Still more literally, “body”. No relation to the foreign term for néktar. No relation to phármakon. Cognate of ‹soma›, ‹soma‑›, ‹‑some›; related to the cognates of ‹somatic›, ‹chromosome›. See also: ánthrōposôma thērós, chromósōma.

###

sophía
sophíai

###

Sophia. Literally, “sophia”. Still more literally, “wisdom”, “skill”, or “cleverness”. No relation to ‹Loren›. Cognate of ‹Sophia› and related to the cognates of ‹sophisticated›, ‹sophistry›, ‹philosophy›. See also: sophós, Sophóglaux.

###

Sophóglaux

###

Literally, “wise owl”, combining sophía, glaúx. The Owl of Wisdom, appellation of the patron god of our epṓnymos pólis, whose Eikṓn is the stylized little owl. Another epítheton is She Who Stays Up At Night.

###

sophós
sophoí

###

Sophist. Literally, “sophist”, referencing sophía. Still more literally, “wise one”, hence scholar, academic, or philosopher. Cognate of ‹sophist›.

###

spárganon
spárgana

###

Literally, “wrapping bands”. Cloth used to cover or swaddle.

###

spáthē
spáthai

###

Spatha. Literally, “spatha”. Still more literally, “blade”. Refers primarily to a long, straight, double-edged broadsword favored by light cavalry for its reach and utility. May also refer to a variety of tools with broad, flat blades. Cognate of ‹spatha›; related to the cognates of ‹spathe›, ‹spatula›, ‹spade›, ‹spada›, ‹espada›, ‹epaulet›. Contrast with: kopís, xíphos.

###

sphaîra
sphaîrai

###

Sphere. Literally, “sphere”. Cognate of ‹sphere›.

###

sphínx
sphínges

###

Sphinx. Literally, “sphinx”. Still more literally, “strangler”. A monstrous chímaira: woman-headed, lion-bodied, and overly fond of grîphoi. Cognate of ‹sphinx›.

###

spinthḗr
spinthêres

###

Literally, “spark”. See also: pŷr.

###

spodós
spodoí

###

Spodo‑. Literally, “spodo‑”. Still more literally, “ash”. Cognate of ‹spodo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹spodomancy›, ‹spodium›, ‹spodumene›.

###

stádion
stádia

###

Stadium. Literally, “stadium”. Still more literally, “stand”, referring to a distance covered in a single stretch. The track where footraces are held and also the unit of length it is based upon, which is approximately 600 pódes. Cognate of ‹stadium›, ‹stade›.

###

stásis
stáseis

###

Stasis. Literally, “stasis”, referencing hístēmi. Still more literally, “stance”, “standing”, “standstill”. In addition to immobility, refers also to a state of civic strife and conflict stemming from a political standstill preventing consensus. Cognate of ‹stasis›, ‹static›. See also: Aiṓnios Stásis. Contrast with: metá.

###

statḗr
statêres

###

Stater. Literally, “stater”. Still more literally, “standard” or “weight”. A unit of weight, and therefore a coin of that weight. As a weight, twice that of a drachmḗ, which means that a silver statḗr is worth 2 drachmaí, making it equivalent to a dióbolon. A gold statḗr is worth 20 drachmaí, and one made of electrum is 12. Cognate of ‹stater›.

###

stenōpós
stenōpoí

###

Stenopos. Literally, “stenopos”, combining stenós, opós. Still more literally, “narrow path”. Specifically, a narrow street, traditionally running north to south. Cognate of ‹stenopos›; related to the cognate of ‹stenosis›. Contrast with: plateía.

###

stígma
stígmata

###

Stigma. Literally, “stigma”. Still more literally, “prick”, “puncture”, or “brand”. A mark on the skin, whether from a brand, a tattoo, or something similar. The connotations are neutral. Cognate of ‹stigma›.

###

stoicheîon
stoicheîa

###

Literally, “one of a series”, hence an element. Still more literally, “walk”. They are to énnoiai as grámmata are to léxeis. No relation to ‹stochastic›. Related to the cognate of ‹stoichiometry›.

###

stōïkismós
stōïkismoí

###

Stoicism. Literally, “stoicism”, referencing stoà. Still more literally, “porch”, for obvious reasons. No relation to ‹stochastic›. Cognate of ‹stoicism›.

###

storgḗ
storgaí

###

Literally, “natural affection”. Familial love: for some, it comes naturally and effortlessly; for others, less so. See also: philóstorgos.

###

stróphion
stróphia

###

Literally, “to twist”, referring to how it is wrapped. The breast band, a simple, supportive undergarment worn as needed for comfort and modesty. While quite comfortable, many women do not bother with them except when engaging in physical activity, although childbirth certainly changes things. Also known as apódesmos. Related to the cognates of ‹strophe›, ‹apostrophe›, ‹catastrophe›.

###

sympátheia
sympátheiai

###

Sympathy. Literally, “sympathy”, combining sýn, páthos. Still more literally, “feeling together”. Also used in more philosophical contexts to speak of the interconnectedness of all things. Cognate of ‹sympathy›; related to the cognates of ‹pathos›, ‹pathetic›, ‹pathology›. Contrast with: empátheia.

###

sympósion
sympósia

###

Symposium. Literally, “symposium”, combining sýn, potón. Still more literally, “drink together”, hence a banquet. It is a sophisticated drinking party filled with wealth, wit, and wine, typically held in the homes of the elite, and following closely on the heels of a deîpnon. Alas, it is by invitation only. Cognate of ‹symposium›. Contrast with: kapēleîon.

###

sýn

###

Literally, “together with”, “together”, or “with”. See also: sympátheia, sympósion, synekdochḗ, sýnesis, sýnthesis.

###

synekdochḗ
synekdochaí

###

Synecdoche. Literally, “synecdoche”, combining sýn, ekdochḗ. Still more literally, “understood together”. In rhētorikḗ, a figure of speech where a part is used to refer to the whole. Cognate of ‹synecdoche›.

###

sýnesis
synéseis

###

Synesis. Literally, “synesis”, combining sýn, híēmi. Still more literally, “throw together”. Coming to an internal understanding or gaining insight. Cognate of ‹synesis›.

###

sýnthesis
synthéseis

###

Synthesis. Literally, “synthesis”, combining sýn, thésis. Still more literally, “place together”. Composition or combination, resolving apparent contradictions. Cognate of ‹synthesis›.

###

technikḗ
technikaí

###

Technique. Literally, “technique”, referencing tektainō. Still more literally, “art”, “craft”, or “skill”. Even more literally, “weave”. Cognate of ‹technique›, ‹technical›. See also: paidéia technikḗ.

###

têi, tô
taîs, toîs

###

Literally, “to the”. The dative definite article, indicating the recipient, in feminine and masculine/neuter forms, respectively, and then again in plural. See also: the.

###

tektainō
tektainomen

###

Literally, “to build” or “to craft”. Related to the cognate of ‹technical›. See also: technikḗ.

###

têle

###

Tele‑. Literally, “tele‑”. Still more literally, “distant”. Cognate of ‹tele‑›, ‹tel‑›; related to the cognates of ‹telescope›, ‹teleport›. See also: tēlekínēsis, tēlemetaphorá, tēlepátheia, tēlephōnía, tēleórasis.

###

tēlekínēsis
tēlekínēseis

###

Telekinesis. Literally, “telekinesis”, combining têle, kínēsis. Still more literally, “distant movement”. Mind over matter, fueled by mánna; it moves or cuts or binds. And sometimes, it burns. Cognate of ‹telekinesis›. See also: pyrokínēsis.

###

tēlemetaphorá
tēlemetaphoraí

###

Teleportation. Literally, “teleportation”, combining têle, metá, phóros. Still more literally, “distant carrying across”. Instantaneous movement, as by a pýlē. Cognate of ‹teleportation›; related to the cognate of ‹metaphor›.

###

tēleórasis
tēleoráseis

###

Television. Literally, “television”, combining têle, ópsis. Still more literally, “distant vision”. Cognate of ‹television›. Contrast with: tēlephōnía.

###

tēlepátheia
tēlepátheiai

###

Telepathy. Literally, “telepathy”, combining têle, páthos. Still more literally, “distant feeling”. Communication, directly mind to mind, over great distance at the speed of light. What is shared can consist of énnoiai, léxeis, kaì phantasíai. Cognate of ‹telepathy›. See also: etymṓnymon.

###

tēlephōnía
tēlephōníai

###

Telephone. Literally, “telephone”, combining têle, phōnḗ. Still more literally, “distant sound”, hence it refers also to ‹radio›. Cognate of ‹telephone›. Contrast with: tēleórasis.

###

teletḗ
teletaí

###

Literally, “ceremony”, “rite”, or “ritual”. Still more literally, “completion”. See also: mystḗrion.

###

tḕn, tòn, tò
tàs, toùs, tà

###

Literally, “the”. The accusative definite article, applying to the object receiving the action of the verb, in feminine, masculine, and neuter forms, respectively, and then again in plural. No relation to déka. See also: the.

###

tḕn dýnamin tôn theōn

###

Literally, “the power of the gods”, combining tḕn, dýnamis, tôn, theós. Metaphorically, an epítheton for mánna.

###

tês, toû
tôn

###

Literally, “of the”. The genitive definite article, showing possession, in feminine, masculine/neuter, and plural forms, respectively. See also: the.

###

tetartēmórion, tetartēmória

###

Literally, “(one) fourth portion”, combining tétartos, mórion. Specifically, a silver (or sometimes even bronze or copper) coin worth ¼ of an obolós, hence a 24th of a drachmḗ.

###

tetrádrachmon
tetrádrachma

###

Literally, “four drachma”, combining téttares, drachmḗ. A coin of that value.

###

tetráedron
tetráedra

###

Tetrahedron. Literally, “tetrahedron”, combining téttares, hédra. Still more literally, “four-faced”. A pyramís with four triangular faces. Cognate of ‹tetrahedron›.

###

tetrágōnon
tetrágōnos

###

Tetragon. Literally, “tetragon”, combining téttares, gōnía, hence a quadrilateral such as a square, a rectangle, a rhombus, or a parallelogram. A four-sided polýgōnon. Cognate of ‹tetragon›. See also: pyramís.

###

tetragrámmaton
tetragrámmata

###

Tetragrammaton. Literally, “tetragrammaton”, combining téttares, grámma. Still more literally, “four letters”. Cognate of ‹tetragrammaton›.

###

téttares, téttara, téttares
tetra‑, tétartos

###

Tetra‑. Literally, “tetra‑”. In cardinal (“four”) masculine/feminine and neuter forms, respectively, and then again in collective (“tetrad”), combining, and ordinal (“fourth”) forms. No relation to fish. Cognate of ‹tetra‑›, ‹tetr‑›, ‹tetra›, ‹tetrad›; related to the cognates of ‹four›, ‹quarter›, ‹tetragonal›. See also: numbers.

###

thálassa
thálassai

###

Thallasso‑. Literally, “thallasso‑”. Still more literally, “sea”. Cognate of ‹thallasso‑›, ‹thallass‑›; related to the cognates of ‹thalassic›, ‹thalassocracy›, ‹thalassophobia›. Contrast with: póntos.

###

thalassaphrós
thalassaphroí

###

Literally, “sea foam”, combining thálassa, aphrós. Spume, foam, or scum. Related to the cognates of ‹aphrology›, ‹Aphrodítē›.

###

thalassobḗryllos
thalassobḗrylloi

###

Literally, “sea beryl”, combining thálassa, bḗryllos. Aquamarine: a semi-precious gem, transparent and sea-colored, with great strength and utility. Related to the cognate of ‹beryl›.

###

thalassoláros
thalassolároi

###

Literally, “sea gull”, combining thálassa, láros. Related to the cognate of ‹Larus›.

###

thalassoprásinos
thalassoprásinoi

###

Literally, “sea-green”, combining thálassa prásinos. Related to the cognate of ‹prasine›.

###

thanatomíasma
thanatomiásmata

###

Literally, “death taint”, combining thánatos, míasma. The indelible taint of forced anástasis. Contrast with: nekromíasma.

###

Thánatos

###

Thanatos. Literally, “thanatos”. Still more literally, “death”. The poets personify this all-too-natural phenomenon as the twin brother of Hýpnos, son of Nýx, and perhaps also of Érebos. Cognate of ‹thanatos›, ‹thanato‑›; related to the cognates of ‹thanatology›, ‹Thanos›. See also: athánatos, thnētós.

###

thaûma
thaúmata

###

Thauma. Literally, “thauma-”. Still more literally, “wonder” or “marvel”. Specifically, a divine miracle: the highest form of mageía. Cognate of ‹thauma‑›; related to the cognates of ‹thaumaturgy›, ‹thaumatology›.

###

thaumatomonopṓlion
thaumatomonopṓlia

###

Literally, “miracle monopoly”, combining thaûma, monopṓlion. The gods’ exclusive power to perform miracles, such as healing.

###

the

###

The definite article. See also: hē, tês, têi, tḕn.

###

théatron
théatra

###

Theater. Literally, “theater”. Still more literally, “beheld”. No relation to ‹Calculon›. Cognate of ‹theater›, ‹theatre›. See also: kōmōidía, tragōidía, drâma, prósōpon.

###

theía maníā

###

Literally, “divine madness” or “divine frenzy”, combining theós, maníā. Specifically, the supernatural trance state invoked in combat. More generally, any state of divinely-inspired madness or ecstatic frenzy, including the sort that drives someone to absurd literary aspirations that keep them awake all night meticulously editing a glossary that nobody will ever read.

###

thḗkē
thḗkaì

###

Theca. Literally, “theca”. Still more literally, “case”, “chest”, “receptacle”, or “sheath”. Cognate of ‹theca›; related to the cognate of ‹apothecary›.

###

thḗleia
thḗleiai

###

Literally, “female” or “feminine”. Still more literally, “soft” or “tender”. The defining attribute of gynḗ kaì kórē. Related to the cognates of ‹thēlitis›, ‹thylakoid›. Contrast with: arsenikós. See also: arsenóthēly.

###

thélēsis
thélēseis

###

Thelema. Literally, “thelema”. Still more literally, “will”. No relation to ‹Crowley›. Cognate of ‹thelema›.

###

thémis
thémistes

###

Literally, “justice”. Divine harmony and structure. Contrast with: díkē. See also: themistokrítēs.

###

themistokrítēs

###

Literally, “justiciar”, combining thémis, kritḗs. Still more literally, “divine law decider”.

###

theogoneús
theogoneîs

###

Literally, “godparent”, combining theós, goneús. Absolute ruler of a pántheion. Typically the divine parent of the junior members, having Ascended them, though sometimes promoted from among these godchildren due to the fading of the progenitor. When speaking of a specific god that is unambiguously male or female, either theopátōr or theomḗtēr is instead used.

###

theokratíā
theokratíai

###

Theocracy. Literally, “theocracy”, combining theós, krátos. Still more literally, “rule by the gods”. The gods obviously know what is best for all, no? Cognate of ‹theocracy›.

###

theoktónos
theoktónoi

###

Literally, “god-slayer”, combining theós, któnos.

###

theología
theologíai

###

Theology. Literally, “theology”, combining theós, logikḗ. Still more literally, “god study”. Take care, as not all gods like being studied. Cognate of ‹theology›. See also: paidéia árkanos.

###

theomachía
theomachíai

###

Theomachy. Literally, “theomachy”, combining theós, machētḗs. Still more literally, “battle of the gods”. A war against or among gods. Cognate of ‹theomachy›. See also: Titanomachía.

###

theomḗtēr
theomḗteres

###

Literally, “godmother”, combining theós, mḗtēr. A female theogoneús. Unrelated to the fairies, I think. Definitely unrelated to ‹thermometer›, and don’t even get me started on ‹Theotókos›.

###

theôn keraunós
theôn keraunoí

###

Literally, “divine thunderbolt”, combining theós, keraunós. One god and many are theoû kaì theôn. One bolt and many are keraunós kaì keraunoí .

###

theopátōr
theopátores

###

Literally, “godfather”, combining theós, patḗr. A male theogoneús. Unrelated to the mob, I think.

###

theophthalmḗs
theophthalmáis

###

Literally, “godseye”, combining theós, ophthalmós. The divine eye, rooted deep within the skull at the kōnárion. There is nothing particularly evil about it. See also: áura.

###

theós
theoí

###

Theo‑. Literally, “theo‑”. Still more literally, “god”. A celestial king. Cognate of ‹theo‑›, ‹the‑›; related to the cognates of ‹theism›, ‹atheism›, ‹theology›, ‹theosophy›. See also: ouraniótheos, chthoniótheos, selēnótheos, athánatos. Contrast with: ánthrōpos.

###

thḗr
thḗres

###

Thero. Literally, “thero‑”. Still more literally, “wild animal” or “beast”. Cognate of ‹thero‑›, ‹therio‑›, ‹ther‑›; related to the cognates of ‹Theria›, ‹therology›, ‹theromorph›, ‹theriomorphic›, ‹theriolatry›, ‹therianthropic›. No relation to Théros. See also: ánthrōposôma thērós, thēroképhalos.

###

thérmē
thérmai

###

Thermo-. Literally, “thermo-”. Still more literally, “heat”. Cognate of ‹thermo-›, ‹therm-›, ‹-therm›; related to the cognate of ‹thermal›, ‹endotherm›. See also: anathermāḗr, Théros.

###

thēroképhalos
thēroképhaloi

###

Literally, “animal-headed (man)”, combining thḗr, kephalḗ. See also: ánthrōposôma thērós.

###

Théros
thérē

###

Literally, “summer” or “harvest”, referencing thérmē. The season of summer. No relation to thḗr.

###

thēsaurós
thēsauroí

###

Thesaurus. Literally, “thesaurus”, “wordbook”, “synonymicon”, “antonymicon”, “compendium”. Still more literally, “treasure”, “container”, “storehouse”, “cache”, “repository”. No relation to ‹the lizard›. Cognate of ‹thesaurus›.

###

thnētós
thnētoí

###

Literally, “mortal”, referencing thánatos. Still more literally, “(capable of) dying”. Contrast with athánatos.

###

thṓrax
thṓrakes

###

Thorax. Literally, “thorax”. Still more literally, “breastplate”. A cuirass consisting of a breastplate and backplate. Typically made of bronze, although there is also the linothṓrax. An essential part of the panoplía of the hoplítēs. Only a fool goes into battle without one, and such a fool deserves to die. Cognate of ‹thorax›.

###

three literacies

###

See: grammatikḗ, logikḗ, rhētorikḗ. See also: paidéia eleuthérōn.

###

thrónos
thrónoi

###

Throne. Literally, “throne”. A hédra fit for basileús ḗ theós. Despite their glory, not entirely comfortable to sit in, and yet not easily escaped. Cognate of ‹throne›; distantly related to the cognate of ‹firm›.

###

thysía
thysíai

###

Thysia. Literally, “thysia”. Still more literally, “sacrifice” or “offering”. Typically, the burning of fat and bones and entrails on the bōmós, with the rest cooked and eaten by the worshipers. Sometimes, to appease angry gods, the entire animal must be burned to spodós; I omit the term for this out of tact. Cognate of ‹thysia›, ‹thusia›.

###

times

###

See: órthros, prōïnós, mesēmbría, hespéra, nýx.

###

tis
ti

###

Literally, “someone”, “something”, “anyone”, “any”. The indefinite pronoun, used also in various other forms with closely-related meanings. No relation to ‹tis›.

###

tísis
tíseis

###

Literally, “payback”, “retribution”, or “vengeance”. No relation to tis. See also: díkē.

###

Titán
Titânes

###

Titan. Literally, “Titan”. The first to Ascend to godhood, they are vast, powerful, and immense. Literally, or perhaps only metaphorically, huge. Cognate of ‹Titan›; related to the cognates of ‹titanic›, ‹titanium›, ‹titanolithic›. See also: titanikós, Titanomachía.

###

titanikós
titanikoí

###

Titanic. Literally, “titanic”, referencing Titán. Unrelated to near or far or wherever you are. Cognate of ‹titanic›. See also: mégas.

###

Titanomachía

###

Titanomachy. Literally, “titanomachy”, combining Titán, machētḗs. Still more literally, “battle of the titans”. The war in the Heavens that laid to waste the first-generation Titânes. Cognate of ‹titanomachy›. See also: theomachía.

###

Tólios

###

Tólios was the hypokorismós of a petty lēstḗs whose etymṓnymon was Antólios Iōánnou. An insignificant thug unworthy of further consideration, particularly as he is dead.

###

tópos
tópoi

###

Topo‑. Literally, “topo‑”. Still more literally, “place”. Cognate of ‹topo‑›, ‹top‑›; related to the cognates of ‹topography›, ‹topology›.

###

tragōidía
tragōidíai

###

Tragedy. Literally, “tragedy”, combining trágos, ōidḗ. Still more literally, “he-goat song”, for obvious reasons. A serious drâma about terrible events causing human suffering, evoking pity and fear. Cognate of ‹tragedy›. See also: kōmōidía, théatron.

###

trápeza
trápezai

###

Trapezoid. Literally, “trapezoid”, combining tetra‑, poús. Still more literally, “four-footed”. Generally, a geometric shape with four sides, only two of which are parallel. Specifically, a table or stand. Metaphorically, a money-changer. Cognate of ‹trapezoid›, ‹trapezium›; related to the cognates of ‹trapeze›, ‹trapezohedron›.

###

treîs, tría
triás, tri‑, trítos

###

Tri‑. Literally, “tri‑”. In cardinal (“three”) masculine/feminine and neuter forms, respectively, and then again in collective (“trio”), combining and ordinal (“third”) forms. No relation to ‹tree›, ‹Cheetos›. Cognate of ‹tri‑›, ‹trio›, ‹triad›, ‹tertiary›, ‹tierce›, ‹terce›; related to the cognates of ‹three›, ‹triple›, ‹triton›. See also: numbers.

###

triakontaekklēsía, triakontaekklēsíai

###

Literally, “congregation of thirty”, combining treîs, ‑konta, ekklēsía. Related to the cognate of ‹ecclesiastic›.

###

trígōnon
trígōna

###

Trigon. Literally, “trigon”, combining treîs, gōnía, hence a triangle. A three-sided polýgōnon. No relation to ‹Trigon›, I hope. Cognate of ‹trigon›; related to the cognate of ‹trigonometry›.

###

trípous
trípodes

###

Tripod. Literally, “tripod”, combining treîs, poús. Still more literally, “three-footed”. Metaphorically, it means divine support: for historical reasons. Cognate of ‹tripod›.

###

trochiodynamikḗ
trochiodynamikaí

###

Trochoid dynamics. Literally, “trochoid dynamics”, combining trochós, dýnamis. Still more literally, “wheel dynamics”, hence orbital dynamics. Related to the cognate of ‹trochoid›. See also: astronomía.

###

Wanderers

###

The Planêtai, none of whom are lost. See also: Asteroeideîs.

###

writing

###

See: epì tà laïá, boustrophēdón, epì tà dexiā́.

###

xenía
xeníai

###

Xenial. Literally, “xenial”, referencing xénos. Still more literally, “hospitality” or “guest-friendship”. A bedrock principle of civilization. Cognate of ‹xenial›, ‹filoxenía›.

###

xenoeisagōgikó
xenoeisagōgiká

###

Literally, “foreign introduction”, combining xénos, eisagōgiká. A quotation mark to indicate foreign words, using single angle braces for ‹English› or ‹elliniká›. See also: orthographía.

###

xénos
xénoi

###

Xeno‑. Literally, “xeno‑”. Still more literally, “foreigner” or “stranger”. Cognate of ‹xeno‑›, ‹xen‑›, ‹‑xene›; related to the cognates of ‹xenophobia›, ‹xenobiotic›. See also: xenía, métoikos.

###

xíphos
xíphē

###

Xiphos. Literally, “xiphos”. Still more literally, “sword”. A short, straight, double-edged sword with a leaf-shaped iron blade. While suitable for cutting and thrusting, it excels at the stabbing, making it ideal for infantry. Standard sidearm for hoplítēs, used always with aspís. Only a fool goes into battle with sword alone, and such a fool deserves to die. Contrast with: kopís, spáthē. Cognate of ‹xiphos›; related to the cognates of ‹xipho‑›, ‹xiph‑›, ‹xiphoid›.

###

xyrón
xyrá

###

Literally, “razor”. Still more literally, “scrape” or “shave”. Note that the phrase, «epì xyroû akmês» — “on the razor’s edge” — is an idiom equivalent to ‹on a knife’s edge›.

###

xystón
xystá

###

Xystum. Literally, “xystum”. Still more literally, “scrape”, relating to how it is made. A lance perhaps twice the length of a dóry, likewise with a saurōtḗr. Favored by cavalry as their primary weapon, while using the kopís or spáthē as the secondary, depending. Cognate of ‹xystum›, ‹xystus›, ‹xyst›; related to the cognate of ‹xyster›.

###

zōḗ
zōaí

###

Zoo. Literally, “zoo”. Still more literally, “life”. Specifically, as existence or vitality, and sometimes in reference to the divine. Cognate of ‹zoo›, ‹zoo‑›, ‹zo‑›; related to the cognates of ‹Zoe›, ‹zoea›. Contrast with: bíos.

###

zṓnē
zṓnai

###

Zone. Literally, “zone”. Still more literally, “belt”, “girdle”, or “cincture”. Metaphorically, a zone. Cognate of ‹zone›. See also: zōstḗr.

###

zóphos
zóphoi

###

Literally, “gloom”. Darkness that is oppressive, profound, and even supernatural. Contrast with: skótos. Cognate of ‹Zophos›.

###

zōstḗr
zōstêres

###

Zoster. Literally, “zoster”. Still more literally, “belt”, “girdle”. A type of wide zṓnē with both practical and symbolic purposes. Worn over a chitṓn: low-girdled around the waist by men, high-girdled under the breasts by women. Cognate of ‹zoster›.

###